INT	O
:	O
Part	O
4	O
,	O
interview	O
with	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
,	O
running	O
tape	O
17	O
.	O

Last	O
time	O
,	O
we	O
ended	O
in	O
--	O
on	O
your	O
account	O
of	O
your	O
meeting	O
with	O
the	O
policemen	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
.	O

I	O
remember	O
the	O
policeman	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
heavy	O
--	O
a	O
heavy	O
person	O
behind	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
put	O
his	O
hand	O
on	O
my	O
shoulder	O
.	O

I	O
turned	O
around	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
--	O
and	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
,	O
you're	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

You're	O
coming	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
that	O
,	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
you	O
are	O
too	O
familiar	O
.	O

I	O
took	O
off	O
his	O
hand	O
from	O
my	O
shoulder	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
we	O
didn't	O
feed	O
pigs	O
together	O
on	O
a	O
farm	O
.	O

If	O
you	O
want	O
to	O
address	O
me	O
,	O
be	O
polite	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
said	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
look	O
.	O

And	O
besides	O
this	O
,	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
I	O
am	O
not	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
please	O
do	O
me	O
a	O
favor	O
.	O

Fuck	O
off	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I	O
have	O
met	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

I	O
dispatched	O
them	O
to	O
hell	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
have	O
never	O
met	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
chutzpah	O
--	O
what	O
do	O
you	O
call	O
it	O
in	O
?	O

Such	O
a	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
Audacity	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

In	O
such	O
an	O
audacious	O
--	O
such	O
an	O
audacious	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I'm	O
not	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
--	O
and	O
I	O
think	O
you	O
should	O
get	O
lost	O
.	O

Look	O
at	O
my	O
satchel	O
that	O
I	O
was	O
--	O
I	O
was	O
carrying	O
a	O
Hessian	O
--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
Hessian	O
briefcase	O
,	O
packed	O
with	O
books	O
,	O
very	O
heavy	O
,	O
of	O
course	O
,	O
from	O
a	O
whole	O
week	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
under	O
the	O
books	O
.	O

There's	O
some	O
hand	O
grenades	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
are	O
people	O
with	O
me	O
,	O
behind	O
me	O
,	O
in	O
front	O
of	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
therefore	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
want	O
--	O
if	O
you	O
want	O
me	O
to	O
go	O
with	O
you	O
to	O
the	O
station	O
,	O
by	O
all	O
means	O
,	O
let's	O
go	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
can	O
assure	O
you	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
never	O
reach	O
the	O
station	O
.	O

You	O
will	O
lose	O
your	O
life	O
before	O
you	O
reach	O
the	O
station	O
.	O

We	O
don't	O
want	O
to	O
carry	O
out	O
executions	O
on	O
the	O
site	O
.	O

But	O
if	O
you	O
force	O
our	O
hands	O
,	O
can't	O
be	O
helped	O
.	O

Now	O
let's	O
go	O
.	O

Said	O
--	O
he	O
was	O
as	O
white	O
as	O
a	O
ghost	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
what	O
should	O
I	O
do	O
?	O

I	O
said	O
,	O
do	O
you	O
want	O
from	O
me	O
a	O
little	O
advice	O
?	O

I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
what	O
you	O
should	O
do	O
.	O

I'll	O
show	O
you	O
a	O
piece	O
of	O
paper	O
.	O

And	O
you	O
will	O
read	O
the	O
paper	O
,	O
and	O
you	O
will	O
salute	O
and	O
turn	O
around	O
and	O
go	O
away	O
.	O

What	O
should	O
I	O
tell	O
the	O
other	O
people	O
,	O
the	O
people	O
who	O
is	O
--	O
who	O
,	O
who	O
,	O
what	O
shall	O
I	O
tell	O
the	O
men	O
who	O
pointed	O
--	O
who	O
pointed	O
out	O
to	O
me	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
and	O
he	O
is	O
observing	O
us	O
?	O

Tell	O
him	O
that	O
I	O
am	O
a	O
Gestapo	B-ORG
officer	O
.	O

And	O
take	O
him	O
in	O
to	O
a	O
doorway	O
and	O
bloody	O
his	O
nose	O
that	O
,	O
that	O
he	O
embarrassed	O
you	O
so	O
much	O
.	O

He	O
went	O
away	O
.	O

I	O
should	O
say	O
that	O
,	O
but	O
I	O
was	O
shocked	O
as	O
never	O
before	O
,	O
the	O
first	O
time	O
I	O
was	O
recognized	O
as	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
I	O
realized	O
that	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
moment	O
of	O
a	O
bluff	O
which	O
succeeded	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
could	O
have	O
lost	O
my	O
life	O
,	O
and	O
my	O
friends	O
and	O
my	O
wife	O
never	O
--	O
nobody	O
would	O
have	O
known	O
where	O
my	O
remains	O
are	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
decided	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
that	O
eventually	O
,	O
eventually	O
I	O
will	O
be	O
recognized	O
,	O
because	O
the	O
war	O
was	O
not	O
going	O
to	O
be	O
over	O
overnight	O
,	O
in	O
a	O
few	O
days	O
.	O

And	O
sooner	O
or	O
later	O
,	O
somebody	O
will	O
recognize	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
not	O
every	O
policeman	O
will	O
be	O
such	O
a	O
fool	O
like	O
this	O
old	O
one	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
will	O
be	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
it	O
.	O

So	O
that	O
was	O
one	O
day	O
where	O
I	O
was	O
really	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
shocked	O
.	O

Then	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
my	O
friends'	O
flat	O
.	O

Of	O
course	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
over	O
for	O
two	O
days	O
--	O
for	O
--	O
for	O
two	O
days	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

I	O
didn't	O
tell	O
them	O
the	O
story	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
had	O
bad	O
news	O
.	O

The	O
news	O
was	O
that	O
my	O
wife	O
is	O
arriving	O
next	O
day	O
in	O
the	O
morning	O
.	O

She	O
would	O
arrive	O
next	O
day	O
in	O
the	O
morning	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
with	O
my	O
friend	O
Kubick	B-PER
,	O
that	O
she	O
was	O
thrown	O
out	O
from	O
her	O
safe	O
place	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
next	O
day	O
in	O
the	O
morning	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
,	O
I	O
found	O
out	O
what	O
happened	O
.	O

She	O
was	O
just	O
thrown	O
out	O
from	O
the	O
safe	O
place	O
given	O
to	O
her	O
,	O
arranged	O
for	O
her	O
by	O
the	O
leader	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
by	O
the	O
commander	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
for	O
the	O
whole	O
district	O
.	O

They	O
just	O
opened	O
the	O
door	O
and	O
told	O
her	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
we	O
don't	O
want	O
to	O
keep	O
you	O
anymore	O
.	O

You	O
go	O
to	O
the	O
Kubicks'	B-PER
with	O
your	O
friend	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
showed	O
even	O
how	O
to	O
go	O
there	O
,	O
this	O
way	O
.	O

They	O
didn't	O
rob	O
her	O
.	O

They	O
didn't	O
take	O
anything	O
from	O
her	O
.	O

They	O
,	O
they	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
paid	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
didn't	O
do	O
any	O
harm	O
to	O
her	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
told	O
her	O
,	O
we	O
don't	O
want	O
to	O
keep	O
you	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Who	O
were	O
these	O
people	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
These	O
people	O
are	O
--	O
were	O
forest	O
rangers	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
members	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

Their	O
daughter	O
was	O
working	O
at	O
the	O
post	O
office	O
.	O

And	O
she	O
was	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

She	O
was	O
the	O
liaison	O
--	O
the	O
liaison	O
officer	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
then	O
I	O
was	O
just	O
wondering	O
what	O
happened	O
.	O

That	O
much	O
I'll	O
talk	O
about	O
some	O
later	O
.	O

But	O
now	O
,	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
let	O
me	O
concentrate	O
on	O
my	O
wife's	O
arrival	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

It	O
happened	O
that	O
Kubick	B-PER
came	O
with	O
her	O
,	O
my	O
friends	O
from	O
Poland	B-LOC
came	O
with	O
her	O
to	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
where	O
he	O
has	O
family	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
family	O
agreed	O
that	O
they	O
will	O
take	O
her	O
in	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
moment	O
they	O
came	O
down	O
from	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
they	O
took	O
a	O
rickshaw	O
.	O

You	O
know	O
what	O
a	O
rickshaw	O
is	O
.	O

It's	O
a	O
bicycle	O
with	O
arrangements	O
for	O
two	O
people	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
luggage	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
rickshaw	O
--	O
young	O
rickshaw	O
man	O
,	O
they	O
gave	O
him	O
the	O
address	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
young	O
rickshaw	O
man	O
took	O
them	O
straight	O
to	O
the	O
police	O
station	O
.	O

He	O
immediately	O
recognized	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

At	O
the	O
police	O
station	O
,	O
my	O
wife	O
denied	O
that	O
she	O
is	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
they	O
ask	O
her	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
questions	O
of	O
,	O
of	O
the	O
Catholic	B-MISC
liturgy	O
.	O

And	O
she	O
answers	O
the	O
questions	O
very	O
well	O
.	O

And	O
--	O
but	O
they	O
still	O
insisted	O
that	O
she	O
is	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

The	O
man	O
in	O
charge	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
man	O
in	O
charge	O
,	O
he	O
says	O
that	O
--	O
that	O
she	O
is	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
he	O
told	O
her	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
you	O
came	O
--	O
you	O
,	O
you	O
--	O
and	O
he	O
started	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
to	O
check	O
what	O
she	O
is	O
wearing	O
around	O
to	O
--	O
a	O
body	O
check	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
found	O
--	O
he	O
found	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
dollars	O
,	O
gold	O
dollars	O
,	O
jewelry	O
,	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
dollars	O
,	O
bank	O
notes	O
,	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
money	O
,	O
a	O
lot	O
--	O
lot	O
of	O
money	O
,	O
thousands	O
of	O
dollars	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
she	O
is	O
very	O
--	O
he	O
had	O
put	O
everything	O
on	O
the	O
table	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
now	O
,	O
the	O
wife	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
husband	O
with	O
the	O
money	O
.	O

The	O
husband	O
is	O
already	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
then	O
the	O
husband	O
will	O
not	O
even	O
know	O
that	O
she	O
died	O
in	O
the	O
cellar	O
of	O
the	O
Gestapo	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
my	O
wife	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
I'm	O
not	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
secondly	O
,	O
the	O
Gestapo	B-ORG
will	O
not	O
prove	O
that	O
I	O
am	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
that	O
I	O
am	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

They	O
may	O
take	O
the	O
money	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
will	O
let	O
me	O
go	O
.	O

Again	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
well	O
,	O
what	O
should	O
I	O
do	O
?	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
let's	O
divide	O
it	O
.	O

She	O
made	O
a	O
mistake	O
.	O

She	O
was	O
--	O
she	O
--	O
and	O
divide	O
it	O
,	O
so	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
it's	O
all	O
right	O
.	O

So	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
divided	O
it	O
honestly	O
,	O
$	O
1	O
for	O
$	O
1	O
,	O
a	O
--	O
and	O
a	O
gold	O
coin	O
for	O
a	O
gold	O
coin	O
,	O
jewelry	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

His	O
half	O
he	O
put	O
immediately	O
into	O
the	O
drawer	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
from	O
--	O
he	O
took	O
her	O
--	O
because	O
she	O
had	O
some	O
local	O
money	O
,	O
probably	O
zlotys	O
.	O

He	O
took	O
about	O
400	O
or	O
500	O
,	O
no	O
,	O
1,000	O
zlotys	O
,	O
1,000	O
zlotys	O
,	O
which	O
was	O
about	O
$	O
3	O
,	O
$	O
2	O
or	O
$	O
3	O
,	O
$	O
2	O
or	O
$	O
3	O
and	O
left	O
them	O
on	O
the	O
table	O
.	O

He	O
called	O
in	O
two	O
policemen	O
and	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
[	O
SIGHS	O
]	O
this	O
young	O
lady	O
,	O
she	O
left	O
us	O
$	O
1,000	O
.	O

I	O
give	O
her	O
back	O
what	O
she	O
has	O
got	O
here	O
on	O
the	O
table	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
think	O
we	O
should	O
call	O
a	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
cab	O
--	O
a	O
cab	O
and	O
to	O
let	O
them	O
go	O
.	O

It	O
happened	O
also	O
that	O
in	O
the	O
other	O
room	O
,	O
they	O
investigated	O
Kubick	B-PER
.	O

And	O
they	O
thought	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

He	O
asked	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
questions	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
,	O
when	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
question	O
of	O
a	O
vesper	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
he	O
didn't	O
know	O
what	O
they	O
were	O
asking	O
.	O

And	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
they	O
told	O
them	O
to	O
let	O
his	O
--	O
his	O
trousers	O
down	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
realized	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
not	O
--	O
he	O
is	O
not	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
he	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
gentlemen	O
.	O

I	O
studied	O
to	O
be	O
a	O
priest	O
.	O

What	O
you	O
are	O
talking	O
about	O
,	O
the	O
name	O
of	O
the	O
vesper	O
may	O
be	O
used	O
in	O
another	O
--	O
may	O
be	O
--	O
may	O
be	O
--	O
may	O
be	O
--	O
may	O
be	O
--	O
used	O
somewhere	O
else	O
,	O
but	O
not	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
,	O
Galicia	B-LOC
or	O
not	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

They	O
immediately	O
had	O
the	O
suspicion	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
an	O
AK	B-ORG
officer	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
scared	O
of	O
him	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
let	O
--	O
they	O
called	O
then	O
a	O
cab	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
gave	O
an	O
advice	O
to	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
never	O
use	O
a	O
rickshaw	O
.	O

They	O
are	O
all	O
informers	O
.	O

Take	O
a	O
--	O
take	O
a	O
cab	O
with	O
an	O
elderly	O
driver	O
,	O
an	O
elderly	O
coach	O
driver	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
this	O
incident	O
.	O

We	O
came	O
--	O
we	O
discussed	O
the	O
matter	O
of	O
state	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

She	O
realized	O
that	O
she	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
go	O
out	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
people	O
--	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
family	O
of	O
my	O
friend	O
Kubick	B-PER
had	O
a	O
very	O
small	O
flat	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
impossible	O
to	O
make	O
a	O
hiding	O
place	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

That	O
means	O
she	O
would	O
have	O
to	O
live	O
open	O
.	O

And	O
with	O
her	O
looks	O
,	O
she	O
wouldn't	O
have	O
survived	O
a	O
single	O
day	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
decided	O
that	O
she	O
should	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
took	O
her	O
back	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
said	O
to	O
Kubick	B-PER
that	O
I	O
will	O
come	O
in	O
a	O
few	O
days'	O
time	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
was	O
shocked	O
with	O
this	O
incident	O
,	O
what	O
happened	O
before	O
with	O
the	O
policeman	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
my	O
friends	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
what	O
happened	O
to	O
my	O
wife	O
.	O

I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
what	O
happened	O
to	O
me	O
with	O
the	O
policeman	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
didn't	O
tell	O
them	O
before	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
way	O
of	O
surviving	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
for	O
me	O
would	O
be	O
to	O
join	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
and	O
to	O
go	O
around	O
the	O
city	O
in	O
company	O
of	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

I	O
know	O
how	O
they	O
operate	O
.	O

One	O
goes	O
ahead	O
.	O

They	O
never	O
go	O
two	O
people	O
together	O
.	O

Behind	O
is	O
one	O
and	O
one	O
is	O
in	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

They	O
keep	O
an	O
eye	O
on	O
each	O
other	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
they	O
walk	O
around	O
the	O
streets	O
of	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

I	O
speak	O
German	B-MISC
like	O
all	O
Germans	B-MISC
.	O

I	O
may	O
be	O
of	O
use	O
to	O
go	O
around	O
to	O
a	O
cafe	O
where	O
the	O
Germans	B-MISC
are	O
sitting	O
and	O
to	O
listen	O
to	O
their	O
conversations	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

I'm	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
want	O
to	O
join	O
official	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

They	O
didn't	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
so	O
happy	O
about	O
it	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
told	O
me	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
to	O
bring	O
up	O
the	O
matter	O
at	O
the	O
highest	O
level	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
shocked	O
me	O
.	O

Why	O
at	O
the	O
highest	O
level	O
?	O

A	O
young	O
man	O
speaks	O
German	B-MISC
,	O
he	O
doesn't	O
look	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
speaks	O
German	B-MISC
,	O
speaks	O
Polish	B-MISC
.	O

Why	O
should	O
it	O
be	O
a	O
question	O
of	O
contacting	O
the	O
highest	O
level	O
to	O
join	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
?	O

And	O
how	O
,	O
a	O
day	O
later	O
,	O
they	O
told	O
me	O
that	O
the	O
man	O
they	O
wanted	O
to	O
talk	O
to	O
is	O
--	O
he's	O
not	O
around	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
other	O
man	O
is	O
not	O
around	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
come	O
tomorrow	O
,	O
come	O
after	O
.	O

After	O
a	O
few	O
days	O
,	O
I	O
asked	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
tell	O
me	O
the	O
truth	O
.	O

They	O
told	O
me	O
that	O
the	O
truth	O
is	O
truth	O
is	O
that	O
AK	B-ORG
is	O
not	O
taking	O
in	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

They	O
have	O
got	O
a	O
few	O
Jews	B-MISC
here	O
and	O
there	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
show	O
--	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
create	O
a	O
kind	O
of	O
an	O
alibi	O
for	O
overseas	O
,	O
that	O
there	O
are	O
a	O
few	O
--	O
there	O
are	O
few	O
Jews	B-MISC
here	O
and	O
there	O
.	O

But	O
AK	B-ORG
doesn't	O
take	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Are	O
we	O
talking	O
about	O
1943	B-DATE
now	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
1943	B-DATE
now	O
,	O
is	O
that	O
the	O
year	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
--	O
no	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
1942	B-DATE
.	O

That	O
was	O
end	O
of	O
--	O
that's	O
December	B-DATE
'92	I-DATE
.	O

They	O
don't	O
take	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
it's	O
unfortunate	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
--	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
some	O
moneys	O
,	O
some	O
money	O
will	O
be	O
coming	O
in	O
for	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
because	O
there	O
are	O
some	O
Jews	B-MISC
connected	O
with	O
the	O
Delegatura	B-ORG
,	O
for	O
the	O
supporting	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

Look	O
,	O
a	O
part	O
of	O
it	O
will	O
go	O
--	O
a	O
part	O
of	O
it	O
will	O
go	O
to	O
those	O
people	O
to	O
distribute	O
amongst	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
are	O
in	O
hiding	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
--	O
but	O
the	O
most	O
of	O
it	O
will	O
be	O
swallowed	O
by	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

That	O
is	O
the	O
position	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
change	O
it	O
.	O

But	O
that	O
is	O
the	O
truth	O
and	O
the	O
whole	O
truth	O
.	O

We	O
talked	O
about	O
this	O
.	O

We	O
talked	O
later	O
on	O
with	O
--	O
we	O
were	O
drinking	O
Bimber	O
for	O
a	O
good	O
few	O
hours	O
,	O
talking	O
about	O
politics	O
,	O
Eisenhower	B-PER
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
in	O
Africa	B-LOC
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
in	O
such	O
a	O
case	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
go	O
.	O

I'll	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

I'm	O
not	O
--	O
I'm	O
not	O
--	O
I	O
can't	O
--	O
I	O
can't	O
work	O
the	O
city	O
.	O

I	O
lost	O
confidence	O
in	O
myself	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
work	O
the	O
city	O
force	O
anymore	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
that	O
.	O

Few	O
days	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
on	O
my	O
way	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
was	O
always	O
thinking	O
,	O
how	O
is	O
it	O
possible	O
that	O
my	O
wife	O
was	O
thrown	O
out	O
from	O
a	O
safe	O
place	O
,	O
from	O
a	O
safe	O
house	O
,	O
supplied	O
by	O
--	O
provided	O
for	O
her	O
by	O
the	O
commander	O
of	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
.	O

By	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
people	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
told	O
my	O
friends	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
if	O
he	O
is	O
such	O
a	O
pull	O
with	O
Jedrus	B-PER
,	O
why	O
doesn't	O
he	O
give	O
him	O
a	O
job	O
over	O
there	O
in	O
his	O
place	O
?	O

Didn't	O
like	O
it	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
was	O
thinking	O
about	O
Jedrus	B-PER
myself	O
.	O

What's	O
going	O
on	O
?	O

I	O
knew	O
that	O
he	O
was	O
an	O
antisemite	O
.	O

I	O
knew	O
that	O
his	O
father	O
was	O
an	O
antisemite	O
.	O

But	O
after	O
all	O
,	O
he	O
approached	O
me	O
.	O

I	O
didn't	O
come	O
--	O
I	O
didn't	O
come	O
to	O
him	O
begging	O
him	O
for	O
protection	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

He	O
offered	O
me	O
protection	O
.	O

He	O
offered	O
protection	O
for	O
my	O
wife	O
.	O

So	O
without	O
his	O
approval	O
--	O
I	O
was	O
thinking	O
without	O
his	O
approval	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
the	O
family	O
name	O
of	O
those	O
foresters	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

The	O
family	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
wouldn't	O
have	O
dared	O
to	O
open	O
the	O
door	O
.	O

At	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
do	O
Jan	B-PER
any	O
,	O
any	O
harm	O
.	O

That	O
means	O
it	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
instruction	O
of	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
How	O
do	O
you	O
explain	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O
And	O
I	O
was	O
--	O
beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
How	O
do	O
you	O
explain	O
this	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
But	O
I	O
didn't	O
--	O
I	O
thought	O
that	O
he	O
was	O
an	O
antisemite	O
,	O
and	O
his	O
father	O
was	O
antisemite	O
.	O

And	O
after	O
a	O
few	O
months	O
,	O
he	O
regretted	O
that	O
he	O
gave	O
a	O
safe	O
house	O
to	O
a	O
Jewess	B-MISC
.	O

He	O
regretted	O
.	O

But	O
he	O
didn't	O
want	O
to	O
do	O
any	O
,	O
any	O
harm	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
send	O
her	O
to	O
the	O
Kubicks	B-PER
.	O

The	O
Kubicks	B-PER
are	O
their	O
friends	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
take	O
care	O
of	O
her	O
.	O

And	O
don't	O
do	O
any	O
harm	O
to	O
her	O
.	O

That's	O
what	O
I	O
thought	O
.	O

What	O
I	O
didn't	O
know	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
--	O
I	O
mean	O
,	O
accusing	O
in	O
my	O
mind	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
,	O
Jedrus	B-PER
Jasinszki	I-PER
,	O
of	O
antisemitism	O
what	O
I	O
didn't	O
know	O
is	O
that	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
gave	O
her	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
safe	O
house	O
and	O
kept	O
her	O
there	O
,	O
disobeying	O
an	O
order	O
of	O
the	O
chief	O
,	O
of	O
the	O
commander	O
in	O
chief	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
for	O
the	O
whole	O
country	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
an	O
order	O
issued	O
by	O
General	O
Bor	B-PER
-	I-PER
Komorowski	I-PER
,	O
was	O
the	O
chief	O
commander	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
for	O
the	O
whole	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
the	O
order	O
was	O
number	O
116	O
,	O
issued	O
on	O
the	O
15th	B-DATE
of	I-DATE
September	I-DATE
1942	I-DATE
.	O

And	O
in	O
that	O
order	O
,	O
General	O
Komorowski	B-PER
,	O
Bor	B-PER
-	I-PER
Komorowski	I-PER
,	O
ordered	O
to	O
kill	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
escaped	O
from	O
ghetto	O
and	O
to	O
kill	O
Russians	B-MISC
who	O
escape	O
from	O
the	O
POW	O
camps	O
--	O
to	O
kill	O
Russian	O
POWs	O
who	O
escaped	O
from	O
the	O
camp	O
--	O
from	O
,	O
from	O
the	O
German	B-MISC
camp	O
,	O
and	O
--	O
but	O
in	O
the	O
first	O
place	O
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

Consequently	O
,	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
for	O
a	O
few	O
months	O
was	O
disobeying	O
an	O
order	O
of	O
his	O
commander	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
chief	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
after	O
a	O
few	O
months	O
,	O
he	O
decided	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
he	O
can't	O
go	O
on	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
being	O
a	O
soldier	O
and	O
disobeying	O
orders	O
.	O

So	O
he	O
--	O
he	O
certainly	O
issued	O
an	O
order	O
to	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
let	O
her	O
go	O
,	O
but	O
don't	O
do	O
--	O
don't	O
do	O
any	O
harm	O
.	O

Send	O
her	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
Kubicks	B-PER
.	O

That	O
was	O
my	O
explanation	O
later	O
when	O
I	O
learned	O
about	O
this	O
infamous	O
order	O
of	O
General	O
Bor	B-PER
-	I-PER
Komorowski	I-PER
,	O
the	O
--	O
from	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
the	O
reason	O
for	O
this	O
order	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
the	O
reason	O
for	O
this	O
order	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
To	O
get	O
rid	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

As	O
long	O
--	O
as	O
long	O
as	O
they	O
didn't	O
know	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
--	O
that	O
the	O
--	O
about	O
this	O
final	O
--	O
about	O
this	O
final	O
solution	O
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
do	O
any	O
harm	O
to	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

But	O
the	O
moment	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
started	O
mass	O
killing	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
want	O
any	O
Jews	B-MISC
to	O
survive	O
,	O
just	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

No	O
matter	O
what	O
Mr.	O
Feliks	B-PER
says	O
,	O
he	O
aren't	O
there	O
--	O
or	O
what	O
Tygodnik	B-MISC
Polski	I-MISC
say	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
they	O
would	O
be	O
--	O
they	O
,	O
they	O
would	O
be	O
happy	O
if	O
I	O
would	O
have	O
written	O
in	O
my	O
book	O
at	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
that	O
the	O
--	O
that	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
and	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
underground	O
,	O
they	O
all	O
were	O
like	O
the	O
Danish	B-MISC
.	O

The	O
--	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
evacuated	O
.	O

But	O
when	O
they	O
came	O
back	O
,	O
they	O
opened	O
the	O
doors	O
.	O

Their	O
flats	O
were	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
best	O
--	O
in	O
good	O
order	O
.	O

Flowers	O
were	O
prepared	O
for	O
them	O
.	O

You	O
see	O
,	O
they	O
would	O
--	O
I	O
mean	O
,	O
Mr.	O
Feliks	B-PER
from	O
the	O
Tygodnik	B-MISC
Polski	I-MISC
would	O
like	O
me	O
to	O
write	O
about	O
it	O
.	O

But	O
that	O
was	O
not	O
the	O
truth	O
.	O

The	O
truth	O
was	O
that	O
they	O
wanted	O
to	O
get	O
rid	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
there	O
are	O
documents	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
repeated	O
it	O
.	O

I	O
think	O
I	O
mentioned	O
this	O
earlier	O
.	O

There	O
are	O
documents	O
in	O
the	O
Yad	B-LOC
Vashem	I-LOC
stating	O
,	O
the	O
Delagatura	B-ORG
--	O
the	O
Delagatura	B-ORG
policy	O
was	O
that	O
Jews	B-MISC
should	O
not	O
come	O
back	O
to	O
their	O
,	O
their	O
homes	O
,	O
to	O
their	O
factories	O
,	O
to	O
their	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
their	O
trade	O
,	O
to	O
their	O
flats	O
.	O

If	O
they	O
come	O
back	O
,	O
they	O
will	O
be	O
treated	O
--	O
they	O
will	O
be	O
treated	O
like	O
invaders	O
.	O

It	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
a	O
restitution	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
will	O
,	O
will	O
force	O
them	O
out	O
,	O
will	O
keep	O
them	O
in	O
a	O
--	O
will	O
keep	O
them	O
in	O
a	O
closed	O
area	O
until	O
they	O
--	O
until	O
they	O
emigrated	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
position	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
question	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
question	O
of	O
,	O
as	O
you	O
mentioned	O
,	O
whether	O
they	O
were	O
alien	O
,	O
whether	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
they	O
considered	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
as	O
an	O
alien	O
element	O
.	O

The	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
were	O
not	O
--	O
were	O
,	O
were	O
not	O
worse	O
than	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
Hungary	B-LOC
,	O
than	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
Bulgaria	B-LOC
,	O
than	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
Czechoslovakia	B-LOC
,	O
than	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
anywhere	O
else	O
.	O

But	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
position	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
,	O
what	O
was	O
behind	O
the	O
thinking	O
in	O
--	O
what	O
was	O
behind	O
the	O
thinking	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
upper	O
echelons	O
in	O
agreeing	O
with	O
the	O
German	B-MISC
directive	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

It	O
just	O
an	O
occasion	O
,	O
an	O
occasion	O
to	O
get	O
rid	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
to	O
--	O
and	O
to	O
grab	O
their	O
--	O
their	O
houses	O
,	O
their	O
flats	O
,	O
their	O
factories	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
--	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
to	O
get	O
--	O
to	O
get	O
rid	O
of	O
a	O
minority	O
,	O
just	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
--	O
what	O
--	O
or	O
actually	O
,	O
where	O
--	O
where	O
did	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
as	O
an	O
underground	O
force	O
,	O
where	O
did	O
it	O
stand	O
in	O
the	O
spectrum	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
underground	O
forces	O
?	O

Was	O
it	O
left	O
or	O
right	O
?	O

Where	O
,	O
where	O
was	O
it	O
in	O
the	O
spectrum	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
.	O

That	O
--	O
and	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
mainstream	O
.	O

The	O
AK	B-ORG
was	O
the	O
mainstream	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
Socialist	B-ORG
over	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
people	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
people	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
--	O
this	O
was	O
the	O
mainstream	O
.	O

The	O
few	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
were	O
in	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
were	O
in	O
units	O
which	O
was	O
solid	O
--	O
which	O
were	O
exclusive	O
Socialist	B-ORG
units	O
--	O
PPS	B-ORG
unit	O
,	O
like	O
the	O
ALP	B-ORG
here	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Social	B-ORG
Democrats	I-ORG
unit	O
.	O

They	O
kept	O
a	O
few	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

The	O
only	O
--	O
the	O
only	O
underground	O
which	O
kept	O
Jews	B-MISC
was	O
Armia	B-ORG
Ludowa	I-ORG
.	O

That	O
was	O
a	O
Communist	B-ORG
underground	O
,	O
which	O
kept	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

You	O
see	O
,	O
even	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
many	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
many	O
memoirs	O
,	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
find	O
it	O
that	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
during	O
,	O
during	O
the	O
Uprising	B-MISC
,	O
when	O
people	O
came	O
out	O
and	O
they	O
wanted	O
to	O
join	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
told	O
them	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
not	O
keeping	O
,	O
so	O
you	O
go	O
to	O
the	O
Armia	B-ORG
Ludowa	I-ORG
.	O

They	O
make	O
the	O
--	O
they	O
may	O
take	O
you	O
in	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
--	O
we	O
don't	O
take	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
mainstream	O
under	O
the	O
Delegatura	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
the	O
Delegatura	B-ORG
was	O
the	O
delegation	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
government	O
in	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
government	O
in	O
exile	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
--	O
you	O
asked	O
what	O
was	O
the	O
reason	O
.	O

The	O
reason	O
was	O
just	O
to	O
grab	O
the	O
little	O
house	O
,	O
the	O
flat	O
,	O
the	O
little	O
factory	O
or	O
the	O
larger	O
factory	O
,	O
which	O
belongs	O
to	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
only	O
reason	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
there	O
any	O
other	O
underground	O
organizations	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
only	O
the	O
mainstream	O
organization	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
on	O
the	O
left	O
side	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
the	O
Armia	B-ORG
Ludowa	I-ORG
.	O

It's	O
the	O
Communist	B-ORG
one	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
accepted	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
then	O
on	O
the	O
extreme	O
right	O
,	O
was	O
NSZ	B-ORG
.	O

This	O
is	O
Narodowe	B-ORG
Sily	I-ORG
Zbrojne	I-ORG
.	O

Yeah	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
just	O
Hitlerites	B-MISC
.	O

Very	O
interesting	O
,	O
because	O
there	O
was	O
--	O
one	O
of	O
their	O
--	O
one	O
of	O
their	O
divisions	O
or	O
a	O
few	O
divisions	O
of	O
their	O
who	O
retreated	O
together	O
with	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
.	O

OK	O
.	O

And	O
yes	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
more	O
or	O
less	O
everything	O
.	O

NSZ	B-ORG
on	O
this	O
--	O
but	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
at	O
a	O
later	O
stage	O
,	O
NSZ	B-ORG
joined	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
under	O
Bor	B-PER
-	I-PER
Komorowski	I-PER
.	O

So	O
the	O
NSZ	B-ORG
became	O
part	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

INT	O
:	O
So	O
after	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
,	O
what	O
did	O
you	O
decide	O
to	O
do	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
After	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
and	O
--	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
,	O
came	O
back	O
by	O
train	O
,	O
by	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
my	O
friend	O
Kubick	B-PER
took	O
me	O
to	O
the	O
place	O
where	O
he	O
placed	O
my	O
wife	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
Kolonia	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
a	O
forest	O
,	O
just	O
a	O
clearing	O
in	O
a	O
forest	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
two	O
houses	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
went	O
by	O
night	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
cold	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
snow	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
cottage	O
,	O
a	O
small	O
cottage	O
.	O

The	O
family's	O
name	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
his	O
,	O
his	O
--	O
the	O
Christian	B-MISC
name	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
this	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
family	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

They	O
had	O
a	O
small	O
house	O
,	O
a	O
room	O
,	O
a	O
living	O
room	O
,	O
which	O
was	O
at	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
a	O
bedroom	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
kitchen	O
.	O

And	O
my	O
wife	O
was	O
there	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
they	O
have	O
--	O
they	O
had	O
a	O
few	O
--	O
they	O
had	O
two	O
sons	O
.	O

The	O
sons	O
were	O
--	O
were	O
transported	O
to	O
the	O
cow	O
shed	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
kept	O
my	O
wife	O
quite	O
open	O
,	O
but	O
inside	O
.	O

She	O
didn't	O
go	O
out	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

We'll	O
continue	O
next	O
tape	O
.	O

