INT	O
:	O
--	O
eight	O
with	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
.	O

Well	O
,	O
I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
why	O
it	O
was	O
.	O

It	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
'	B-DATE
24	I-DATE
.	O

The	O
reason	O
is	O
that	O
one	O
and	O
a	O
half	O
years	O
later	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
bloodless	O
putsch	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
this	O
year	O
.	O

He	O
went	O
with	O
his	O
soldiers	O
and	O
officers	O
of	O
the	O
parliament	O
and	O
sent	O
the	O
Endeks	B-ORG
packing	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
took	O
over	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
Prime	O
Minister	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
by	O
him	O
established	O
,	O
was	O
Mr.	O
Bartel	B-PER
,	O
Kazimierz	B-PER
Bartel	I-PER
.	O

He	O
promised	O
a	O
lot	O
.	O

But	O
this	O
Grabski	B-PER
business	O
died	O
with	O
,	O
with	O
this	O
putsch	O
,	O
anyhow	O
.	O

But	O
,	O
but	O
what	O
I	O
am	O
driving	O
at	O
to	O
say	O
is	O
that	O
antisemitism	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
was	O
instigated	O
by	O
the	O
government	O
,	O
by	O
leaders	O
of	O
the	O
antisemitic	O
parties	O
,	O
who	O
manipulated	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
population	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
has	O
always	O
been	O
the	O
case	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
was	O
there	O
any	O
--	O
in	O
your	O
view	O
,	O
was	O
there	O
any	O
role	O
played	O
by	O
the	O
Church	B-ORG
in	O
this	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
Church	B-ORG
was	O
always	O
anti-Jewish	O
.	O

The	O
reason	O
is	O
,	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
Church	B-ORG
,	O
that	O
the	O
dominated	O
elements	O
in	O
the	O
Church	B-ORG
were	O
the	O
village	O
priests	O
,	O
which	O
were	O
not	O
educated	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
really	O
ignorant	O
people	O
,	O
ignorant	O
people	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
,	O
they	O
believed	O
literally	O
in	O
what	O
was	O
written	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
Bible	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
they	O
kept	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
responsible	O
for	O
the	O
crucifixion	O
of	O
Christ	B-PER
.	O

They	O
did	O
whatever	O
they	O
could	O
--	O
they	O
did	O
whatever	O
they	O
could	O
to	O
incite	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
against	O
,	O
against	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

For	O
instance	O
,	O
Good	B-MISC
Friday	I-MISC
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
great	O
holiday	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
fast	O
.	O

But	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
the	O
same	O
as	O
,	O
as	O
Good	B-MISC
Friday	I-MISC
in	O
the	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
Protestant	B-MISC
countries	O
.	O

But	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
afraid	O
to	O
walk	O
the	O
streets	O
of	O
the	O
shtetl	O
or	O
even	O
--	O
or	O
even	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
especially	O
of	O
the	O
shtetl	O
.	O

Because	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
priests	O
incited	O
them	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
up	O
till	O
today	O
,	O
until	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
world	O
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
took	O
upon	O
themselves	O
,	O
according	O
to	O
Matthew	B-PER
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
took	O
upon	O
themselves	O
the	O
responsibility	O
for	O
the	O
blood	O
spilled	O
,	O
for	O
the	O
Christ	B-PER
blood	O
spilled	O
by	O
them	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
was	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
tension	O
,	O
tension	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
pleasant	O
atmosphere	O
.	O

But	O
again	O
,	O
again	O
,	O
I	O
would	O
say	O
the	O
population	O
,	O
as	O
such	O
,	O
was	O
not	O
very	O
much	O
moved	O
.	O

But	O
there	O
was	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
tension	O
.	O

The	O
trouble	O
is	O
that	O
it	O
was	O
Hitler	B-PER
who	O
brutalized	O
,	O
to	O
a	O
very	O
great	O
extent	O
,	O
the	O
whole	O
nation	O
.	O

But	O
up	O
till	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
up	O
till	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
I	O
couldn't	O
see	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
thing	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
surely	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
pogroms	O
.	O

In	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
,	O
there	O
was	O
the	O
pogrom	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
in	O
Radom	B-LOC
and	O
in	O
many	O
other	O
places	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
were	O
always	O
instigated	O
by	O
people	O
who	O
wanted	O
to	O
have	O
a	O
pogrom	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
people	O
were	O
--	O
the	O
people	O
were	O
very	O
--	O
very	O
easily	O
manipulated	O
when	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
question	O
of	O
looting	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
is	O
--	O
that	O
is	O
what	O
happened	O
in	O
Przytyk	B-LOC
in	O
1937	B-DATE
.	O

The	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
farmers	O
came	O
along	O
,	O
the	O
peasants	O
came	O
along	O
,	O
instigated	O
by	O
,	O
by	O
people	O
who	O
,	O
who	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
they	O
say	O
,	O
we'll	O
have	O
an	O
easier	O
life	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
they	O
will	O
have	O
an	O
easy	O
jobs	O
,	O
to	O
make	O
a	O
pogrom	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
,	O
and	O
to	O
loot	O
the	O
merchandise	O
in	O
the	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
marketplace	O
.	O

The	O
Jews	B-MISC
used	O
to	O
have	O
stalls	O
in	O
the	O
marketplace	O
with	O
merchandise	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
said	O
to	O
them	O
that	O
they	O
will	O
--	O
they	O
will	O
have	O
--	O
they	O
will	O
make	O
a	O
commotion	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
will	O
grab	O
whatever	O
they	O
could	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
never	O
realized	O
that	O
the	O
stall	O
owners	O
,	O
young	O
people	O
,	O
will	O
turn	O
around	O
and	O
will	O
organize	O
themselves	O
,	O
immediately	O
,	O
for	O
a	O
self	O
-	O
defense	O
in	O
Przytyk	B-LOC
From	O
the	O
stalls	O
,	O
they	O
grabbed	O
out	O
whatever	O
they	O
could	O
--	O
poles	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
started	O
to	O
defend	O
themselves	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
that	O
moment	O
,	O
the	O
people	O
ran	O
away	O
.	O

But	O
being	O
on	O
the	O
outskirts	O
of	O
Przytyk	B-LOC
they	O
were	O
turned	O
back	O
by	O
these	O
inciters	O
,	O
by	O
,	O
by	O
these	O
manipulators	O
,	O
including	O
Polish	B-ORG
police	I-ORG
.	O

Go	O
back	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
the	O
pogrom	O
started	O
.	O

They	O
came	O
back	O
,	O
right	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
started	O
to	O
kill	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
when	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
end	O
--	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
when	O
they	O
were	O
hitting	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
hitting	O
the	O
doors	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
trying	O
to	O
break	O
the	O
doors	O
of	O
one	O
house	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
,	O
upstairs	O
,	O
one	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

He	O
has	O
--	O
he	O
had	O
a	O
rifle	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
shoot	O
and	O
killed	O
a	O
Pole	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
with	O
that	O
moment	O
,	O
everybody	O
ran	O
away	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
no	O
more	O
pogrom	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
quite	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
killed	O
--	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
killed	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
prepared	O
a	O
case	O
for	O
the	O
court	O
.	O

The	O
court	O
was	O
in	O
Radom	B-LOC
.	O

A	O
famous	O
Jewish	B-MISC
journalist	O
and	O
sociologist	O
,	O
Jakob	B-PER
Jasinszki	I-PER
,	O
a	O
great	O
scholar	O
,	O
was	O
,	O
on	O
behalf	O
of	O
the	O
American	B-ORG
press	I-ORG
,	O
he	O
was	O
recording	O
this	O
trial	O
.	O

I	O
knew	O
him	O
very	O
well	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
what	O
happened	O
was	O
they	O
did	O
then	O
--	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
prosecution	O
said	O
that	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
made	O
the	O
pogrom	O
against	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
who	O
came	O
to	O
town	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
feed	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

Because	O
they	O
came	O
here	O
to	O
buy	O
the	O
goods	O
and	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
make	O
possible	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
could	O
make	O
a	O
living	O
.	O

And	O
instead	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
hit	O
by	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
people	O
,	O
one	O
family	O
--	O
one	O
who	O
,	O
who	O
,	O
who	O
killed	O
the	O
--	O
who	O
killed	O
the	O
Jew	B-MISC
and	O
his	O
wife	O
and	O
the	O
children	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
.	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
exactly	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
sentenced	O
to	O
a	O
few	O
months	O
,	O
some	O
months	O
of	O
imprisonment	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
quite	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
followers	O
,	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
followers	O
--	O
small	O
number	O
of	O
followers	O
,	O
who	O
were	O
sentenced	O
to	O
,	O
somehow	O
,	O
to	O
some	O
months	O
of	O
imprisonment	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
defended	O
themselves	O
were	O
sentenced	O
to	O
years	O
of	O
prison	O
,	O
many	O
years	O
of	O
prison	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
,	O
that	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
true	O
.	O

But	O
,	O
but	O
that's	O
not	O
--	O
that	O
was	O
in	O
1937	B-DATE
.	O

The	O
main	O
trouble	O
came	O
--	O
of	O
course	O
,	O
as	O
I	O
mentioned	O
to	O
you	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
instigators	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
Falangists	B-ORG
.	O

There	O
were	O
Endeks	B-ORG
.	O

There	O
were	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
had	O
a	O
Chrzescijanska	B-ORG
Demokracja	I-ORG
,	O
Christian	B-ORG
Democrats	I-ORG
.	O

A	O
Christian	B-ORG
Democrat	I-ORG
meant	O
that	O
Christian	B-MISC
democracy	O
,	O
that	O
democracy	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
is	O
only	O
for	O
Christians	B-MISC
.	O

That	O
is	O
what	O
they	O
said	O
of	O
--	O
what	O
they	O
said	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
we	O
want	O
democracy	O
,	O
but	O
only	O
for	O
Christians	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
not	O
only	O
Christians	B-MISC
,	O
only	O
for	O
Catholics	B-MISC
.	O

They	O
don't	O
want	O
for	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
and	O
so	O
on	O
,	O
only	O
,	O
only	O
for	O
Polish	B-MISC
Christians	I-MISC
.	O

But	O
the	O
main	O
problem	O
came	O
in	O
1934	B-DATE
.	O

Up	O
till	O
1934	B-DATE
,	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
antisemitism	O
here	O
and	O
there	O
.	O

The	O
Poles	B-MISC
still	O
behaved	O
decently	O
,	O
with	O
an	O
exception	O
of	O
the	O
,	O
of	O
the	O
instigators	O
.	O

But	O
in	O
1934	B-DATE
,	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
made	O
a	O
pact	O
with	O
Hitler	B-PER
.	O

And	O
too	O
,	O
it	O
said	O
that	O
Hitler's	B-PER
influence	O
on	O
Polish	B-MISC
politics	O
,	O
on	O
Polish	B-MISC
internal	O
politics	O
got	O
hold	O
.	O

Then	O
now	O
after	O
,	O
the	O
Falangists	B-ORG
,	O
they	O
all	O
started	O
openly	O
to	O
be	O
anti-Jew	O
,	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
pay	O
anti-Jewish	O
excesses	O
.	O

And	O
what's	O
more	O
,	O
the	O
government	O
did	O
not	O
say	O
no	O
.	O

Then	O
came	O
this	O
new	O
party	O
.	O

Pilsudski	B-PER
died	O
a	O
year	O
later	O
.	O

New	O
party	O
,	O
OZN	B-ORG
,	O
Obóz	B-ORG
Zjednoczenia	I-ORG
Narodowego	I-ORG
,	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
was	O
already	O
a	O
fascist	O
party	O
.	O

The	O
government	O
party	O
became	O
a	O
fascist	O
party	O
.	O

And	O
after	O
Przytyk	B-LOC
,	O
it	O
was	O
General	O
Slawoj	B-PER
Skladkowski	I-PER
,	O
who	O
officially	O
said	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
not	O
allow	O
any	O
pogroms	O
.	O

But	O
economic	O
boycott	O
is	O
pleasure	O
.	O

[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
yeah	O
,	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
but	O
how	O
do	O
you	O
say	O
in	O
Polish	B-MISC
?	O

[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

They	O
used	O
the	O
excuse	O
of	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
economic	O
boycott	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
means	O
it's	O
,	O
it's	O
accepted	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
that	O
time	O
they	O
tried	O
to	O
make	O
,	O
they	O
decide	O
to	O
really	O
implement	O
it	O
.	O

How	O
could	O
they	O
implement	O
it	O
?	O

How	O
could	O
they	O
have	O
implemented	O
it	O
?	O

The	O
only	O
way	O
was	O
to	O
bring	O
Polish	B-MISC
merchants	O
from	O
Pomerania	B-LOC
,	O
from	O
,	O
from	O
Poznan	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
this	O
western	O
part	O
of	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
where	O
there	O
always	O
were	O
antisemites	O
,	O
although	O
this	O
was	O
the	O
place	O
where	O
no	O
--	O
where	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
didn't	O
live	O
.	O

That's	O
very	O
important	O
.	O

The	O
antisemites	O
,	O
the	O
real	O
antisemites	O
,	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
came	O
from	O
the	O
western	O
part	O
of	O
Poland	B-LOC
--	O
Pomerania	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
Jews	B-MISC
didn't	O
live	O
there	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
organized	O
in	O
a	O
--	O
in	O
my	O
--	O
a	O
migration	O
of	O
Polish	B-MISC
merchants	O
,	O
from	O
Western	B-LOC
Poland	I-LOC
,	O
from	O
Pomerania	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
Galicia	B-LOC
and	O
to	O
all	O
other	O
parts	O
of	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
take	O
over	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
trades	O
,	O
Jewish	O
,	O
Jewish	O
,	O
Jewish	B-MISC
shops	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
they	O
did	O
it	O
with	O
large	O
credits	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
still	O
remember	O
,	O
in	O
my	O
,	O
in	O
my	O
,	O
in	O
my	O
town	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
two	O
cafes	O
.	O

They	O
opened	O
two	O
cafes	O
.	O

This	O
was	O
people	O
they	O
,	O
they	O
bought	O
from	O
Pomerania	B-LOC
,	O
from	O
Posen	B-LOC
,	O
from	O
Poznan	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
opened	O
two	O
cafes	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
first	O
time	O
a	O
cafe	O
put	O
up	O
a	O
sign	O
--	O
Jews	B-MISC
are	O
not	O
permitted	O
to	O
come	O
in	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
remember	O
,	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
just	O
bewildered	O
,	O
going	O
over	O
to	O
see	O
this	O
sign	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Huh	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
in	O
1937	B-DATE
,	O
193	O
--	O
end	O
of	O
1936	B-DATE
,	O
'37	B-DATE
.	O

1937	B-DATE
.	O

Either	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
this	O
,	O
this	O
cafe	O
,	O
this	O
restaurant	O
,	O
cafe	O
did	O
not	O
do	O
too	O
good	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
another	O
cafe	O
,	O
by	O
a	O
man	O
from	O
the	O
same	O
Pomerania	B-LOC
,	O
who	O
did	O
well	O
and	O
invited	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

I	O
used	O
to	O
go	O
there	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
my	O
client	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
my	O
client	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
--	O
we	O
,	O
we	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
we	O
did	O
all	O
,	O
all	O
the	O
legal	O
work	O
for	O
them	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Can	O
we	O
just	O
go	O
back	O
,	O
quickly	O
,	O
to	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
your	O
university	O
years	O
.	O

What	O
year	O
did	O
you	O
finish	O
university	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beginning	O
of	O
19	O
--	O
1936	B-DATE
,	O
middle	O
1936	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
you	O
mentioned	O
earlier	O
that	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
student	O
parties	O
was	O
from	O
the	O
far	O
right	O
.	O

Another	O
one	O
represented	O
Pilsudski's	B-PER
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
were	O
--	O
were	O
there	O
any	O
other	O
major	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O
Sanacja	B-ORG
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
there	O
any	O
other	O
major	O
student	O
parties	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
--	O
yes	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
peasant	O
party	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
were	O
quite	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
a	O
large	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
a	O
large	O
,	O
large	O
amount	O
of	O
them	O
.	O

Mostly	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
either	O
Sanacja	B-ORG
or	O
they	O
were	O
Endeks	B-ORG
,	O
or	O
they	O
were	O
Endeks	B-ORG
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
Sanacja	B-ORG
students	O
,	O
put	O
it	O
frankly	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
people	O
--	O
to	O
put	O
it	O
that	O
way	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
who	O
would	O
be	O
friends	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

They	O
were	O
mostly	O
opportunists	O
.	O

They	O
didn't	O
believe	O
that	O
the	O
Endeks	B-ORG
will	O
take	O
over	O
the	O
government	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
studied	O
at	O
the	O
university	O
,	O
thinking	O
that	O
being	O
Sanacja	B-ORG
,	O
being	O
the	O
organization	O
of	O
students	O
representing	O
,	O
represented	O
by	O
the	O
government	O
,	O
they	O
will	O
get	O
good	O
jobs	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
were	O
mostly	O
opportunists	O
.	O

So	O
it	O
was	O
--	O
this	O
is	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
party	O
which	O
they	O
created	O
later	O
,	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

That	O
means	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
non-party	O
bloc	O
supporting	O
the	O
government	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
all	O
opportunists	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
thought	O
that	O
being	O
with	O
the	O
party	O
,	O
being	O
with	O
the	O
party	O
of	O
the	O
government	O
,	O
they	O
will	O
have	O
better	O
jobs	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
be	O
better	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
get	O
a	O
better	O
loan	O
from	O
a	O
government	O
bank	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
students	O
organized	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
Jewish	B-MISC
students	O
were	O
organized	O
.	O

The	O
Jewish	B-MISC
students	O
,	O
we	O
organized	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
we	O
organized	O
most	O
--	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
Student	I-ORG
Union	I-ORG
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
officially	O
.	O

For	O
instance	O
,	O
m	O
this	O
beautiful	O
house	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
which	O
you	O
would	O
say	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
student	O
house	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
partly	O
,	O
quite	O
in	O
a	O
large	O
extent	O
,	O
funded	O
by	O
the	O
university	O
.	O

The	O
university	O
pays	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
money	O
for	O
helping	O
,	O
see	O
?	O

They're	O
helping	O
to	O
establish	O
it	O
.	O

They	O
couldn't	O
take	O
--	O
according	O
to	O
the	O
Constitution	O
,	O
they	O
couldn't	O
have	O
done	O
otherwise	O
.	O

Because	O
they	O
were	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
similar	O
houses	O
for	O
Catholics	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
there	O
were	O
similar	O
houses	O
for	O
Protestants	B-MISC
,	O
even	O
,	O
for	O
--	O
'	O
cause	O
,	O
'	O
cause	O
--	O
because	O
they	O
were	O
German	B-MISC
students	O
.	O

They	O
couldn't	O
say	O
that	O
they	O
will	O
not	O
give	O
some	O
money	O
for	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
students	O
.	O

So	O
that	O
meant	O
that	O
house	O
was	O
partly	O
funded	O
by	O
the	O
university	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
,	O
just	O
was	O
a	O
student	O
union	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
called	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
'	O
wreath	O
of	O
fire	O
.	O
'	O

[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
you	O
would	O
say	O
,	O
well	O
,	O
you	O
would	O
say	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
a	O
fire	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
you	O
involved	O
in	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
MV	O
:	O

Oh	O
yes	O
,	O
oh	O
yes	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
involved	O
,	O
but	O
not	O
in	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
involved	O
in	O
the	O
political	O
Zionist	B-ORG
parties	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
that	O
name	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
Zionist	B-ORG
--	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
after	O
the	O
second	O
year	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
invited	O
to	O
take	O
over	O
the	O
academic	O
--	O
the	O
university	O
students'	O
organization	O
,	O
called	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
revisionist	O
student	O
Jabotinsky's	B-PER
group	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
what	O
was	O
its	O
philosophy	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
its	O
philosophy	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Philosophy	O
was	O
,	O
it	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
Zionists	B-ORG
for	O
a	O
,	O
for	O
,	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
state	O
,	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
state	O
in	O
Palestine	B-LOC
,	O
for	O
a	O
large	O
Jewish	B-MISC
state	O
in	O
Palestine	B-LOC
,	O
against	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
immigration	O
,	O
the	O
immigration	O
--	O
against	O
the	O
English	B-MISC
prohibition	O
of	O
immigration	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
representing	O
Jewish	B-MISC
Jabotinsky's	B-PER
philosophy	O
at	O
the	O
campus	O
.	O

I	O
would	O
have	O
to	O
start	O
with	O
Jabotinsky's	B-PER
philosophy	O
altogether	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
,	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
--	O
Jabotinsky	B-PER
was	O
the	O
man	O
who	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
traveled	O
along	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
from	O
shtetl	O
to	O
shtetl	O
,	O
warning	O
Jews	B-MISC
that	O
the	O
catastrophe	O
comes	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
will	O
not	O
survive	O
the	O
next	O
war	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
Hitler	B-PER
rise	O
,	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
will	O
not	O
survive	O
that	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
went	O
.	O

He	O
made	O
--	O
he	O
went	O
at	O
--	O
he	O
made	O
him	O
an	O
agreement	O
with	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
government	I-ORG
,	O
because	O
England	B-LOC
did	O
not	O
allow	O
to	O
--	O
so	O
they	O
did	O
not	O
--	O
England	B-LOC
did	O
not	O
allow	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
to	O
migrate	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
Palestine	B-LOC
.	O

There	O
were	O
very	O
strict	O
quotas	O
.	O

Quota	O
was	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
certificates	O
or	O
visas	O
were	O
issued	O
through	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
agency	O
,	O
but	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
very	O
small	O
number	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
,	O
you	O
could	O
go	O
on	O
as	O
a	O
capitalist	O
,	O
with	O
5,000	O
pounds	O
or	O
$	O
5,000	O
--	O
I	O
don't	O
remember	O
the	O
amount	O
,	O
the	O
amount	O
of	O
money	O
.	O

And	O
besides	O
this	O
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
allow	O
anybody	O
to	O
go	O
in	O
,	O
to	O
go	O
in	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
he	O
makes	O
an	O
agreement	O
with	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
government	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
government	I-ORG
was	O
only	O
willing	O
to	O
help	O
Jews	B-MISC
go	O
to	O
Palestine	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
so	O
they	O
smuggled	O
him	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
through	O
Romania	B-LOC
into	O
Palestine	B-LOC
.	O

Because	O
in	O
Palestine	B-LOC
,	O
on	O
the	O
other	O
hand	O
--	O
when	O
they	O
,	O
when	O
he	O
arrived	O
in	O
Palestine	B-LOC
,	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
illegal	O
immigrant	O
when	O
he	O
arrives	O
there	O
,	O
he	O
didn't	O
need	O
any	O
papers	O
.	O

It's	O
like	O
here	O
and	O
England	B-LOC
,	O
you	O
don't	O
need	O
--	O
you	O
don't	O
need	O
any	O
papers	O
.	O

They	O
came	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
disappeared	O
in	O
the	O
kibbutzim	O
.	O

They	O
disappeared	O
amongst	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
amongst	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
population	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
people	O
were	O
sent	O
illegally	O
,	O
illegally	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
Palestine	B-LOC
through	O
the	O
Jabotinsky	B-PER
movement	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
state	O
at	O
the	O
time	O
,	O
when	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
agency	O
,	O
or	O
the	O
Zionist	B-ORG
--	O
the	O
main	O
Zionist	B-ORG
organization	O
,	O
they	O
said	O
that	O
they	O
would	O
be	O
willing	O
for	O
to	O
settle	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
entity	O
within	O
Palestine	B-LOC
.	O

Well	O
,	O
we	O
said	O
,	O
no	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
not	O
going	O
to	O
kill	O
--	O
not	O
going	O
to	O
kill	O
anybody	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
going	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
going	O
there	O
to	O
have	O
a	O
state	O
of	O
ours	O
.	O

And	O
now	O
,	O
this	O
was	O
more	O
or	O
less	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
Jabotinsky	B-PER
traveled	O
from	O
town	O
to	O
town	O
,	O
calling	O
on	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
1936	B-DATE
,	O
'37	B-DATE
,	O
'38	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Did	O
you	O
agree	O
with	O
that	O
prognosis	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
If	O
I	O
agreed	O
?	O

Of	O
what	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Did	O
you	O
think	O
the	O
same	O
way	O
,	O
did	O
you	O
think	O
that	O
the	O
disaster	O
might	O
come	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
same	O
way	O
.	O

I	O
thought	O
the	O
same	O
way	O
,	O
but	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
changed	O
my	O
mind	O
.	O

I	O
,	O
at	O
first	O
,	O
I	O
thought	O
that	O
we	O
--	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
to	O
stay	O
here	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
to	O
fight	O
for	O
our	O
,	O
for	O
our	O
rights	O
,	O
here	O
.	O

But	O
this	O
was	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
in	O
that	O
university	O
.	O

At	O
the	O
university	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
,	O
we	O
were	O
then	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
fighting	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	O
--	O
for	O
a	O
Jewish	B-MISC
state	O
against	O
the	O
English	B-MISC
restrictions	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
Palestine	B-LOC
.	O

Now	O
,	O
I	O
became	O
the	O
president	O
of	O
this	O
organization	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
I	O
wrote	O
in	O
my	O
book	O
about	O
it	O
--	O
that	O
Haim	B-PER
Landau	I-PER
came	O
to	O
see	O
me	O
,	O
that	O
I	O
should	O
take	O
--	O
so	O
Haim	B-PER
Landau	I-PER
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
went	O
to	O
Israel	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
became	O
later	O
,	O
as	O
you	O
have	O
maybe	O
heard	O
,	O
he	O
became	O
later	O
the	O
chief	O
of	O
staff	O
of	O
the	O
Irgun	B-ORG
during	O
the	O
war	O
against	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
,	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
this	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
Knesset	B-ORG
,	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
Parliament	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
later	O
a	O
minister	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
he	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
greatest	O
orators	O
in	O
Israel	B-LOC
,	O
this	O
Haim	B-PER
Landau	I-PER
.	O

So	O
he	O
came	O
to	O
me	O
together	O
with	O
another	O
delegation	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
I	O
didn't	O
remember	O
the	O
other	O
people	O
who	O
was	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
,	O
and	O
maybe	O
I	O
told	O
--	O
I'll	O
show	O
you	O
later	O
a	O
letter	O
from	O
an	O
English	B-MISC
writer	O
,	O
a	O
writer	O
in	O
London	B-LOC
.	O

Rafael	B-PER
here	O
--	O
Rafael	B-PER
Scharf	I-PER
,	O
Rafael	B-PER
Scharf	I-PER
.	O

He	O
was	O
in	O
this	O
delegation	O
just	O
the	O
same	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
he	O
went	O
to	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
lives	O
now	O
in	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
he's	O
a	O
--	O
he's	O
a	O
,	O
a	O
quite	O
a	O
known	O
--	O
a	O
well	O
-	O
known	O
writer	O
and	O
intellectual	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
book	O
,	O
written	O
by	O
Anne	B-PER
Karpf	I-PER
.	O

Maybe	O
you	O
have	O
seen	O
it	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
seen	O
this	O
book	O
.	O

I	O
got	O
this	O
book	O
from	O
the	O
library	O
.	O

This	O
book	O
is	O
called	O
Another	B-MISC
War	I-MISC
.	O

It	O
is	O
written	O
by	O
Anne	B-PER
Karpf	I-PER
.	O

She	O
is	O
a	O
columnist	O
at	O
The	B-MISC
Guardian	I-MISC
,	O
Guardian	B-MISC
columnist	O
,	O
an	O
intellectual	O
.	O

And	O
she	O
was	O
a	O
child	O
of	O
survivors	O
.	O

Her	O
mother	O
was	O
a	O
concert	O
pianist	O
in	O
Berlin	B-LOC
,	O
Philadelphia	B-LOC
--	O
in	O
the	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
Berlin	B-ORG
Symphony	I-ORG
Orchestra	I-ORG
.	O

Her	O
father	O
was	O
a	O
the	O
consular	O
at	O
the	O
embassy	O
,	O
at	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
Embassy	I-ORG
in	O
London	B-LOC
and	O
defected	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
--	O
but	O
,	O
but	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
--	O
she	O
was	O
a	O
child	O
of	O
survivors	O
.	O

It's	O
a	O
very	O
interesting	O
book	O
,	O
because	O
that's	O
the	O
only	O
book	O
with	O
a	O
deep	O
knowledge	O
of	O
psychology	O
.	O

To	O
see	O
the	O
chasm	O
and	O
the	O
love	O
,	O
the	O
love	O
and	O
hatred	O
between	O
the	O
survivor	O
,	O
the	O
child	O
,	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
between	O
the	O
child	O
of	O
survivor	O
and	O
their	O
parents	O
.	O

It's	O
a	O
beautiful	O
book	O
.	O

I	O
think	O
Felicity	B-PER
is	O
going	O
to	O
review	O
this	O
book	O
.	O

It's	O
here	O
in	O
the	O
library	O
--	O
Heinemann	B-PER
,	O
Heinemann	B-PER
.	O

But	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
introduction	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
acknowledgment	O
,	O
she	O
thanks	O
her	O
father	O
,	O
Scharf	B-PER
,	O
for	O
his	O
help	O
.	O

And	O
in	O
the	O
second	O
part	O
,	O
she	O
writes	O
quite	O
a	O
--	O
quite	O
a	O
few	O
pages	O
about	O
this	O
--	O
her	O
father	O
,	O
Scharf	B-PER
,	O
who	O
was	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
member	O
of	O
this	O
delegation	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
who	O
came	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
who	O
came	O
to	O
me	O
that	O
I	O
should	O
take	O
over	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
thing	O
is	O
,	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
I	O
went	O
into	O
hiding	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
Scharf	B-PER
was	O
clever	O
enough	O
.	O

Haim	B-PER
Landau	I-PER
went	O
to	O
Israel	B-LOC
to	O
become	O
later	O
a	O
minister	O
.	O

And	O
Rafael	B-PER
Scharf	I-PER
went	O
to	O
England	B-LOC
,	O
where	O
he	O
studied	O
at	O
Oxford	B-LOC
and	O
served	O
in	O
the	O
,	O
and	O
served	O
in	O
the	O
British	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
and	O
later	O
became	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
intellectuals	O
,	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
intellectuals	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
London	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
is	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
founders	O
of	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
Quarterly	I-MISC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
How	O
long	O
,	O
how	O
long	O
did	O
you	O
remain	O
president	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
of	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
organization	I-ORG
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Until	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
my	O
studies	O
.	O

Until	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
my	O
studies	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
the	O
president	O
of	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
of	O
this	O
Jewish	B-ORG
organization	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
there	O
were	O
other	O
organizations	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
fraternities	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
fraternities	O
,	O
the	O
same	O
fraternities	O
as	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
,	O
as	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
corporations	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
corporations	O
,	O
or	O
fraternities	O
.	O

I	O
used	O
to	O
,	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
invite	O
me	O
for	O
lectures	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
used	O
to	O
lecture	O
very	O
often	O
at	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

And	O
interestingly	O
,	O
I	O
received	O
from	O
a	O
fellow	O
,	O
here	O
in	O
Australia	B-LOC
,	O
called	O
Alexander	B-PER
,	O
a	O
photo	O
--	O
a	O
photocopy	O
from	O
a	O
book	O
,	O
written	O
about	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
.	O
]	O

And	O
there	O
,	O
they	O
claimed	O
that	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
member	O
.	O

I	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
an	O
honorary	O
member	O
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
I've	O
got	O
it	O
here	O
.	O

They	O
made	O
me	O
a	O
member	O
,	O
but	O
I	O
was	O
never	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
fraternities	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
During	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
at	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
your	O
university	O
studies	O
,	O
1935	B-DATE
,	O
'36	B-DATE
,	O
as	O
a	O
young	O
man	O
of	O
very	O
strong	O
Jewish	B-MISC
tradition	O
,	O
background	O
,	O
did	O
you	O
feel	O
that	O
being	O
Jewish	B-MISC
was	O
an	O
issue	O
in	O
the	O
day	O
to	O
day	O
life	O
around	O
you	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Sure	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
an	O
issue	O
.	O

We	O
knew	O
in	O
advance	O
it	O
was	O
an	O
issue	O
.	O

But	O
we	O
accepted	O
it	O
.	O

We	O
knew	O
in	O
advance	O
that	O
the	O
Constitution	O
,	O
giving	O
us	O
full	O
rights	O
,	O
was	O
just	O
a	O
fiction	O
,	O
though	O
we	O
accepted	O
it	O
.	O

We	O
accept	O
.	O

For	O
instance	O
,	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
killed	O
themselves	O
to	O
get	O
honors	O
at	O
the	O
university	O
,	O
because	O
with	O
that	O
,	O
with	O
the	O
honors	O
,	O
they	O
will	O
get	O
better	O
positions	O
.	O

The	O
Jew	B-MISC
knew	O
in	O
advance	O
that	O
he	O
will	O
not	O
get	O
any	O
position	O
,	O
any	O
position	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Why	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Because	O
,	O
because	O
,	O
because	O
he	O
was	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
he	O
couldn't	O
get	O
out	O
of	O
it	O
.	O

You	O
know	O
,	O
the	O
system	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
was	O
such	O
that	O
when	O
you	O
lived	O
in	O
a	O
town	O
,	O
you	O
were	O
registered	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
column	O
stating	O
your	O
religion	O
and	O
your	O
nationality	O
.	O

You	O
could	O
have	O
said	O
your	O
nationality	O
is	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
but	O
your	O
religion	O
is	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

You	O
couldn't	O
change	O
your	O
religion	O
.	O

You	O
couldn't	O
,	O
even	O
,	O
even	O
if	O
you	O
were	O
an	O
atheist	O
,	O
you	O
were	O
born	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
it	O
is	O
written	O
there	O
.	O

If	O
you	O
want	O
--	O
and	O
besides	O
--	O
and	O
because	O
of	O
that	O
,	O
you	O
belong	O
to	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
kahal	I-ORG
,	O
to	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
to	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
community	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
community	I-ORG
could	O
impose	O
taxes	O
on	O
you	O
.	O

And	O
if	O
you	O
didn't	O
pay	O
the	O
taxes	O
,	O
the	O
sheriff	O
,	O
the	O
government	O
sheriff	O
,	O
will	O
come	O
and	O
collect	O
your	O
candlesticks	O
and	O
sell	O
them	O
at	O
an	O
auction	O
to	O
pay	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
taxes	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
you	O
may	O
think	O
,	O
if	O
I	O
am	O
running	O
away	O
from	O
my	O
shtetl	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
I'll	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
say	O
,	O
I'm	O
not	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

Can't	O
do	O
it	O
,	O
because	O
according	O
to	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
regulations	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
--	O
if	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
went	O
--	O
if	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
migrated	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
--	O
not	O
only	O
migrated	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
went	O
for	O
,	O
for	O
a	O
holiday	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
for	O
four	O
weeks	O
,	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
fill	O
out	O
a	O
slip	O
,	O
where	O
it	O
is	O
written	O
--	O
I	O
,	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
,	O
nationality	O
,	O
Polish	B-MISC
,	O
or	O
nationality	O
,	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
whatever	O
you	O
like	O
to	O
write	O
,	O
and	O
religion	O
,	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
or	O
Jewish	B-MISC
religion	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
--	O
I'm	O
going	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
you	O
can't	O
,	O
when	O
you	O
came	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
come	O
to	O
the	O
city	O
council	O
and	O
fill	O
out	O
a	O
new	O
,	O
a	O
new	O
slip	O
,	O
and	O
there	O
it	O
was	O
written	O
,	O
you	O
showed	O
.	O

It	O
is	O
written	O
there	O
.	O

The	O
full	O
slip	O
said	O
you	O
are	O
Jewish	B-MISC
.	O

You	O
couldn't	O
say	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
not	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
because	O
the	O
moment	O
you	O
are	O
born	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
only	O
way	O
of	O
getting	O
out	O
of	O
it	O
was	O
conversion	O
.	O

If	O
you	O
did	O
not	O
convert	O
,	O
you	O
stayed	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

You	O
could	O
have	O
shouted	O
to	O
heaven	O
,	O
I	O
don't	O
believe	O
in	O
God	O
.	O

You	O
are	O
still	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

We'll	O
continue	O
next	O
time	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Next	O
time	O
?	O

But	O
we	O
had	O
to	O
--	O

