INT	O
:	O
Tape	O
seven	O
of	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

We	O
were	O
talking	O
the	O
previous	O
discussion	O
about	O
your	O
time	O
at	O
university	O
,	O
and	O
you	O
talked	O
about	O
some	O
of	O
the	O
far	O
right	O
-	O
wing	O
students	O
and	O
the	O
trouble	O
they	O
caused	O
.	O

When	O
you	O
look	O
back	O
at	O
the	O
day	O
-	O
to	O
-	O
day	O
experience	O
with	O
other	O
students	O
in	O
general	O
,	O
was	O
there	O
any	O
ethnic	O
tension	O
or	O
religious	O
conflict	O
at	O
university	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

At	O
university	O
,	O
yes	O
.	O

That	O
extension	O
was	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
the	O
attitude	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
students	O
against	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

But	O
again	O
,	O
I	O
wouldn't	O
say	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
students	O
as	O
a	O
whole	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
the	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
and	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
the	O
troublemakers	O
.	O

The	O
other	O
Poles	B-MISC
were	O
indifferent	O
.	O

No	O
,	O
I	O
--	O
I	O
have	O
--	O
I	O
can't	O
remember	O
a	O
Pole	B-MISC
coming	O
out	O
in	O
defense	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

But	O
they	O
were	O
indifferent	O
,	O
but	O
they	O
didn't	O
take	O
part	O
in	O
it	O
.	O

Whether	O
they	O
like	O
it	O
--	O
liked	O
it	O
or	O
not	O
.	O

Maybe	O
they	O
didn't	O
.	O

But	O
it	O
was	O
,	O
like	O
always	O
,	O
a	O
minority	O
of	O
troublemakers	O
,	O
a	O
minority	O
to	O
--	O
which	O
was	O
seeking	O
power	O
riding	O
on	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
horse	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
a	O
very	O
convenient	O
horse	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Where	O
do	O
you	O
think	O
this	O
prominence	O
of	O
the	O
far	O
right	O
-	O
wing	O
students	O
came	O
from	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
prominence	O
came	O
--	O
to	O
a	O
certain	O
extent	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
always	O
trouble	O
from	O
the	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
from	O
the	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
.	O

The	O
Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
,	O
as	O
I	O
mentioned	O
earlier	O
,	O
was	O
created	O
--	O
I	O
mean	O
,	O
the	O
--	O
with	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
pogroms	O
all	O
over	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

All	O
over	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

It	O
does	O
not	O
mean	O
that	O
the	O
population	O
was	O
eager	O
to	O
pogrom	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

In	O
Galicia	B-LOC
,	O
for	O
instance	O
,	O
in	O
our	O
town	O
,	O
the	O
population	O
came	O
in	O
because	O
they	O
were	O
told	O
to	O
--	O
the	O
farmers	O
were	O
told	O
that	O
they	O
will	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
loot	O
,	O
to	O
get	O
something	O
.	O

But	O
it	O
so	O
happened	O
they	O
came	O
for	O
three	O
weeks	O
.	O

In	O
the	O
third	O
week	O
,	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
government	O
sent	O
in	O
some	O
military	O
.	O

And	O
our	O
balcony	O
,	O
I	O
remember	O
--	O
I	O
was	O
six	O
years	O
old	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
machine	O
gun	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
remember	O
that	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
I	O
have	O
seen	O
because	O
I	O
was	O
on	O
the	O
balcony	O
,	O
as	O
a	O
child	O
,	O
a	O
six	O
-	O
year	O
-	O
old	O
child	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
--	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
the	O
--	O
like	O
today	O
,	O
I	O
remember	O
it	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
three	O
soldiers	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
hitting	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
with	O
the	O
butt	O
of	O
the	O
rifle	O
.	O

Was	O
not	O
much	O
.	O

But	O
then	O
suddenly	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
there	O
--	O
they	O
could	O
see	O
smoke	O
coming	O
out	O
--	O
coming	O
out	O
from	O
two	O
different	O
directions	O
in	O
the	O
villages	O
,	O
enclosed	O
by	O
villages	O
.	O

From	O
one	O
side	O
and	O
from	O
the	O
other	O
side	O
.	O

And	O
within	O
minutes	O
,	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
peasant	O
disappeared	O
because	O
they	O
could	O
see	O
that	O
somebody	O
burned	O
this	O
--	O
this	O
--	O
this	O
--	O
their	O
houses	O
somewhere	O
could	O
be	O
on	O
fire	O
.	O

It	O
so	O
happens	O
that	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
it	O
was	O
later	O
I	O
heard	O
that	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
people	O
,	O
young	O
people	O
,	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
were	O
in	O
the	O
Austrian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
.	O

They	O
were	O
serving	O
in	O
the	O
Austrian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
,	O
and	O
they	O
organized	O
for	O
the	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
third	O
week	O
.	O

They	O
organized	O
some	O
kind	O
of	O
a	O
self	O
-	O
defense	O
.	O

They	O
placed	O
themselves	O
during	O
the	O
night	O
in	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
villages	O
.	O

In	O
one	O
village	O
on	O
the	O
north	O
and	O
the	O
other	O
on	O
the	O
south	O
,	O
for	O
instance	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
put	O
on	O
fire	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
barns	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
enough	O
to	O
keep	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
away	O
--	O
away	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
town	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
no	O
more	O
pogroms	O
whatsoever	O
.	O

In	O
other	O
towns	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
much	O
--	O
this	O
was	O
worse	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
worst	O
pogroms	O
during	O
--	O
connected	O
with	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
were	O
instigated	O
by	O
army	O
officers	O
.	O

Just	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
by	O
army	O
officers	O
.	O

For	O
instance	O
,	O
in	O
Vilna	B-LOC
.	O

In	O
Vilna	B-LOC
,	O
they	O
arrested	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

The	O
army	O
arrested	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
they	O
did	O
the	O
same	O
as	O
the	O
SS	B-ORG
did	O
20	O
years	O
later	O
,	O
23	O
years	O
later	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
took	O
them	O
out	O
and	O
told	O
them	O
to	O
dig	O
their	O
own	O
graves	O
.	O

A	O
famous	O
Jewish	B-MISC
writer	O
was	O
shot	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
arrested	O
together	O
with	O
another	O
,	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
poet	O
--	O
poet	O
Yaffe	B-PER
.	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
the	O
name	O
of	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
writer	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
Bundist	B-ORG
.	O

I	O
--	O
I'll	O
--	O
I	O
could	O
--	O
I	O
could	O
check	O
on	O
it	O
.	O

They	O
shot	O
him	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
.	O

Yaffe	B-PER
was	O
arrested	O
.	O

Yaffe	B-PER
was	O
a	O
Hebrew	B-MISC
poet	O
,	O
a	O
Zionist	B-ORG
,	O
a	O
Hebrew	B-MISC
poet	O
.	O

And	O
eventually	O
he	O
was	O
relieved	O
and	O
thrown	O
.	O

But	O
there	O
were	O
pogroms	O
in	O
Vilna	B-LOC
.	O

In	O
Lindbergh	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
Lwow	B-LOC
,	O
there	O
were	O
terrible	O
pogroms	O
.	O

Because	O
the	O
officers	O
said	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
should	O
help	O
--	O
should	O
come	O
out	O
against	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
.	O

Because	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
did	O
not	O
come	O
--	O
come	O
out	O
against	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
,	O
there	O
were	O
pogroms	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
there	O
--	O
quite	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

A	O
very	O
big	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
killed	O
.	O

So	O
what	O
I	O
am	O
driving	O
at	O
to	O
say	O
is	O
that	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
the	O
population	O
of	O
Poles	B-MISC
.	O

There	O
were	O
the	O
instigators	O
.	O

So	O
Polish	B-MISC
officers	O
in	O
the	O
army	O
,	O
mostly	O
Polish	B-MISC
officers	O
in	O
the	O
army	O
in	O
the	O
beginning	O
.	O

And	O
later	O
was	O
the	O
element	O
--	O
the	O
elements	O
of	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
and	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

They	O
instigated	O
Poles	B-MISC
to	O
do	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
do	O
the	O
same	O
as	O
Hitler	B-PER
did	O
in	O
Kristallnacht	B-MISC
later	O
.	O

So	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
problem	O
.	O

The	O
minority	O
--	O
a	O
minority	O
of	O
Poles	B-MISC
poisoned	O
the	O
atmosphere	O
.	O

Take	O
,	O
for	O
instance	O
,	O
the	O
establishment	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-LOC
Republic	I-LOC
.	O

As	O
you	O
know	O
--	O
as	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
the	O
moment	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
established	O
themselves	O
,	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
marched	O
against	O
Kiev	B-LOC
and	O
conquered	O
Kiev.	B-LOC

You	O
--	O
you	O
--	O
you	O
know	O
about	O
it	O
.	O

They	O
entered	O
Kiev	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
to	O
Ukraine	B-LOC
to	O
establish	O
the	O
Polish	B-LOC
boundaries	I-LOC
from	O
the	O
16th	B-DATE
century	I-DATE
,	O
including	O
the	O
Ukraine	B-LOC
as	O
it	O
should	O
belong	O
to	O
Poland	B-LOC
together	O
with	O
Kiev	B-LOC
.	O

Now	O
,	O
who	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
?	O

The	O
legionnaires	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
,	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
to	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
going	O
together	O
with	O
Haller's	B-PER
army	O
--	O
General	O
Joseph	B-PER
Haller	I-PER
,	O
Jozef	B-PER
Haller	I-PER
.	O

Jozef	B-PER
Haller	I-PER
established	O
himself	O
a	O
name	O
in	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
history	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
killing	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
beating	O
up	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
tearing	O
the	O
beards	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
out	O
with	O
the	O
flesh	O
.	O

They	O
did	O
it	O
in	O
towns	O
,	O
in	O
shtetls	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
did	O
it	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
trains	O
.	O

And	O
what	O
is	O
interesting	O
,	O
they	O
came	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
Haller's	B-PER
army	O
came	O
to	O
Poland	B-LOC
under	O
the	O
leadership	O
of	O
French	B-MISC
officers	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
fact	O
is	O
that	O
the	O
French	B-MISC
officers	O
did	O
not	O
take	O
part	O
in	O
the	O
pogroms	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
Haller	B-PER
himself	O
,	O
his	O
army	O
,	O
although	O
Poland	B-LOC
was	O
a	O
sovereign	O
state	O
,	O
his	O
army	O
came	O
in	O
on	O
the	O
condition	O
that	O
it	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
under	O
the	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
regime	O
.	O

It	O
will	O
be	O
like	O
a	O
sovereign	O
--	O
like	O
an	O
independent	O
--	O
an	O
independent	O
army	O
,	O
under	O
the	O
French	B-MISC
officers	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
French	B-MISC
officers	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
didn't	O
take	O
back	O
--	O
didn't	O
take	O
--	O
didn't	O
pogrom	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

Only	O
the	O
Haller	B-PER
--	O
Haller's	B-PER
army	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
well	O
-	O
known	O
.	O

In	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
say	O
Haller	B-PER
chicken	O
.	O

That	O
means	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
tear	O
out	O
the	O
beard	O
together	O
with	O
the	O
flesh	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
that's	O
--	O
but	O
what	O
is	O
not	O
very	O
well	O
-	O
known	O
is	O
that	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
made	O
to	O
use	O
an	O
alliance	O
with	O
Petliura	B-PER
.	O

And	O
you	O
know	O
--	O
you	O
remember	O
Petliura	B-PER
?	O

Hetman	B-PER
Petliura	I-PER
.	O

The	O
man	O
who	O
was	O
shot	O
later	O
by	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
in	O
Paris	B-LOC
that	O
he	O
organized	O
the	O
pogroms	O
,	O
the	O
most	O
bloody	O
pogroms	O
in	O
Ukraine	B-LOC
--	O
in	O
the	O
Ukraine	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
the	O
French	B-ORG
court	I-ORG
acquitted	O
him	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
Hitler	B-PER
.	O

And	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
went	O
to	O
Kiev	B-LOC
together	O
with	O
General	O
Haller	B-PER
and	O
together	O
--	O
and	O
together	O
with	O
Hetman	B-PER
Petliura	I-PER
.	O

In	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
--	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
history	O
you	O
never	O
--	O
they	O
will	O
--	O
they	O
never	O
mentioned	O
the	O
shameless	O
story	O
--	O
stories	O
.	O

I	O
discovered	O
it	O
recently	O
on	O
the	O
internet	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
internet	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
--	O
the	O
internet	O
quoted	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
an	O
essay	O
published	O
in	O
the	O
Gazeta	B-MISC
Polska	I-MISC
.	O

Wouldn't	O
have	O
--	O
if	O
it	O
--	O
if	O
it	O
wouldn't	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
truth	O
,	O
Gazeta	B-MISC
Polska	I-MISC
wouldn't	O
have	O
dared	O
to	O
connect	O
Petliura	B-PER
with	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
.	O

Now	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
he	O
left	O
--	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
came	O
back	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
left	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
over	O
there	O
in	O
Kiev	B-LOC
.	O

You	O
remember	O
him	O
?	O

Rydz	B-PER
-	I-PER
Smigly	I-PER
.	O

Rydz	B-PER
-	I-PER
Smigly	I-PER
was	O
a	O
Polish	B-MISC
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
in	O
Kiev	B-LOC
.	O

In	O
the	O
meantime	O
,	O
Budyonny	B-PER
marched	O
on	O
Kiev	B-LOC
on	O
the	O
one	O
side	O
,	O
and	O
took	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
from	O
the	O
north	O
,	O
and	O
Poland	B-LOC
suddenly	O
became	O
squished	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
marched	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
on	O
the	O
outskirt	O
of	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
was	O
just	O
hanging	O
on	O
the	O
--	O
on	O
--	O
on	O
a	O
hair	O
.	O

And	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
government	I-ORG
--	O
the	O
prime	O
minister	O
was	O
Witos	B-PER
,	O
Wincenty	B-PER
Witos	B-PER
,	O
The	O
leader	O
of	O
the	O
Piast	B-ORG
.	O

Piast	B-ORG
,	O
peasant	O
party	O
,	O
or	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
farmers'	O
party	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
the	O
prime	O
minister	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
our	O
neighborhood	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
from	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
,	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
a	O
--	O
from	O
a	O
village	O
close	O
to	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
,	O
between	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
and	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
his	O
deputy	O
was	O
Ignacy	B-PER
Daszynski	I-PER
,	O
who	O
was	O
the	O
leader	O
of	O
the	O
PPS	B-ORG
,	O
of	O
the	O
Socialist	B-ORG
Party	I-ORG
of	I-ORG
Poland	I-ORG
.	O

They	O
issued	O
an	O
appeal	O
,	O
a	O
--	O
an	O
appeal	O
through	O
the	O
people	O
of	O
Poland	B-LOC
to	O
the	O
intelligentsia	O
,	O
and	O
to	O
the	O
people	O
of	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

Whoever	O
served	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
Austrian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
,	O
whoever	O
served	O
in	O
the	O
German	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
,	O
in	O
Russian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
,	O
and	O
feels	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
a	O
Pole	B-MISC
,	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
--	O
that	O
feels	O
that	O
a	O
Polish	B-MISC
independence	O
is	O
--	O
is	O
really	O
in	O
danger	O
,	O
he	O
should	O
volunteer	O
--	O
he	O
should	O
volunteer	O
to	O
help	O
defend	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

About	O
10,000	O
Jewish	B-MISC
intellectuals	O
,	O
most	O
of	O
them	O
former	O
officers	O
of	O
the	O
Prussian	B-MISC
--	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
Austrian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
and	O
of	O
the	O
Prussian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
and	O
of	O
the	O
Russian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
,	O
most	O
of	O
them	O
.	O

But	O
there	O
were	O
some	O
youngsters	O
who	O
never	O
served	O
in	O
the	O
army	O
.	O

They	O
all	O
volunteered	O
,	O
10,000	O
of	O
them	O
.	O

And	O
what	O
happened	O
?	O

They	O
came	O
to	O
the	O
point	O
of	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
point	O
showing	O
indicators	O
that	O
they	O
should	O
come	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

They	O
all	O
were	O
arrested	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
put	O
into	O
a	O
concentration	O
camp	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
first	O
concentration	O
camp	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
volunteered	O
to	O
defend	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
here	O
in	O
Melbourne	B-LOC
,	O
if	O
you	O
go	O
to	O
the	O
cemetery	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
see	O
that	O
some	O
15	O
months	O
ago	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
died	O
a	O
man	O
,	O
95	O
years	O
old	O
,	O
Dr.	O
Handelsman	B-PER
.	O

Dr.	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
Handelsman	B-PER
.	O

He	O
was	O
there	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
20	O
-	O
year	O
-	O
old	O
man	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
was	O
there	O
in	O
this	O
camp	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
Dr.	O
Handelsman	B-PER
was	O
a	O
scholar	O
,	O
was	O
later	O
a	O
French	B-MISC
citizen	O
.	O

I	O
--	O
he	O
showed	O
me	O
his	O
photographs	O
with	O
the	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
men	O
in	O
France	B-LOC
,	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
French	B-MISC
politicians	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

He	O
studied	O
in	O
Paris	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
Sorbonne	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
Sorbonne	B-LOC
published	O
a	O
few	O
books	O
of	O
his	O
in	O
French	B-MISC
.	O

Then	O
before	O
he	O
--	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
before	O
he	O
died	O
--	O
before	O
he	O
died	O
he	O
phoned	O
me	O
that	O
he	O
want	O
to	O
show	O
me	O
some	O
documents	O
.	O

I	O
remembered	O
him	O
,	O
but	O
I	O
didn't	O
remember	O
his	O
age	O
.	O

I	O
remembered	O
the	O
name	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
all	O
right	O
.	O

So	O
come	O
along	O
.	O

I	O
live	O
here	O
and	O
--	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I'm	O
95	O
years	O
old	O
.	O

95	O
years	O
old	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
travel	O
.	O

Said	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
are	O
95	O
,	O
I'll	O
come	O
to	O
see	O
you	O
.	O

He	O
shows	O
me	O
all	O
the	O
documents	O
of	O
--	O
all	O
the	O
documents	O
relating	O
to	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
and	O
all	O
the	O
correspondence	O
he	O
had	O
with	O
people	O
like	O
--	O
who	O
were	O
like	O
him	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
this	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
in	O
this	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
concentration	O
camp	O
.	O

After	O
quite	O
a	O
time	O
--	O
quite	O
a	O
time	O
,	O
a	O
few	O
years	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
released	O
because	O
there	O
was	O
an	O
outcry	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
whole	O
world	O
.	O

So	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
--	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
prime	O
--	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
this	O
appeal	O
that	O
they	O
should	O
come	O
along	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
signed	O
--	O
no	O
.	O

The	O
document	O
to	O
arrest	O
them	O
was	O
signed	O
by	O
General	O
Sosnkowski	B-PER
,	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
Pilsudski's	B-PER
deputy	O
.	O

So	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
kind	O
of	O
a	O
--	O
of	O
an	O
anti-Jewish	O
approach	O
.	O

They	O
thought	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
are	O
--	O
that	O
--	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
will	O
--	O
will	O
be	O
in	O
the	O
army	O
and	O
will	O
help	O
--	O
will	O
help	O
the	O
Bolsheviks	B-ORG
.	O

Now	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
how	O
it	O
started	O
.	O

Then	O
Poland	B-LOC
was	O
already	O
established	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
--	O
no	O
more	O
was	O
--	O
was	O
peace	O
with	O
Russia	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
the	O
boundaries	O
were	O
established	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
not	O
in	O
Kiev	B-LOC
,	O
but	O
the	O
--	O
but	O
the	O
borders	O
were	O
established	O
.	O

Everything	O
was	O
right	O
.	O

But	O
then	O
there	O
was	O
the	O
Sejm	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
Pilsudski	B-PER
realized	O
--	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
he	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
means	O
the	O
--	O
he	O
was	O
the	O
head	O
of	O
the	O
state	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
constitution	O
,	O
and	O
then	O
he	O
realized	O
that	O
the	O
majority	O
in	O
the	O
Sejm	B-ORG
are	O
always	O
against	O
him	O
.	O

The	O
majority	O
of	O
the	O
Sejm	B-ORG
were	O
the	O
peasant	O
party	O
,	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
Christian	B-ORG
Democrats	I-ORG
,	O
the	O
national	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
antisemitic	O
national	O
party	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
anti-Jewish	O
party	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
party	O
of	O
-	O
-	O
of	O
-	O
-	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
peasants	O
--	O
what	O
is	O
--	O
led	O
by	O
Wincenty	B-PER
Witos	I-PER
.	O

He	O
realized	O
that	O
the	O
majority	O
is	O
against	O
him	O
.	O

So	O
he	O
withdrew	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
government	O
was	O
a	O
government	O
of	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

Later	O
was	O
the	O
Grabskis	B-PER
.	O

Yes	O
.	O

With	O
the	O
Grabskis	B-PER
--	O
with	O
Wladyslaw	B-PER
Grabski	I-PER
and	O
Stanislaw	B-PER
Grabski	I-PER
.	O

One	O
was	O
a	O
minister	O
for	O
culture	O
,	O
for	O
education	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
other	O
was	O
minister	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
other	O
was	O
a	O
treasurer	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
they	O
were	O
in	O
government	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
anti-Jewish	O
.	O

And	O
although	O
the	O
Constitution	B-MISC
of	I-MISC
the	I-MISC
3rd	I-MISC
of	I-MISC
May	I-MISC
of	I-MISC
1922	I-MISC
was	O
democratic	O
and	O
contained	O
all	O
--	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
democratic	O
stipulations	O
,	O
but	O
it	O
was	O
on	O
paper	O
only	O
.	O

What	O
they	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
did	O
is	O
to	O
gerrymander	O
through	O
geography	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
this	O
an	O
example	O
.	O

If	O
Mielec	B-LOC
had	O
,	O
let's	O
say	O
,	O
5,000	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	B-MISC
and	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
had	O
40,000	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
that	O
is	O
one	O
close	O
to	O
the	O
other	O
,	O
what	O
they	O
did	O
is	O
they	O
joined	O
Mielec	B-LOC
with	O
a	O
different	O
region	O
where	O
they	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
hundred	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
where	O
--	O
where	O
Jews	B-MISC
did	O
not	O
live	O
.	O

That	O
means	O
that	O
this	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
,	O
Jaslo	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
couldn't	O
--	O
couldn't	O
elect	O
a	O
deputy	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
parliament	O
because	O
geographically	O
,	O
for	O
--	O
for	O
the	O
sake	O
of	O
elections	O
,	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
constituencies	O
was	O
created	O
in	O
such	O
a	O
case	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
such	O
a	O
way	O
that	O
people	O
that	O
--	O
cities	O
with	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
--	O
were	O
cut	O
off	O
,	O
were	O
connected	O
with	O
large	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
large	O
territories	O
,	O
villages	O
,	O
where	O
there	O
are	O
no	O
Jews	B-MISC
whatsoever	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
able	O
to	O
elect	O
anybody	O
.	O

Only	O
,	O
let	O
us	O
say	O
,	O
a	O
few	O
people	O
here	O
,	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
where	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
themselves	O
had	O
enough	O
votes	O
to	O
elect	O
somebody	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
came	O
Greenbaum	B-PER
with	O
an	O
idea	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
what	O
they	O
did	O
not	O
only	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
but	O
they	O
did	O
similar	O
things	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
.	O

So	O
Greenbaum	B-PER
,	O
being	O
a	O
deputy	O
,	O
organized	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
coalition	O
between	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
Germans	B-MISC
.	O

All	O
ethnics	O
were	O
joined	O
together	O
in	O
a	O
coalition	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
decided	O
that	O
if	O
an	O
Ukrainian	B-MISC
will	O
stand	O
for	O
election	O
in	O
a	O
place	O
where	O
there	O
are	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
will	O
vote	O
for	O
Ukrainian	B-MISC
.	O

If	O
the	O
majority	O
there	O
are	O
Ukrainian	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
will	O
vote	O
for	O
Ukrainian	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
in	O
places	O
where	O
there	O
were	O
more	O
Jews	B-MISC
than	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
will	O
vote	O
for	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
the	O
whole	O
gerrymander	O
collapsed	O
.	O

If	O
Poland	B-LOC
wanted	O
to	O
hide	O
that	O
35	O
%	O
to	O
37	O
%	O
of	O
the	O
population	O
are	O
minorities	O
,	O
and	O
in	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
they	O
committed	O
themselves	O
to	O
give	O
all	O
the	O
rights	O
to	O
the	O
minorities	O
.	O

If	O
they	O
wanted	O
to	O
hide	O
the	O
problem	O
that	O
Poland	B-LOC
consists	O
of	O
only	O
65	O
%	O
--	O
the	O
most	O
,	O
62	O
%	O
,	O
63	O
%	O
,	O
the	O
most	O
65	O
%	O
of	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
35	O
%	O
are	O
minorities	O
.	O

They	O
wanted	O
to	O
hide	O
it	O
with	O
--	O
through	O
this	O
gerrymander	O
.	O

Here	O
suddenly	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
alone	O
came	O
up	O
with	O
35	O
--	O
with	O
35	O
deputies	O
in	O
parliament	O
with	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
--	O
with	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
senators	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
the	O
real	O
number	O
--	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
ethnic	O
representatives	O
in	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
parliament	O
in	O
the	O
lower	O
house	O
and	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
in	O
the	O
senate	O
really	O
reflected	O
the	O
real	O
population	O
percentage	O
in	O
the	O
country	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
something	O
,	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
expect	O
to	O
.	O

Then	O
with	O
that	O
up	O
,	O
they	O
came	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
--	O
there	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
--	O
there	O
--	O
they	O
came	O
up	O
with	O
an	O
idea	O
of	O
the	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
Ugoda	B-MISC
,	O
which	O
means	O
with	O
an	O
idea	O
to	O
make	O
an	O
agreement	O
with	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

This	O
happened	O
on	O
a	O
Friday	O
night	O
.	O

As	O
I	O
mentioned	O
to	O
you	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
called	O
Leon	B-PER
Selpeter	I-PER
,	O
was	O
a	O
friend	O
of	O
my	O
brother	O
.	O

Comes	O
from	O
[	O
POLISH	O
]	O
,	O
was	O
a	O
pharmacist	O
and	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
great	O
Zionist	B-ORG
.	O

He	O
is	O
mentioned	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
in	O
Schindler's	B-MISC
Ark	I-MISC
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
Schindler's	B-MISC
Ark	I-MISC
as	O
the	O
man	O
who	O
gave	O
Schindler	B-PER
letters	O
to	O
the	O
Jewish	B-ORG
Congress	I-ORG
,	O
the	O
old	O
Jewish	B-ORG
Congress	I-ORG
.	O

He	O
was	O
in	O
Schindler's	B-MISC
Ark	I-MISC
.	O

So	O
Leon	B-PER
Selpeter	I-PER
told	O
the	O
story	O
secretly	O
,	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
still	O
secrecy	O
told	O
it	O
to	O
my	O
brother	O
.	O

And	O
--	O
and	O
,	O
oh	O
,	O
the	O
story	O
went	O
up	O
from	O
one	O
--	O
from	O
mouth	O
to	O
mouth	O
,	O
houses	O
--	O
from	O
houses	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
Friday	O
night	O
.	O

And	O
before	O
Friday	O
,	O
Stanislaw	B-PER
Markowski	I-PER
--	O
Stanislaw	B-PER
Grabski	I-PER
.	O

Stanislaw	B-PER
Grabski	I-PER
suggested	O
to	O
Dr.	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
who	O
was	O
the	O
leader	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
Galicia	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
suggested	O
to	O
him	O
that	O
he	O
would	O
like	O
to	O
come	O
to	O
see	O
him	O
on	O
Friday	O
night	O
for	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
Jewish	B-MISC
fish	O
,	O
for	O
gefilte	O
fish	O
,	O
which	O
you	O
will	O
--	O
well	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
very	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
very	O
much	O
liked	O
Jewish	B-MISC
fish	O
.	O

So	O
he	O
invited	O
himself	O
to	O
Dr.	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
for	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
for	O
gefilte	O
fish	O
.	O

And	O
Dr.	O
[	O
NON	O
-ENGLISH	O
]	O
invited	O
him	O
and	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
great	O
--	O
this	O
--	O
this	O
reception	O
,	O
the	O
kiddush	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
gefilte	O
fish	O
.	O

But	O
after	O
the	O
fish	O
,	O
Stanislaw	B-PER
Grabski	I-PER
came	O
out	O
with	O
an	O
idea	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
should	O
make	O
an	O
agreement	O
with	O
the	O
government	O
.	O

The	O
agreement	O
be	O
Ugoda	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
agreement	O
being	O
that	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
will	O
declare	O
their	O
--	O
you	O
call	O
it	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

Their	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
Citizenship	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Huh	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Citizenship	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
.	O

They	O
declare	O
their	O
loyalty	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
--	O
should	O
declare	O
their	O
loyalty	O
to	O
the	O
Polish	B-LOC
Republic	I-LOC
in	O
the	O
borders	O
which	O
are	O
now	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
present	O
borders	O
,	O
and	O
in	O
--	O
and	O
for	O
that	O
,	O
the	O
government	O
will	O
see	O
what	O
can	O
be	O
done	O
to	O
improve	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
Polish	I-MISC
relations	I-MISC
.	O

Surely	O
Greenbaum	B-PER
was	O
against	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
were	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

They	O
said	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
why	O
should	O
be	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
singled	O
out	O
,	O
that	O
they	O
should	O
declare	O
loyalty	O
to	O
Poland	B-LOC
in	O
the	O
present	O
boundaries	O
?	O

The	O
present	O
boundaries	O
were	O
disputed	O
by	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
.	O

That	O
means	O
they	O
wanted	O
to	O
put	O
a	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
between	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
the	O
Ukrainians	B-MISC
.	O

The	O
present	O
boundaries	O
were	O
not	O
recognized	O
by	O
the	O
--	O
by	O
--	O
by	O
the	O
League	B-ORG
of	I-ORG
Nations	I-ORG
.	O

So	O
why	O
should	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
be	O
singled	O
out	O
?	O

That's	O
number	O
one	O
.	O

And	O
number	O
two	O
,	O
the	O
promise	O
was	O
nothing	O
.	O

We	O
will	O
see	O
what	O
we	O
can	O
do	O
to	O
improve	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
Jewish	I-MISC
relations	I-MISC
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
great	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
great	O
affair	O
in	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
--	O
in	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
community	O
all	O
over	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

There	O
was	O
the	O
--	O
Greenbaum	B-PER
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
was	O
against	O
it	O
,	O
and	O
there	O
was	O
Dr.	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
who	O
was	O
always	O
in	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

Galicia	B-LOC
was	O
always	O
trying	O
to	O
--	O
not	O
to	O
fight	O
,	O
not	O
to	O
fight	O
.	O

To	O
try	O
--	O
to	O
get	O
out	O
whatever	O
is	O
possible	O
,	O
although	O
he	O
never	O
believes	O
that	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
will	O
--	O
will	O
--	O
will	O
stick	O
to	O
the	O
constitution	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
in	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
1922	B-DATE
,	O
'	B-DATE
23	I-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

We'll	O
have	O
to	O
finish	O
next	O
tape	O
.	O

