INT	O
:	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

So	O
,	O
you	O
saw	O
this	O
cart	O
approaching	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O

This	O
cart	O
approaching	O
,	O
so	O
they	O
stopped	O
.	O

They	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
what's	O
happened	O
to	O
you	O
--	O
you	O
are	O
--	O
you	O
are	O
sick	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
Frieda	B-PER
,	O
you	O
can't	O
walk	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
who	O
we	O
are	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
jumped	O
down	O
,	O
lifted	O
my	O
wife	O
to	O
this	O
place	O
where	O
he	O
was	O
sitting	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
walking	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
we	O
were	O
walking	O
until	O
we	O
came	O
to	O
the	O
city	O
,	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
about	O
another	O
3	O
,	O
or	O
4	O
,	O
maybe	O
4	O
kilometers	O
,	O
or	O
5	O
kilometers	O
.	O

We	O
were	O
in	O
the	O
city	O
.	O

When	O
we	O
were	O
already	O
on	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
street	O
,	O
which	O
means	O
next	O
to	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
,	O
I	O
thanked	O
him	O
very	O
much	O
,	O
and	O
my	O
wife	O
came	O
down	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
our	O
house	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
man	O
,	O
the	O
first	O
man	O
who	O
recognized	O
me	O
was	O
Mr.	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
clerk	O
of	O
our	O
office	O
--	O
of	O
our	O
--	O
of	O
our	O
law	O
office	O
.	O

He	O
looked	O
at	O
us	O
,	O
and	O
his	O
first	O
--	O
and	O
--	O
his	O
--	O
his	O
first	O
reaction	O
was	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

You	O
are	O
still	O
alive	O
?	O

He	O
was	O
disappointed	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
still	O
alive	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
that	O
.	O

We	O
went	O
--	O
we	O
went	O
home	O
to	O
our	O
house	O
,	O
and	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
family	O
over	O
from	O
--	O
which	O
you	O
--	O
which	O
we	O
had	O
to	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
our	O
tenants	O
,	O
who	O
had	O
this	O
restaurant	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
first	O
floor	O
where	O
the	O
Judenrat	B-ORG
was	O
--	O
was	O
now	O
occupied	O
by	O
her	O
.	O

Was	O
occupied	O
by	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
,	O
but	O
when	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
left	O
,	O
she	O
moved	O
in	O
.	O

When	O
--	O
the	O
moment	O
we	O
came	O
,	O
she	O
opened	O
the	O
door	O
,	O
well	O
--	O
well	O
,	O
that's	O
--	O
--	O
that's	O
yours	O
.	O

That's	O
yours	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
--	O
was	O
our	O
--	O
our	O
furniture	O
was	O
there	O
.	O

No	O
,	O
we	O
,	O
we	O
came	O
,	O
we	O
came	O
home	O
.	O

A	O
few	O
hours	O
later	O
,	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
hours	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
went	O
down	O
.	O

I	O
went	O
down	O
to	O
have	O
a	O
look	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
.	O

In	O
this	O
restaurant	O
where	O
we're	O
at	O
,	O
were	O
dozens	O
and	O
dozens	O
of	O
soldiers	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
restaurant	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
pub	O
--	O
dozens	O
of	O
soldiers	O
.	O

When	O
I	O
was	O
standing	O
there	O
at	O
the	O
entrance	O
,	O
a	O
man	O
approached	O
me	O
.	O

I	O
knew	O
his	O
face	O
.	O

I	O
didn't	O
know	O
his	O
name	O
,	O
a	O
young	O
man	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I	O
knew	O
,	O
I	O
heard	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
back	O
.	O

Tell	O
me	O
what	O
is	O
your	O
opinion	O
of	O
the	O
situation	O
.	O

I	O
immediately	O
recognized	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
a	O
--	O
that	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
knows	O
that	O
we	O
are	O
back	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
want	O
to	O
know	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
--	O
what	O
,	O
in	O
my	O
opinion	O
.	O

I	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
why	O
should	O
I	O
tell	O
you	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
opinion	O
.	O

You	O
ask	O
the	O
brother	O
of	O
Dr.	O
Droba	B-PER
,	O
Jozef	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
--	O
but	O
he	O
got	O
there	O
Jozef	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
.	O

He	O
is	O
a	O
friend	O
of	O
mine	O
.	O

We	O
had	O
discussions	O
before	O
.	O

He	O
used	O
to	O
come	O
to	O
the	O
office	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
had	O
discussions	O
on	O
the	O
situation	O
.	O

He	O
knows	O
what	O
--	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
,	O
he	O
knows	O
my	O
--	O
he	O
knows	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
I	O
am	O
standing	O
for	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
very	O
indecisive	O
,	O
so	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
that	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
friend	O
of	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
.	O

Jasinszki	B-PER
took	O
--	O
Jasinszki	B-PER
was	O
the	O
man	O
who	O
gave	O
me	O
his	O
--	O
his	O
--	O
his	O
Aryan	B-MISC
papers	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
had	O
a	O
safe	O
house	O
for	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
very	O
pleased	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
pleased	O
with	O
his	O
mission	O
and	O
went	O
away	O
.	O

I	O
immediately	O
recognized	O
that	O
the	O
AK	B-ORG
sent	O
him	O
out	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
,	O
I	O
thought	O
that	O
I	O
will	O
give	O
him	O
the	O
right	O
address	O
,	O
which	O
will	O
ensure	O
him	O
about	O
my	O
loyalty	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
didn't	O
know	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
what	O
I	O
knew	O
later	O
--	O
that	O
it	O
was	O
Brigadier	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
,	O
the	O
Jozef	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
,	O
the	O
brother	O
of	O
Dr.	O
Antoni	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
,	O
who	O
was	O
the	O
commander	O
in	O
chief	O
of	O
the	O
NSZ	B-ORG
for	O
the	O
District	B-LOC
of	I-LOC
Cracow	I-LOC
.	O

But	O
I	O
am	O
sure	O
that	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
figurehead	O
.	O

They	O
took	O
a	O
figurehead	O
,	O
because	O
he	O
was	O
,	O
before	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
a	O
professional	O
officer	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
professor	O
,	O
a	O
teacher	O
at	O
the	O
Academy	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Military	B-ORG
Academy	I-ORG
.	O

So	O
he	O
was	O
the	O
right	O
man	O
,	O
but	O
I	O
gave	O
him	O
the	O
right	O
man	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
express	O
an	O
opinion	O
about	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
that	O
.	O

A	O
couple	O
of	O
days	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
went	O
to	O
Droba	B-PER
,	O
and	O
then	O
we	O
met	O
there	O
.	O

I	O
could	O
see	O
that	O
Droba	B-PER
was	O
embarrassed	O
with	O
our	O
coming	O
to	O
see	O
him	O
a	O
few	O
times	O
,	O
more	O
than	O
,	O
within	O
these	O
two	O
days	O
.	O

Somehow	O
with	O
him	O
,	O
I	O
could	O
feel	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
a	O
little	O
bit	O
embarrassed	O
,	O
although	O
we	O
made	O
out	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
reconciliation	O
of	O
the	O
accounts	O
,	O
because	O
he	O
told	O
us	O
,	O
he	O
gave	O
us	O
back	O
whatever	O
was	O
left	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

About	O
two	O
,	O
three	O
,	O
maybe	O
four	O
days	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
suddenly	O
,	O
we	O
suddenly	O
saw	O
that	O
people	O
are	O
winding	O
up	O
the	O
telephone	O
lines	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
were	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
worried	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
came	O
to	O
an	O
officer	O
.	O

My	O
Russian	B-MISC
is	O
very	O
,	O
was	O
very	O
slow	O
,	O
was	O
very	O
limited	O
.	O

I	O
came	O
to	O
an	O
officer	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
asked	O
him	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
what	O
,	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
?	O

Are	O
--	O
are	O
--	O
are	O
you	O
withdrawing	O
,	O
are	O
you	O
,	O
are	O
you	O
going	O
back	O
?	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
very	O
scared	O
that	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
may	O
come	O
back	O
.	O

I	O
met	O
another	O
officer	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
we	O
want	O
to	O
know	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
,	O
because	O
I'm	O
the	O
only	O
Jew	B-MISC
here	O
with	O
my	O
wife	O
.	O

In	O
case	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
go	O
,	O
come	O
in	O
,	O
I	O
have	O
to	O
run	O
away	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

I	O
came	O
to	O
Droba	B-PER
.	O

And	O
there	O
was	O
news	O
of	O
Droba	B-PER
the	O
Colonel	O
and	O
the	O
Brigadier	O
and	O
the	O
other	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
her	O
--	O
look	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
?	O

I	O
could	O
see	O
they	O
are	O
winding	O
up	O
the	O
telephones	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
people	O
told	O
me	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
yes	O
,	O
I	O
heard	O
it	O
,	O
too	O
,	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

The	O
Germans	B-ORG
may	O
come	O
back	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
Droba	B-PER
told	O
me	O
,	O
the	O
Jozef	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
,	O
they	O
said	O
,	O
you	O
run	O
for	O
your	O
life	O
to	O
a	O
town	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
but	O
why	O
?	O

And	O
I	O
asked	O
the	O
other	O
officer	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
,	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
told	O
her	O
,	O
you	O
must	O
have	O
misunderstood	O
him	O
.	O

I	O
,	O
in	O
your	O
place	O
,	O
wouldn't	O
fight	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
same	O
afternoon	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
quarter	O
of	O
an	O
hour	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
already	O
on	O
my	O
way	O
in	O
the	O
direction	O
of	O
town	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
another	O
main	O
road	O
.	O

We	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

We	O
went	O
,	O
we	O
marched	O
7	O
kilometers	O
,	O
this	O
time	O
.	O

And	O
my	O
wife	O
said	O
,	O
she	O
can't	O
do	O
it	O
anymore	O
.	O

She	O
rubbed	O
off	O
the	O
back	O
of	O
her	O
foot	O
.	O

It's	O
hurting	O
,	O
she	O
can't	O
go	O
anymore	O
.	O

We	O
sat	O
down	O
.	O

When	O
we	O
sat	O
down	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
behind	O
--	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
house	O
deep	O
in	O
--	O
about	O
200	O
yards	O
from	O
the	O
road	O
,	O
and	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
Russian	B-ORG
truck	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

But	O
it	O
looked	O
that	O
the	O
house	O
is	O
empty	O
.	O

And	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
two	O
people	O
,	O
two	O
young	O
people	O
rode	O
by	O
on	O
bikes	O
.	O

100	O
yards	O
from	O
us	O
,	O
they	O
stopped	O
,	O
and	O
both	O
of	O
them	O
bent	O
down	O
to	O
repair	O
their	O
bikes	O
.	O

They	O
made	O
it	O
look	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
repairing	O
their	O
bikes	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
in	O
danger	O
.	O

These	O
are	O
Jedrus'	B-PER
people	O
--	O
AK	B-ORG
.	O

They	O
have	O
got	O
guns	O
behind	O
the	O
belt	O
.	O

Suddenly	O
both	O
bikes	O
need	O
repair	O
.	O

They	O
bent	O
down	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
Jedrus	B-PER
told	O
me	O
how	O
they	O
are	O
doing	O
it	O
.	O

They	O
are	O
waiting	O
--	O
that's	O
an	O
ambush	O
.	O

They	O
are	O
waiting	O
that	O
we	O
could	O
come	O
closer	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
am	O
going	O
to	O
this	O
road	O
to	O
this	O
house	O
,	O
where	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
Russian	B-ORG
truck	O
outside	O
there	O
,	O
although	O
it	O
looks	O
empty	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
jump	O
down	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
this	O
place	O
,	O
and	O
suddenly	O
I	O
saw	O
from	O
afar	O
,	O
an	O
ambulance	O
coming	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
jumped	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
middle	O
of	O
the	O
road	O
.	O

I	O
didn't	O
allow	O
it	O
to	O
go	O
.	O

Put	O
my	O
hands	O
up	O
--	O
the	O
ambulance	O
stopped	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
them	O
my	O
wife	O
is	O
injured	O
.	O

She	O
needs	O
help	O
.	O

And	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
officers	O
jumped	O
down	O
and	O
took	O
my	O
wife	O
up	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
went	O
up	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
--	O
I've	O
showed	O
to	O
--	O
I	O
showed	O
to	O
my	O
wife	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
the	O
two	O
bikes	O
doesn't	O
,	O
do	O
not	O
need	O
anymore	O
,	O
anymore	O
repairs	O
.	O

They	O
just	O
disappeared	O
.	O

In	O
the	O
front	O
of	O
this	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
front	O
of	O
--	O
but	O
they	O
were	O
going	O
just	O
the	O
opposite	O
direction	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
where	O
we	O
ran	O
away	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
I	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
in	O
the	O
wrong	O
direction	O
.	O

The	O
Germans	B-ORG
are	O
coming	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
the	O
Russians	B-ORG
are	O
leaving	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
they	O
came	O
and	O
told	O
what	O
I	O
have	O
told	O
them	O
to	O
the	O
man	O
sitting	O
next	O
to	O
the	O
driver	O
--	O
without	O
any	O
signs	O
,	O
without	O
any	O
officers	O
.	O

I	O
thought	O
he	O
is	O
a	O
sergeant	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
--	O
an	O
elderly	O
fellow	O
,	O
middle	O
-	O
aged	O
fellow	O
.	O

A	O
few	O
--	O
but	O
they	O
didn't	O
say	O
,	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
went	O
further	O
,	O
went	O
a	O
kilometer	O
or	O
so	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
--	O
two	O
Russians	B-MISC
came	O
on	O
a	O
motorbike	O
,	O
on	O
a	O
motorbike	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
that	O
way	O
.	O

They	O
stopped	O
them	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
asked	O
them	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
they	O
told	O
us	O
,	O
no	O
--	O
the	O
telephone	O
unit	O
is	O
going	O
back	O
,	O
and	O
another	O
is	O
coming	O
in	O
.	O

They	O
stay	O
there	O
.	O

Don't	O
worry	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

We	O
have	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
hospital	O
.	O

So	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
back	O
.	O

We	O
ran	O
away	O
to	O
meet	O
a	O
rendezvous	O
with	O
these	O
two	O
.	O

We	O
--	O
we	O
nearly	O
were	O
killed	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
went	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
,	O
to	O
the	O
hospital	O
,	O
outside	O
,	O
to	O
the	O
hospital	O
outside	O
the	O
town	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
then	O
--	O
then	O
--	O
the	O
COP	B-ORG
,	O
that's	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
some	O
large	O
--	O
they	O
changed	O
a	O
large	O
building	O
into	O
a	O
hospital	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

They	O
went	O
down	O
.	O

A	O
few	O
minutes	O
later	O
,	O
they	O
came	O
to	O
invite	O
us	O
inside	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
they	O
gave	O
us	O
all	O
facilities	O
to	O
wash	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
invited	O
us	O
to	O
have	O
dinner	O
,	O
beautiful	O
dinner	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
an	O
officer	O
came	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
brought	O
us	O
blankets	O
and	O
everything	O
.	O

You'll	O
be	O
sleeping	O
in	O
the	O
ambulance	O
,	O
and	O
next	O
day	O
,	O
we	O
will	O
take	O
you	O
to	O
Kolbuszowa	B-LOC
,	O
far	O
away	O
from	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

About	O
midnight	O
,	O
midnight	O
--	O
or	O
more	O
past	O
midnight	O
--	O
we	O
couldn't	O
sleep	O
.	O

We	O
were	O
sitting	O
,	O
we	O
were	O
sitting	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
this	O
ambulance	O
and	O
thinking	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
happened	O
.	O

Maybe	O
,	O
we	O
maybe	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
in	O
paradise	O
.	O

Maybe	O
they	O
have	O
,	O
they	O
have	O
shot	O
us	O
,	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
we	O
are	O
no	O
more	O
alive	O
,	O
that's	O
all	O
a	O
dream	O
.	O

And	O
my	O
wife	O
asked	O
me	O
,	O
why	O
didn't	O
they	O
come	O
along	O
to	O
shoot	O
us	O
?	O

I	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
--	O
because	O
a	O
revolver	O
,	O
a	O
handgun	O
is	O
a	O
nuisance	O
.	O

If	O
you	O
stand	O
,	O
inviting	O
--	O
two	O
,	O
two	O
,	O
three	O
foot	O
away	O
,	O
two	O
,	O
three	O
feet	O
away	O
,	O
they	O
will	O
shoot	O
you	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
what	O
they	O
were	O
waiting	O
for	O
.	O

But	O
if	O
we	O
were	O
,	O
if	O
they	O
realized	O
that	O
we	O
are	O
suspicious	O
,	O
if	O
the	O
moment	O
they	O
would	O
come	O
closer	O
,	O
we	O
would	O
start	O
running	O
.	O

And	O
when	O
we	O
start	O
running	O
,	O
a	O
handgun	O
is	O
not	O
worth	O
a	O
penny	O
.	O

In	O
the	O
meantime	O
,	O
a	O
Russian	B-ORG
car	O
can	O
come	O
from	O
that	O
side	O
or	O
from	O
that	O
side	O
.	O

They	O
will	O
be	O
in	O
bigger	O
trouble	O
.	O

They	O
are	O
,	O
they	O
are	O
not	O
such	O
,	O
such	O
big	O
heroes	O
.	O

And	O
a	O
handgun	O
is	O
not	O
good	O
for	O
those	O
things	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
aren't	O
good	O
when	O
you	O
are	O
standing	O
against	O
a	O
handgun	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
this	O
man	O
,	O
who	O
was	O
sitting	O
next	O
to	O
the	O
driver	O
,	O
came	O
out	O
in	O
a	O
white	O
coat	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
introduced	O
himself	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
my	O
name	O
is	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
am	O
Major	O
General	O
[	O
NON-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I'm	O
the	O
head	O
of	O
this	O
medical	O
unit	O
for	O
the	O
whole	O
army	O
,	O
thousand	O
army	O
,	O
here	O
.	O

I'm	O
a	O
professor	O
,	O
a	O
surgeon	O
,	O
a	O
professor	O
at	O
the	O
Moscow	B-ORG
University	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
I'm	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
we	O
can	O
write	O
in	O
Yiddish	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
tell	O
me	O
your	O
story	O
--	O
what	O
,	O
what	O
was	O
done	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
--	O
look	O
,	O

It	O
was	O
the	O
first	O
time	O
I	O
spoke	O
to	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
during	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
first	O
time	O
I've	O
spoken	O
to	O
--	O
I	O
spoke	O
to	O
him	O
in	O
Yiddish	B-MISC
.	O

He	O
finished	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
performing	O
,	O
they	O
are	O
performing	O
operations	O
.	O

And	O
another	O
fellow	O
came	O
in	O
,	O
a	O
Captain	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
the	O
whole	O
,	O
the	O
whole	O
,	O
the	O
whole	O
ambulance	O
was	O
--	O
they	O
all	O
came	O
out	O
to	O
hear	O
the	O
story	O
.	O

Next	O
day	O
,	O
they	O
took	O
us	O
to	O
Kolbuszowa	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
in	O
Kolbuszowa	B-LOC
,	O
we	O
were	O
sitting	O
outside	O
where	O
they	O
told	O
us	O
to	O
wait	O
in	O
the	O
ambulance	O
.	O

A	O
minute	O
later	O
,	O
a	O
few	O
minutes	O
later	O
,	O
a	O
captain	O
came	O
along	O
and	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
few	O
minutes	O
--	O
maybe	O
a	O
few	O
,	O
maybe	O
,	O
maybe	O
a	O
half	O
an	O
hour	O
later	O
,	O
or	O
something	O
--	O
they	O
came	O
,	O
there	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
a	O
bit	O
of	O
time	O
,	O
they	O
came	O
back	O
.	O

They	O
,	O
they	O
invited	O
us	O
inside	O
.	O

And	O
inside	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
man	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
in	O
this	O
whole	O
uniform	O
,	O
everything	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
introduced	O
us	O
to	O
the	O
man	O
in	O
charge	O
of	O
this	O
hospital	O
,	O
a	O
colonel	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
colonel	O
told	O
us	O
that	O
we	O
will	O
be	O
the	O
guests	O
of	O
his	O
in	O
his	O
hospital	O
until	O
we	O
are	O
ready	O
to	O
go	O
,	O
until	O
we	O
are	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
ready	O
to	O
go	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
that	O
.	O

They	O
found	O
us	O
a	O
place	O
,	O
they	O
found	O
us	O
a	O
place	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
first	O
night	O
,	O
we	O
were	O
in	O
his	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
surgery	O
inside	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
they	O
found	O
us	O
a	O
place	O
where	O
to	O
,	O
where	O
to	O
live	O
in	O
Kolbuszowa	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
there	O
,	O
we	O
met	O
our	O
friends	O
,	O
the	O
Hoenigs	B-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
what	O
happened	O
to	O
your	O
wife's	O
injury	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
To	O
what	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Your	O
wife's	O
bullet	O
wounds	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Oh	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

From	O
there	O
,	O
we	O
found	O
our	O
friends	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
who	O
came	O
to	O
,	O
who	O
were	O
in	O
Kolbuszowa	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
then	O
we	O
decided	O
to	O
go	O
by	O
truck	O
,	O
by	O
a	O
Russian	B-MISC
truck	O
to	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
belief	O
that	O
there	O
will	O
be	O
more	O
Jewish	B-MISC
people	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
where	O
we	O
will	O
be	O
able	O
somehow	O
to	O
see	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
we	O
arrived	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
evening	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
went	O
from	O
house	O
to	O
house	O
,	O
seeking	O
shelter	O
--	O
knock	O
the	O
door	O
.	O

We	O
are	O
refugees	O
.	O

We	O
want	O
shelter	O
.	O

They	O
recognized	O
us	O
as	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
because	O
they	O
recognize	O
my	O
wife	O
and	O
the	O
other	O
people	O
were	O
--	O
a	O
group	O
of	O
people	O
,	O
maybe	O
ten	O
people	O
--	O
no	O
shelter	O
.	O

In	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
we	O
found	O
a	O
house	O
.	O

We	O
didn't	O
know	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
.	O

We	O
found	O
a	O
house	O
,	O
they	O
took	O
us	O
in	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
Mrs.	O
Schreiber	B-PER
from	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

She	O
lives	O
now	O
in	O
,	O
in	O
New	B-LOC
York	I-LOC
.	O

She	O
looked	O
100	O
%	O
Polish	B-MISC
,	O
Aryan	B-MISC
.	O

I	O
was	O
standing	O
with	O
her	O
in	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
looked	O
shelter	O
.	O

We	O
came	O
from	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
thought	O
that	O
we	O
are	O
Poles	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
they	O
invited	O
us	O
and	O
made	O
us	O
a	O
nice	O
,	O
nice	O
supper	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
of	O
the	O
supper	O
,	O
they	O
realize	O
that	O
we	O
are	O
Jewish	B-MISC
,	O
because	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
other	O
people	O
--	O
my	O
wife	O
was	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
lady	O
,	O
the	O
lady	O
came	O
in	O
and	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
do	O
me	O
a	O
favor	O
,	O
I	O
don't	O
want	O
my	O
neighbors	O
to	O
know	O
that	O
we	O
gave	O
shelter	O
to	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

Before	O
dawn	O
,	O
please	O
leave	O
this	O
place	O
that	O
nobody	O
could	O
see	O
and	O
go	O
to	O
this	O
and	O
that	O
place	O
,	O
that	O
and	O
that	O
street	O
.	O

She	O
told	O
us	O
where	O
.	O

There	O
is	O
a	O
house	O
with	O
,	O
which	O
are	O
occupied	O
already	O
by	O
some	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
who	O
came	O
back	O
from	O
the	O
forest	O
.	O

The	O
whole	O
house	O
is	O
empty	O
and	O
occupied	O
by	O
them	O
.	O

You	O
go	O
there	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
didn't	O
realize	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
.	O

But	O
anyhow	O
,	O
before	O
dawn	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
out	O
.	O

We	O
went	O
out	O
,	O
but	O
we	O
realized	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
that	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
family	O
was	O
more	O
scared	O
that	O
the	O
neighboring	O
Poles	B-MISC
shouldn't	O
know	O
that	O
they	O
gave	O
shelter	O
to	O
Jewish	B-MISC
refugees	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
scared	O
for	O
the	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
scared	O
of	O
their	O
neighbors	O
more	O
than	O
they	O
were	O
scared	O
of	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
.	O

And	O
we	O
went	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
a	O
doctor	O
,	O
a	O
surgeon	O
.	O

And	O
as	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
the	O
surgeon	O
made	O
,	O
made	O
an	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
,	O
which	O
is	O
today	O
an	O
antique	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
say	O
,	O
I	O
would	O
like	O
you	O
to	O
photograph	O
this	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
.	O

Today	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
got	O
an	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
on	O
a	O
negative	O
.	O

There	O
,	O
they	O
made	O
an	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
,	O
a	O
negative	O
,	O
and	O
from	O
the	O
negative	O
,	O
they	O
made	O
the	O
positive	O
.	O

So	O
you	O
could	O
see	O
the	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
on	O
a	O
positive	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
showed	O
this	O
dumdum	O
bullet	O
inside	O
,	O
and	O
it	O
was	O
bleeding	O
,	O
and	O
it	O
was	O
infected	O
.	O

In	O
fact	O
,	O
it	O
had	O
to	O
be	O
taken	O
out	O
.	O

But	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I	O
can't	O
do	O
it	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
do	O
it	O
.	O

I	O
am	O
busy	O
every	O
day	O
,	O
the	O
whole	O
day	O
,	O
performing	O
operations	O
in	O
the	O
military	O
hospital	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
thing	O
I	O
can	O
do	O
--	O
I	O
can	O
take	O
your	O
wife	O
one	O
day	O
--	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
I'll	O
let	O
you	O
know	O
which	O
day	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
will	O
,	O
between	O
one	O
operation	O
and	O
another	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
remove	O
this	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
remove	O
this	O
bullet	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
what	O
happened	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
I	O
wasn't	O
there	O
at	O
that	O
particular	O
day	O
when	O
the	O
messenger	O
came	O
that	O
we	O
should	O
come	O
to	O
the	O
hospital	O
.	O

So	O
a	O
friend	O
of	O
mine	O
and	O
Mrs.	O
Schreiber	B-PER
,	O
they	O
--	O
and	O
a	O
certain	O
Mr.	O
Schwartz	B-PER
and	O
Mrs.	O
Schreiber	B-PER
took	O
my	O
wife	O
to	O
the	O
hospital	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
,	O
she	O
was	O
sitting	O
.	O

And	O
you	O
could	O
see	O
--	O
she	O
,	O
they	O
told	O
me	O
,	O
they	O
could	O
see	O
people	O
moving	O
in	O
and	O
out	O
--	O
dead	O
people	O
--	O
and	O
performing	O
operations	O
while	O
you	O
were	O
sitting	O
outside	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
she	O
--	O
a	O
nurse	O
came	O
in	O
and	O
said	O
,	O
it's	O
your	O
turn	O
,	O
come	O
in	O
.	O

They	O
put	O
her	O
on	O
the	O
table	O
,	O
and	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
anesthetic	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
anesthetic	O
was	O
there	O
--	O
this	O
--	O
chlo	O
--	O
is	O
it	O
called	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
Chloroform	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Chloroform	O
.	O

Chloroform	O
anesthetic	O
--	O
put	O
the	O
chloroform	O
anesthetic	O
.	O

A	O
minute	O
later	O
,	O
they	O
operated	O
,	O
took	O
out	O
the	O
bullet	O
and	O
bandaged	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
out	O
to	O
the	O
porch	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
told	O
her	O
,	O
when	O
she	O
was	O
still	O
half	O
asleep	O
--	O
they	O
said	O
,	O
out	O
to	O
the	O
porch	O
.	O

After	O
a	O
quarter	O
of	O
an	O
hour	O
,	O
he	O
told	O
them	O
--	O
Mr.	O
Schwartz	B-PER
and	O
Schreiber	B-PER
,	O
take	O
the	O
lady	O
home	O
.	O

And	O
if	O
,	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
can't	O
walk	O
,	O
so	O
take	O
a	O
cab	O
and	O
,	O
and	O
take	O
her	O
away	O
from	O
here	O
,	O
because	O
it's	O
not	O
even	O
healthy	O
to	O
sit	O
here	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
the	O
bullet	O
was	O
taken	O
out	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
this	O
was	O
about	O
September	B-DATE
,	I-DATE
'44	I-DATE
.	O

MV	O
:	O

No	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
still	O
August	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
still	O
August	O
.	O

It	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
date	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
on	O
this	O
,	O
on	O
this	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
.	O

You'll	O
see	O
the	O
date	O
on	O
the	O
X	O
-	O
ray	O
,	O
exactly	O
when	O
it	O
was	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
So	O
what	O
happened	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
you	O
and	O
your	O
wife	O
the	O
remainder	O
of	O
1944	B-DATE
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
the	O
remainder	O
.	O

We	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
--	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
Valas	B-PER
,	O
in	O
the	O
meantime	O
--	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
on	O
the	O
day	O
when	O
we	O
ran	O
--	O
on	O
the	O
day	O
,	O
on	O
the	O
4th	B-DATE
of	I-DATE
August	I-DATE
,	O
when	O
we	O
were	O
liberated	O
,	O
Valas	B-PER
was	O
back	O
,	O
because	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
evacuated	O
the	O
prison	O
in	O
Rzeszow	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
the	O
people	O
had	O
the	O
possibility	O
of	O
just	O
running	O
away	O
.	O

And	O
Valas	B-PER
went	O
together	O
with	O
Kolciak	B-PER
.	O

And	O
Valas	B-PER
told	O
him	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
we	O
have	O
,	O
we	O
have	O
got	O
all	O
possibilities	O
just	O
to	O
move	O
out	O
,	O
to	O
run	O
away	O
,	O
to	O
disappear	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
no	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
,	O
they	O
weren't	O
even	O
,	O
they	O
weren't	O
even	O
watched	O
properly	O
.	O

But	O
Kolciak	B-PER
didn't	O
want	O
.	O

Kolciak	B-PER
was	O
scared	O
.	O

Kolciak	B-PER
was	O
scared	O
that	O
I	O
will	O
take	O
him	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
make	O
him	O
responsible	O
for	O
the	O
deaths	O
of	O
the	O
families	O
,	O
there	O
.	O

So	O
Kolciak	B-PER
didn't	O
want	O
to	O
come	O
back	O
,	O
and	O
Kolciak	B-PER
disappeared	O
.	O

Some	O
people	O
say	O
that	O
he	O
died	O
.	O

Some	O
people	O
say	O
that	O
he	O
disappeared	O
among	O
the	O
refugees	O
,	O
amongst	O
the	O
millions	O
of	O
refugees	O
in	O
the	O
western	O
world	O
.	O

So	O
Valas	B-PER
came	O
along	O
,	O
Valas	B-PER
came	O
back	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
when	O
we	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
from	O
Rzeszow	B-LOC
,	O
Valas	B-PER
came	O
along	O
and	O
said	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
your	O
life	O
is	O
in	O
danger	O
,	O
that	O
what	O
happened	O
--	O
they're	O
letting	O
people	O
,	O
the	O
unit	O
of	O
AK	B-ORG
,	O
who	O
performed	O
,	O
who	O
,	O
who	O
murdered	O
your	O
family	O
and	O
who	O
came	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
they	O
established	O
themselves	O
as	O
the	O
militia	O
of	O
the	O
new	O
communist	B-ORG
government	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
they	O
already	O
know	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
alive	O
,	O
and	O
you	O
are	O
the	O
last	O
witness	O
of	O
their	O
crime	O
.	O

Therefore	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
to	O
run	O
for	O
your	O
life	O
.	O

I	O
immediately	O
took	O
a	O
train	O
to	O
Lublin	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
Lublin	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
my	O
wife	O
still	O
was	O
there	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
I	O
went	O
to	O
see	O
Dr.	O
Sommerstein	B-PER
.	O

Dr.	O

Sommerstein	B-PER
was	O
a	O
Zionist	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
he	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
top	O
leaders	O
of	O
the	O
,	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
Jewry	I-ORG
before	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
member	O
of	O
the	O
Parliament	B-ORG
,	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
Parliament	I-ORG
on	O
behalf	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
when	O
the	O
new	O
government	O
came	O
in	O
,	O
the	O
communist	B-ORG
-	O
dominated	O
government	O
came	O
in	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
the	O
Minister	O
for	O
Repatriation	O
.	O

They	O
made	O
him	O
Minister	O
on	O
orders	O
of	O
Stalin	B-PER
.	O

They	O
made	O
a	O
Zionist	B-MISC
the	O
Minister	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
show	O
to	O
the	O
world	O
that	O
it's	O
not	O
so	O
bad	O
,	O
because	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
Zionist	B-MISC
in	O
the	O
government	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
went	O
to	O
see	O
him	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
can	O
remember	O
coming	O
,	O
him	O
making	O
an	O
appointment	O
with	O
his	O
daughter	O
to	O
come	O
again	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
the	O
story	O
--	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

They	O
said	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
tell	O
me	O
the	O
whole	O
story	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
felt	O
like	O
--	O
I	O
know	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
a	O
very	O
busy	O
man	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
I	O
want	O
to	O
listen	O
to	O
you	O
the	O
whole	O
story	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
the	O
whole	O
story	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
sitting	O
there	O
maybe	O
1	O
and	O
1	O
/	O
2	O
hours	O
or	O
2	O
hours	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
he	O
said	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
the	O
only	O
way	O
of	O
saving	O
you	O
is	O
to	O
get	O
you	O
a	O
job	O
here	O
in	O
Lublin	B-LOC
in	O
a	O
house	O
which	O
you	O
will	O
be	O
,	O
which	O
you	O
will	O
be	O
guarded	O
day	O
and	O
night	O
.	O

He	O
told	O
me	O
to	O
come	O
later	O
in	O
the	O
night	O
,	O
later	O
in	O
the	O
day	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
calculated	O
on	O
the	O
day	O
that	O
he	O
consulted	O
--	O
what	O
is	O
the	O
name	O
,	O
I	O
don't	O
remember	O
if	O
this	O
is	O
the	O
name	O
--	O
it	O
disappeared	O
again	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
son	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
of	O
Dr.	O
Landau	B-PER
,	O
a	O
famous	O
lawyer	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
is	O
now	O
a	O
famous	O
lawyer	O
in	O
the	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
Ministry	B-ORG
of	I-ORG
Justice	I-ORG
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
his	O
name	O
was	O
Reisner	B-PER
original	O
name	O
.	O

But	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
he	O
used	O
the	O
name	O
--	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
he	O
used	O
another	O
name	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Varshovski	B-PER
.	O
MV	O
:	O
Huh	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Varshovski	B-PER
.	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
Lublein	B-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Varshovski	B-PER
was	O
his	O
name	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
not	O
Varshovski	B-PER
,	O
not	O
Varshovski	B-PER
.	O

I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
the	O
name	O
in	O
a	O
minute	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
anyhow	O
,	O
I	O
came	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
one	O
position	O
free	O
,	O
and	O
that	O
is	O
--	O
you	O
--	O
that	O
is	O
a	O
judicial	O
law	O
counselor	O
,	O
a	O
law	O
counselor	O
,	O
a	O
legal	O
advisor	O
in	O
drafting	O
laws	O
.	O

Each	O
ministry	O
has	O
got	O
a	O
legal	O
advisor	O
.	O

When	O
a	O
statute	O
is	O
being	O
drafted	O
--	O
this	O
means	O
it's	O
going	O
from	O
one	O
minister	O
to	O
the	O
other	O
for	O
a	O
legal	O
opinion	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
,	O
there	O
are	O
special	O
--	O
the	O
lawyer	O
,	O
the	O
specialist	O
is	O
giving	O
his	O
approval	O
or	O
,	O
or	O
he's	O
making	O
correction	O
of	O
,	O
of	O
this	O
draft	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
the	O
position	O
you	O
will	O
get	O
,	O
and	O
that	O
this	O
is	O
the	O
Ministry	B-ORG
,	O
in	O
the	O
Ministry	B-ORG
of	I-ORG
Security	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
for	O
that	O
,	O
and	O
because	O
of	O
that	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
get	O
a	O
flat	O
,	O
which	O
will	O
be	O
guarded	O
day	O
and	O
night	O
.	O

And	O
don't	O
worry	O
,	O
he	O
told	O
me	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
already	O
the	O
local	O
,	O
the	O
local	O
,	O
the	O
Minister	O
,	O
the	O
local	O
security	O
.	O

And	O
Mielec	B-LOC
was	O
already	O
informed	O
to	O
guard	O
your	O
wife	O
day	O
and	O
night	O
until	O
she	O
is	O
coming	O
,	O
until	O
she	O
will	O
come	O
to	O
Lublin	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
how	O
it	O
was	O
.	O

You	O
see	O
,	O
she	O
was	O
guarded	O
.	O

I	O
,	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
.	O

I	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
I	O
took	O
my	O
wife	O
to	O
Lublin	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
that	O
is	O
how	O
I	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
how	O
I	O
started	O
.	O

I	O
started	O
as	O
a	O
legal	O
advisor	O
in	O
charge	O
of	O
drafting	O
laws	O
.	O

As	O
an	O
advisor	O
--	O
giving	O
opinion	O
on	O
drafted	O
laws	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Was	O
this	O
already	O
'45	B-DATE
?	O

MV	O
:	O

No	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
still	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
still	O
'44	B-DATE
.	O

It	O
was	O
still	O
'44	B-DATE
.	O

And	O
in	O
'45	B-DATE
,	O
in	O
December	O
,	O
in	O
December	B-DATE
of	I-DATE
'44	I-DATE
,	O
the	O
offensive	O
started	O
to	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
last	O
push	O
,	O
the	O
last	O
push	O
to	O
Berlin	B-LOC
.	O

The	O
offensive	O
started	O
from	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
Lublin	B-LOC
,	O
which	O
,	O
which	O
occupied	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
from	O
there	O
,	O
the	O
offensive	O
went	O
out	O
to	O
Lublin	B-LOC
.	O

To	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
the	O
offensive	O
went	O
to	O
Berlin	B-LOC
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
I	O
remember	O
that	O
I	O
got	O
a	O
commission	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
called	O
to	O
the	O
Premier's	O
office	O
of	O
Osobka	B-PER
-	I-PER
Morawski	I-PER
.	O

He	O
was	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
the	O
Prime	O
Minister	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
Socialist	O
--	O
PPS	B-ORG
.	O

I	O
was	O
called	O
,	O
they	O
told	O
me	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
we	O
decided	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
the	O
man	O
who	O
will	O
go	O
with	O
the	O
army	O
to	O
ensure	O
that	O
the	O
administration	O
,	O
that	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
new	O
administration	O
should	O
take	O
over	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
life	O
should	O
become	O
normal	O
when	O
the	O
Red	B-ORG
Army	I-ORG
--	O
when	O
the	O
army	O
goes	O
in	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
got	O
a	O
car	O
with	O
the	O
chauffeur	O
.	O

And	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
famous	O
actor	O
--	O
his	O
wife	O
was	O
working	O
in	O
the	O
radio	O
--	O
Lillian	B-PER
.	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
the	O
name	O
anymore	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
came	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
that	O
he	O
has	O
got	O
--	O
he	O
must	O
go	O
with	O
me	O
,	O
because	O
behind	O
him	O
,	O
somewhere	O
in	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
or	O
outside	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
,	O
his	O
seven	O
-	O
year	O
-	O
old	O
daughter	O
is	O
hidden	O
,	O
is	O
in	O
hiding	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

I	O
had	O
to	O
find	O
her	O
.	O

So	O
here	O
,	O
I	O
took	O
--	O
I	O
gave	O
him	O
my	O
military	O
coat	O
.	O

I	O
myself	O
got	O
a	O
military	O
coat	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
went	O
with	O
the	O
army	O
.	O

I	O
had	O
a	O
military	O
coat	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
went	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
Warsaw	B-LOC
.	O

The	O
next	O
day	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
be	O
behind	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
,	O
you	O
shouldn't	O
be	O
worried	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
in	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

But	O
next	O
day	O
,	O
when	O
after	O
the	O
bridge	O
was	O
created	O
over	O
the	O
Vistula	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
December	O
,	O
we	O
saw	O
that	O
the	O
Vistula	B-LOC
--	O
we	O
went	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
,	O
we	O
went	O
along	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
,	O
really	O
,	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
trucks	O
coming	O
up	O
on	O
mines	O
,	O
exploding	O
on	O
mines	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
they	O
called	O
you	O
will	O
be	O
behind	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
be	O
behind	O
the	O
front	O
.	O

Eight	O
hours	O
,	O
it	O
took	O
eight	O
hours	O
until	O
we	O
come	O
to	O
the	O
center	O
of	O
Ostrow	B-LOC
from	O
the	O
bridge	O
,	O
from	O
the	O
bridge	O
.	O

Anyhow	O
,	O
from	O
there	O
we	O
went	O
to	O
Bydgoszcz	B-LOC
.	O

We	O
went	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
first	O
town	O
was	O
Bydgoszcz	B-LOC
,	O
where	O
I	O
came	O
along	O
,	O
and	O
people	O
told	O
me	O
that	O
the	O
,	O
that	O
an	O
Endek	B-PER
,	O
an	O
antisemite	O
,	O
an	O
Endek	B-PER
became	O
,	O
established	O
himself	O
as	O
the	O
mayor	O
of	O
the	O
city	O
.	O

When	O
I	O
had	O
--	O
this	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
what	O
I	O
was	O
told	O
by	O
a	O
PPS	B-ORG
man	O
,	O
by	O
a	O
Socialist	B-ORG
,	O
a	O
Social	B-ORG
Democrat	I-ORG
--	O
came	O
to	O
me	O
.	O

Because	O
my	O
,	O
my	O
job	O
was	O
that	O
the	O
life	O
should	O
be	O
normal	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
,	O
I	O
came	O
,	O
I	O
went	O
immediately	O
to	O
the	O
office	O
of	O
the	O
mayor	O
,	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
--	O
look	O
,	O
pack	O
your	O
things	O
now	O
and	O
go	O
.	O

This	O
man	O
is	O
going	O
to	O
be	O
the	O
mayor	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
put	O
a	O
Socialist	B-ORG
,	O
a	O
Social	B-ORG
Democrat	I-ORG
in	O
his	O
place	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

We'll	O
continue	O
next	O
tape	O
.	O

