INT	O
:	O
Tape	O
22	O
of	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

Mark	B-PER
,	O
would	O
you	O
like	O
to	O
introduce	O
your	O
family	O
,	O
please	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
thanks	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
First	O
the	O
young	O
lady	O
next	O
to	O
you	O
on	O
your	O
left	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
the	O
young	O
lady	O
next	O
to	O
me	O
on	O
my	O
left	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
my	O
wife	O
Frieda	B-PER
.	O

And	O
me	O
her	O
husband	O
,	O
at	O
least	O
until	O
120	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
my	O
grandson	O
Aron	B-PER
.	O

FRIEDA	O
VERSTANDIG	O
:	O
The	O
youngest	O
one	O
MV	O
:	O
The	O
youngest	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
my	O
daughter	O
,	O
Felicity	B-PER
,	O
my	O
David	B-PER
,	O
the	O
grandson	O
.	O

He's	O
the	O
middle	O
one	O
.	O

And	O
behind	O
me	O
is	O
Sydney	B-PER
.	O

He's	O
my	O
son	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
who	O
is	O
your	O
eldest	O
grandchild	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
eldest	O
grandchild	O
,	O
Leah	B-PER
,	O
is	O
at	O
this	O
very	O
moment	O
in	O
Israel	B-LOC
.	O

After	O
the	O
matriculation	O
,	O
she	O
went	O
for	O
a	O
year	O
to	O
Israel	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
the	O
other	O
young	O
lady	O
on	O
your	O
left	O
,	O
behind	O
your	O
wife	O
is	O
Felicity	B-PER
.	O

FELICITY	O
BLOCH	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
introduced	O
already	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
is	O
Felicity	B-PER
.	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
daughter	O
,	O
Felicity	B-PER
.	O

FELICITY	O
BLOCH	O
:	O
INT	O
:	O
Felicity	B-PER
,	O
would	O
you	O
like	O
to	O
say	O
something	O
about	O
how	O
your	O
parents'	O
experiences	O
have	O
shaped	O
your	O
thinking	O
,	O
in	O
particular	O
,	O
the	O
way	O
you	O
helped	O
your	O
dad	O
put	O
his	O
book	O
out	O
.	O

FELICITY	O
BLOCH	O
:	O
Well	O
,	O
I'm	O
glad	O
you	O
gave	O
me	O
an	O
opportunity	O
for	O
a	O
plug	O
.	O

So	O
--	O
--	O
this	O
book	O
is	O
now	O
going	O
to	O
be	O
published	O
next	O
month	O
,	O
again	O
,	O
by	O
Melbourne	B-ORG
University	I-ORG
Press	I-ORG
.	O

And	O
it's	O
been	O
quite	O
a	O
remarkable	O
experience	O
.	O

It	O
came	O
about	O
almost	O
by	O
accident	O
.	O

I	O
really	O
had	O
no	O
sense	O
that	O
this	O
would	O
take	O
the	O
shape	O
it	O
has	O
.	O

But	O
my	O
father	O
began	O
writing	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
manuscript	O
just	O
developed	O
.	O

He	O
wrote	O
it	O
in	O
Yiddish	B-MISC
,	O
again	O
,	O
almost	O
by	O
accident	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
almost	O
a	O
trick	O
to	O
get	O
him	O
to	O
write	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
I	O
found	O
myself	O
in	O
the	O
position	O
of	O
having	O
to	O
translate	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
process	O
of	O
translation	O
was	O
very	O
powerful	O
,	O
because	O
it	O
was	O
so	O
slow	O
.	O

Everything	O
that	O
I	O
read	O
had	O
to	O
be	O
digested	O
and	O
absorbed	O
and	O
pondered	O
to	O
get	O
it	O
right	O
into	O
English	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
that	O
made	O
it	O
sink	O
in	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
felt	O
--	O
I	O
became	O
very	O
much	O
more	O
intimate	O
with	O
my	O
parents	O
.	O

And	O
at	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
,	O
it	O
opened	O
up	O
to	O
me	O
a	O
world	O
that	O
I	O
had	O
known	O
very	O
little	O
about	O
because	O
very	O
little	O
was	O
said	O
about	O
the	O
past	O
and	O
about	O
the	O
families	O
that	O
had	O
disappeared	O
or	O
the	O
way	O
of	O
life	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
wasn't	O
all	O
tragic	O
,	O
either	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
just	O
fascinating	O
to	O
me	O
to	O
learn	O
about	O
the	O
way	O
of	O
life	O
before	O
the	O
war	O
as	O
well	O
as	O
the	O
horrible	O
experiences	O
they	O
had	O
during	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

And	O
almost	O
incidentally	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
,	O
I'm	O
also	O
got	O
a	O
great	O
feeling	O
for	O
the	O
language	O
,	O
which	O
is	O
in	O
the	O
process	O
of	O
disappearing	O
.	O

I	O
felt	O
this	O
is	O
a	O
great	O
treasure	O
of	O
humor	O
and	O
wisdom	O
and	O
a	O
strong	O
expression	O
,	O
which	O
needs	O
,	O
in	O
some	O
way	O
,	O
to	O
get	O
recognition	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
hope	O
that	O
the	O
translation	O
has	O
helped	O
that	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Books	O
such	O
as	O
your	O
father's	O
,	O
of	O
course	O
,	O
are	O
immensely	O
important	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
preserve	O
the	O
experience	O
of	O
a	O
very	O
unfortunate	O
generation	O
,	O
as	O
you	O
might	O
say	O
,	O
or	O
groups	O
of	O
people	O
who	O
went	O
through	O
the	O
Holocaust	B-MISC
,	O
most	O
of	O
whom	O
did	O
not	O
return	O
to	O
tell	O
their	O
tale	O
.	O

Why	O
do	O
you	O
think	O
it's	O
important	O
that	O
your	O
father	O
has	O
written	O
this	O
book	O
and	O
,	O
again	O
,	O
recorded	O
his	O
experiences	O
on	O
film	O
?	O

FELICITY	O
BLOCH	O
:	O
Well	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
,	O
obviously	O
,	O
this	O
--	O
we're	O
going	O
through	O
a	O
very	O
strange	O
period	O
in	O
history	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
period	O
of	O
silence	O
and	O
repression	O
,	O
where	O
very	O
little	O
was	O
said	O
about	O
the	O
past	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
there's	O
this	O
period	O
of	O
remembering	O
,	O
where	O
we	O
are	O
realizing	O
that	O
the	O
last	O
witnesses	O
won't	O
be	O
with	O
us	O
for	O
very	O
long	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
need	O
to	O
know	O
their	O
story	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
kind	O
of	O
a	O
desperate	O
need	O
to	O
know	O
and	O
to	O
find	O
out	O
as	O
much	O
as	O
we	O
can	O
before	O
it's	O
too	O
late	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
have	O
been	O
just	O
overwhelmed	O
by	O
the	O
depth	O
of	O
the	O
response	O
to	O
this	O
book	O
since	O
we've	O
published	O
it	O
,	O
partly	O
from	O
people	O
who	O
have	O
got	O
a	O
stake	O
in	O
it	O
already	O
,	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
community	O
,	O
who	O
feel	O
that	O
their	O
way	O
of	O
life	O
is	O
getting	O
recognition	O
,	O
their	O
stories	O
,	O
somehow	O
,	O
are	O
being	O
mirrored	O
in	O
this	O
.	O

But	O
also	O
from	O
the	O
non-Jewish	B-MISC
community	O
,	O
from	O
people	O
who	O
have	O
approached	O
us	O
,	O
just	O
off	O
the	O
street	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
post	O
office	O
,	O
the	O
people	O
who	O
come	O
up	O
to	O
my	O
father	O
and	O
say	O
they've	O
read	O
this	O
book	O
.	O

They	O
find	O
it	O
absolutely	O
wonderful	O
.	O

They	O
really	O
knew	O
nothing	O
about	O
what	O
happened	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
think	O
part	O
of	O
is	O
that	O
the	O
book	O
is	O
so	O
detailed	O
,	O
that	O
,	O
like	O
a	O
novel	O
,	O
it	O
actually	O
creates	O
a	O
world	O
so	O
that	O
you	O
have	O
almost	O
--	O
it's	O
hard	O
to	O
say	O
it	O
,	O
but	O
it's	O
almost	O
like	O
the	O
pleasure	O
of	O
the	O
old	O
kind	O
of	O
fiction	O
of	O
the	O
19th	B-DATE
century	I-DATE
novel	O
,	O
which	O
creates	O
a	O
world	O
for	O
you	O
that	O
you	O
can	O
live	O
in	O
and	O
experience	O
for	O
yourself	O
.	O

So	O
that's	O
--	O
that's	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
,	O
been	O
part	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
value	O
of	O
the	O
book	O
,	O
the	O
recognition	O
that	O
it's	O
had	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Finally	O
,	O
what	O
have	O
you	O
been	O
able	O
,	O
and	O
what	O
do	O
you	O
think	O
others	O
of	O
your	O
generation	O
can	O
learn	O
from	O
the	O
experiences	O
of	O
those	O
people	O
fortunate	O
enough	O
to	O
survive	O
the	O
Holocaust	B-MISC
?	O

FELICITY	O
BLOCH	O
:	O
Well	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
you	O
take	O
nothing	O
for	O
granted	O
.	O

You	O
don't	O
feel	O
too	O
complacent	O
about	O
living	O
in	O
a	O
country	O
like	O
Australia	B-LOC
.	O

I	O
--	O
we're	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
moment	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
of	O
this	O
'	O
stolen	O
generation	O
'	O
scandal	O
,	O
the	O
story	O
of	O
the	O
aboriginal	O
children	O
who	O
were	O
taken	O
away	O
from	O
their	O
parents	O
to	O
be	O
fostered	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
dumped	O
in	O
institutions	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
brutally	O
treated	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
can't	O
believe	O
that	O
this	O
was	O
going	O
on	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
an	O
adolescent	O
and	O
a	O
student	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
knew	O
nothing	O
about	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
yet	O
in	O
somehow	O
--	O
somehow	O
I'm	O
responsible	O
.	O

I'm	O
part	O
of	O
that	O
society	O
that	O
allowed	O
that	O
to	O
happen	O
.	O

And	O
at	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
terrible	O
refusal	O
to	O
acknowledge	O
the	O
suffering	O
of	O
those	O
people	O
.	O

And	O
,	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
the	O
political	O
repercussions	O
at	O
the	O
moment	O
are	O
causing	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
anguish	O
to	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
people	O
in	O
Australia	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
I	O
think	O
you	O
find	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
Holocaust	B-MISC
survivors	O
are	O
standing	O
up	O
and	O
saying	O
--	O
finding	O
some	O
sort	O
of	O
element	O
of	O
recognition	O
in	O
what's	O
happening	O
--	O
what	O
happened	O
in	O
Australia	B-LOC
,	O
that	O
it's	O
not	O
just	O
something	O
that	O
happened	O
out	O
there	O
in	O
another	O
world	O
.	O

It	O
could	O
happen	O
here	O
.	O

It	O
did	O
happen	O
here	O
.	O

I	O
couldn't	O
believe	O
a	O
story	O
last	O
week	O
,	O
that	O
there	O
were	O
mass	O
graves	O
,	O
in	O
country	O
towns	O
,	O
in	O
Australia	B-LOC
,	O
of	O
children	O
who	O
had	O
been	O
murdered	O
or	O
died	O
of	O
neglect	O
or	O
illness	O
,	O
mass	O
unmarked	O
graves	O
in	O
Australian	B-MISC
institutions	O
in	O
suburbs	O
and	O
country	O
towns	O
.	O

This	O
was	O
just	O
something	O
I	O
thought	O
would	O
have	O
only	O
happened	O
,	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
in	O
some	O
distant	O
past	O
,	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
that	O
you	O
can	O
call	O
the	O
Holocaust	B-MISC
.	O

But	O
it's	O
--	O
it's	O
not	O
something	O
you	O
can	O
ever	O
forget	O
about	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
Who	O
are	O
these	O
people	O
,	O
Mr.	O
Verstandig	B-PER
?	O

MV	O
:	O

On	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
my	O
mother	O
.	O

Her	O
name	O
was	O
--	O
was	O
Gela	B-PER
,	O
Gela	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

On	O
the	O
right	O
is	O
my	O
father	O
,	O
Lajzer	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

The	O
picture	O
is	O
--	O
was	O
made	O
certainly	O
before	O
the	O
turn	O
of	O
the	O
century	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
In	O
which	O
town	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

It	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
Sokolow	B-LOC
.	O

It	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
Who	O
are	O
these	O
three	O
dashing	O
young	O
men	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
on	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
my	O
father	O
.	O

The	O
middle	O
is	O
my	O
father's	O
brother	O
,	O
Adolf	B-PER
.	O

And	O
on	O
the	O
right	O
is	O
his	O
other	O
brother	O
,	O
Leon	B-PER
.	O

My	O
father	O
was	O
the	O
oldest	O
one	O
.	O

Adolf	B-PER
was	O
the	O
youngest	O
one	O
.	O

And	O
Leon	B-PER
was	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
--	O
was	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
between	O
them	O
.	O

This	O
picture	O
was	O
taken	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
.	O

It	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
about	O
1905	B-DATE
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
--	O
'05	B-DATE
or	O
'08	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Before	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
older	O
sister	O
,	O
Gizella	B-PER
.	O

Picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
,	O
before	O
the	O
world	O
war	O
,	O
before	O
the	O
First	B-MISC
World	I-MISC
War	I-MISC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Should	O
I	O
--	O
Yes	O
,	O
and	O
this	O
is	O
my	O
brother	O
,	O
Solomon	B-PER
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
,	O
maybe	O
,	O
in	O
19	O
--	O
during	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
maybe	O
in	O
Bratislava	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
This	O
--	O
this	O
photo	O
is	O
?	O

This	O
photo	O
is	O
your	O
sister	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
my	O
sister	O
Rucha	B-PER
.	O

This	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
in	O
1926	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
OK	O
,	O
thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
You	O
can	O
see	O
the	O
school	O
uniform	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
sister	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
Berta	B-PER
.	O

This	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
in	O
1929	B-DATE
.	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
sister	O
,	O
Sucha	B-PER
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
in	O
1936	B-DATE
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
my	O
family	O
from	O
Sweden	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
the	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
about	O
1923	B-DATE
.	O

On	O
the	O
right	O
side	O
is	O
Paulina	B-PER
,	O
my	O
auntie	O
.	O

And	O
next	O
to	O
her	O
is	O
Gina	B-PER
,	O
her	O
daughter	O
.	O

And	O
to	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
Solomon	B-PER
,	O
the	O
oldest	O
child	O
of	O
my	O
--	O
of	O
this	O
family	O
.	O

We're	O
coming	O
down	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
right	O
is	O
Monish	B-PER
,	O
or	O
Marcus	B-PER
.	O

And	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
is	O
Sigmund	B-PER
.	O

And	O
to	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
Philip	B-PER
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
they	O
and	O
--	O
from	O
all	O
those	O
people	O
,	O
Sigmund	B-PER
is	O
alive	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
Philip	B-PER
is	O
alive	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Who	O
is	O
this	O
group	O
of	O
young	O
people	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
is	O
--	O
I	O
will	O
--	O
I	O
will	O
enumerate	O
them	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
Leah	B-PER
,	O
Leah	B-PER
Ostrow	I-PER
,	O
my	O
cousin	O
.	O

Next	O
to	O
her	O
is	O
my	O
other	O
Solomon	B-PER
.	O

Behind	O
him	O
is	O
myself	O
.	O

To	O
the	O
right	O
is	O
a	O
girl	O
called	O
--	O
I	O
think	O
her	O
name	O
was	O
Mindla	B-PER
Garfunkel	I-PER
.	O

And	O
then	O
there	O
was	O
my	O
sister	O
,	O
Sucha	B-PER
,	O
a	O
friend	O
of	O
the	O
family	O
,	O
Aron	B-PER
Sempler	I-PER
.	O

And	O
to	O
the	O
right	O
is	O
my	O
sister	O
,	O
Rucha	B-PER
.	O

This	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
July	B-DATE
1931	I-DATE
on	O
the	O
lawn	O
in	O
Sadkowa	B-LOC
-	I-LOC
Gora	I-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
the	O
name	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
recall	O
the	O
name	O
of	O
this	O
man	O
on	O
the	O
left	O
.	O

Then	O
there	O
is	O
Ita	B-PER
and	O
Solomon	B-PER
.	O

That's	O
my	O
sister	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
with	O
my	O
brother	O
and	O
Willie	B-PER
,	O
their	O
son	O
.	O

Later	O
,	O
we	O
have	O
got	O
three	O
children	O
.	O

One	O
is	O
Lana	B-PER
,	O
and	O
on	O
the	O
other	O
,	O
on	O
the	O
right	O
-	O
hand	O
side	O
,	O
is	O
Hala	B-PER
.	O

They	O
were	O
the	O
children	O
of	O
my	O
sister	O
Golda	O
Reches	O
and	O
Moshiska	B-PER
.	O

In	O
the	O
middle	O
is	O
Louise	B-PER
,	O
my	O
niece	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
the	O
daughter	O
of	O
my	O
brother	O
Solomon	B-PER
and	O
Ita	B-PER
.	O

Louise	B-PER
is	O
now	O
--	O
lives	O
now	O
in	O
Melbourne	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
that	O
photo	O
was	O
taken	O
in	O
which	O
year	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
photo	O
must	O
be	O
taken	O
in	O
1938	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
brother	O
,	O
Solo	B-PER
and	O
his	O
wife	O
Ita	B-PER
after	O
their	O
wedding	O
in	O
1931	B-DATE
.	O

This	O
is	O
Sabina	B-PER
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
Frieda's	B-PER
older	O
sister	O
,	O
who	O
died	O
of	O
leukemia	O
in	O
1937	B-DATE
.	O

An	O
enlargement	O
from	O
her	O
graduation	O
photo	O
,	O
at	O
the	O
--	O
at	O
the	O
teacher	O
training	O
college	O
,	O
taken	O
in	O
about	O
1921	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
picture	O
--	O
on	O
the	O
left	O
-	O
hand	O
side	O
is	O
Dr.	O
Jacob	B-PER
Schalpeter	I-PER
,	O
and	O
then	O
his	O
wife	O
,	O
Lola	B-PER
,	O
and	O
Dr.	O
Shimon	B-PER
Mala	I-PER
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Krynica	B-LOC
,	O
a	O
Carpathian	B-LOC
resort	O
,	O
taken	O
in	O
1934	B-DATE
,	O
'25	B-DATE
,	O
a	O
year	O
after	O
the	O
Schalpeter's	B-PER
marriage	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
is	O
Frieda's	B-PER
sister	O
,	O
Lola	B-PER
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
a	O
matriculation	O
photo	O
taken	O
in	O
1927	B-DATE
,	O
'28	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
the	O
Mielec	B-LOC
shul	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
13th	B-DATE
September	I-DATE
1939	I-DATE
,	O
many	O
Jews	B-MISC
were	O
burnt	O
alive	O
in	O
this	O
shul	O
.	O

The	O
shul	O
was	O
bulldozed	O
after	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
Mielec	B-LOC
shul	O
after	O
it	O
was	O
burned	O
down	O
.	O

That	O
this	O
Felicity	B-PER
in	O
front	O
of	O
our	O
manor	O
house	O
in	O
Sadkowa	B-LOC
-	I-LOC
Gora	I-LOC
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
taken	O
in	O
1990	B-DATE
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
Mielec's	B-ORG
Gymnasium	I-ORG
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
taken	O
after	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
the	O
Mielec's	B-LOC
courthouse	O
.	O

Mielec's	B-LOC
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
live	O
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
our	O
house	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
our	O
house	O
at	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
,	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
in	O
Mielec	O
,	O
a	O
picture	O
taken	O
after	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
Frieda's	O
--	O
Frieda's	O
house	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
house	O
of	O
Frieda's	O
parents	O
and	O
of	O
her	O
uncle	O
,	O
together	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
our	O
academic	O
house	O
,	O
where	O
we	O
lived	O
where	O
--	O
while	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
student	O
,	O
a	O
Jewish	O
house	O
.	O

During	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
the	O
Germans	O
turned	O
it	O
into	O
a	O
brothel	O
.	O

And	O
today	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
a	O
student	O
--	O
this	O
is	O
--	O
this	O
is	O
a	O
music	O
students'	O
house	O
without	O
any	O
indication	O
that	O
it	O
once	O
belonged	O
to	O
the	O
Jews	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

This	O
is	O
a	O
picture	O
taken	O
during	O
the	O
deportation	O
of	O
the	O
Jews	O
from	O
Mielec	O
.	O

A	O
number	O
of	O
similar	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
pictures	O
,	O
showing	O
the	O
deportation	O
will	O
appear	O
in	O
the	O
next	O
edition	O
of	O
the	O
book	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
And	O
how	O
did	O
you	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O

I	O
Rest	O
My	O
Case	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
how	O
did	O
you	O
obtain	O
these	O
photos	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

These	O
photos	O
were	O
made	O
by	O
a	O
photographer	O
called	O
Jaderny	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
very	O
good	O
photographer	O
,	O
a	O
very	O
nice	O
man	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
had	O
a	O
sense	O
of	O
his	O
--	O
I	O
mean	O
,	O
he	O
--	O
he	O
realized	O
that	O
what	O
he	O
is	O
doing	O
,	O
what	O
--	O
photographing	O
it	O
all	O
will	O
--	O
will	O
--	O
will	O
have	O
the	O
value	O
of	O
documents	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
how	O
did	O
you	O
get	O
these	O
photos	O
later	O
on	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
today	O
the	O
Jaderny	O
--	O
Jaderny	O
museum	O
in	O
Mielec	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
are	O
many	O
pictures	O
of	O
different	O
--	O
from	O
different	O
periods	O
--	O
from	O
different	O
periods	O
,	O
made	O
by	O
him	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
are	O
part	O
--	O
and	O
these	O
pictures	O
are	O
--	O
are	O
displayed	O
over	O
there	O
in	O
this	O
museum	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

This	O
is	O
another	O
picture	O
of	O
the	O
deportation	O
of	O
Jews	O
in	O
Mielec	O
,	O
made	O
by	O
Jaderny	O
.	O

I	O
don't	O
recognized	O
the	O
people	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
a	O
picture	O
of	O
my	O
cousin	O
,	O
Leah	O
Hal	O
and	O
her	O
daughter	O
,	O
Lana	O
.	O

Photo	O
dated	O
Mielec	O
,	O
8	O
October	O
,	O
1942	O
,	O
just	O
before	O
Leah	O
went	O
into	O
hiding	O
.	O

Probably	O
the	O
last	O
time	O
she	O
saw	O
her	O
child	O
.	O

Leah	O
was	O
murdered	O
by	O
Polish	O
Partisans	O
on	O
the	O
31st	O
of	O
May	O
,	O
1944	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
my	O
picture	O
,	O
taken	O
after	O
liberation	O
in	O
August	O
1944	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
when	O
I	O
needed	O
a	O
new	O
identity	O
card	O
after	O
the	O
liberation	O
.	O

And	O
with	O
that	O
picture	O
,	O
I	O
went	O
up	O
to	O
the	O
city	O
council	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
clerk	O
over	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
school	O
friend	O
of	O
mine	O
,	O
a	O
school	O
mate	O
of	O
mine	O
.	O

And	O
when	O
I	O
came	O
up	O
,	O
he	O
asked	O
me	O
who	O
authorized	O
me	O
to	O
take	O
down	O
this	O
band	O
with	O
the	O
--	O
with	O
the	O
Star	O
of	O
David	O
,	O
which	O
we	O
had	O
to	O
wear	O
when	O
--	O
during	O
the	O
German	O
occupation	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
explained	O
to	O
him	O
that	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Germans	O
had	O
no	O
right	O
to	O
issue	O
such	O
a	O
decree	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
against	O
the	O
international	O
law	O
,	O
against	O
the	O
constitution	O
,	O
and	O
that	O
the	O
Germans	O
are	O
no	O
more	O
here	O
.	O

I	O
don't	O
have	O
to	O
wear	O
it	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
said	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
to	O
wear	O
it	O
until	O
our	O
government	O
will	O
see	O
it	O
fit	O
to	O
change	O
the	O
law	O
to	O
allow	O
you	O
not	O
to	O
wear	O
--	O
not	O
to	O
wear	O
this	O
arm	O
band	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
.	O

I	O
didn't	O
come	O
here	O
to	O
listen	O
to	O
your	O
stupid	O
things	O
.	O

Either	O
you	O
give	O
me	O
my	O
identity	O
card	O
,	O
or	O
I'll	O
bring	O
here	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
Soviet	O
officer	O
up	O
.	O

His	O
name	O
is	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

And	O
you'll	O
tell	O
him	O
to	O
put	O
on	O
a	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
put	O
on	O
a	O
Star	O
of	O
David	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
scared	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
gave	O
me	O
the	O
identity	O
card	O
.	O

And	O
in	O
the	O
mean	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
I	O
did	O
him	O
a	O
favor	O
,	O
because	O
if	O
I	O
would	O
have	O
listened	O
to	O
him	O
and	O
put	O
on	O
the	O
band	O
and	O
went	O
down	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
town	O
was	O
swarming	O
with	O
Russian	O
officers	O
and	O
Jewish	O
officers	O
and	O
soldiers	O
,	O
because	O
this	O
was	O
the	O
front	O
line	O
.	O

He	O
would	O
have	O
been	O
in	O
Siberia	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

That	O
shows	O
you	O
only	O
the	O
attitude	O
of	O
the	O
Poles	O
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
this	O
photo	O
shows	O
Cheslow	O
and	O
Batalia	O
Kubick	O
our	O
friends	O
from	O
Polaniec	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
helped	O
us	O
during	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

I	O
wrote	O
about	O
them	O
in	O
my	O
book	O
.	O

Today	O
,	O
they	O
live	O
in	O
Lutsk	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
picture	O
was	O
taken	O
in	O
1950	O
.	O

Stefania	O
and	O
Franciszek	O
Markowski	O
in	O
Chrzastow	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
sheltered	O
us	O
during	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
before	O
the	O
liberation	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
This	O
is	O
Marcin	O
Valas	O
,	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
was	O
leading	O
us	O
from	O
one	O
hiding	O
place	O
to	O
another	O
hiding	O
place	O
,	O
a	O
trusted	O
man	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
Dr.	O

Kasprowicz	O
,	O
the	O
man	O
who	O
risked	O
his	O
life	O
coming	O
through	O
she	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
Frieda	O
after	O
she	O
was	O
wounded	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
examined	O
her	O
.	O

Yeah	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
a	O
photograph	O
of	O
of	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
and	O
Jan	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-ENGLISH	O
]	O
not	O
far	O
from	O
Polaniec	O
.	O

Who	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
they	O
gave	O
us	O
shelter	O
for	O
about	O
three	O
,	O
four	O
months	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
Cheslow	O
Kubick	O
,	O
how	O
he	O
looked	O
in	O
1990	O
.	O

And	O
to	O
the	O
left	O
is	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
the	O
daughter	O
of	O
the	O
family	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
Who	O
provided	O
us	O
with	O
shelter	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
is	O
Kubick	O
,	O
who	O
brought	O
us	O
,	O
in	O
December	O
1943	O
,	O
to	O
the	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
this	O
hiding	O
place	O
.	O

On	O
the	O
left	O
,	O
that's	O
myself	O
.	O

Next	O
to	O
me	O
is	O
Frieda	O
.	O

Then	O
is	O
Louise	O
,	O
the	O
daughter	O
of	O
my	O
brother	O
and	O
his	O
Ita	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
Ita	O
Verstandig	O
,	O
Willie	O
Verstandig	O
,	O
their	O
son	O
,	O
Solo	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
younger	O
brother	O
of	O
Ita	O
,	O
Bernard	O
Foster	O
.	O

The	O
picture	O
was	O
taken	O
in	O
1946	O
before	O
we	O
left	O
Poland	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
a	O
photograph	O
of	O
an	O
ID	O
issued	O
by	O
the	O
Federation	O
of	O
Polish	O
Jewry	O
,	O
in	O
Germany	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
American	O
occupation	O
zone	O
in	O
Germany	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
the	O
publishers	O
of	O
the	O
Ibergang	O
Weekly	O
,	O
where	O
I	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
editors	O
of	O
this	O
paper	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
an	O
ID	O
card	O
issued	O
by	O
Unsere	O
Welt	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
--	O
that	O
was	O
a	O
weekly	O
--	O
a	O
weekly	O
in	O
the	O
German	O
occupation	O
zone	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
was	O
the	O
political	O
editor	O
of	O
this	O
paper	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
the	O
front	O
page	O
of	O
an	O
issue	O
,	O
Ibergang	O
.	O

It's	O
written	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

It	O
means	O
it	O
is	O
a	O
--	O
it	O
is	O
a	O
paper	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	O
Federation	O
in	O
Germany	O
.	O

An	O
article	O
in	O
--	O
signed	O
by	O
me	O
,	O
written	O
by	O
me	O
,	O
for	O
the	O
Ibergang	O
,	O
where	O
I	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
editors	O
.	O

Editor	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
chief	O
was	O
Libhaber	O
,	O
there	O
.	O

Besides	O
this	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
three	O
other	O
editors	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
made	O
the	O
paper	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
weekly	O
paper	O
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
this	O
is	O
a	O
commentary	O
.	O

It's	O
--	O
it's	O
in	O
Yiddish	O
.	O

The	O
Yiddish	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

That	O
is	O
a	O
commentary	O
on	O
the	O
restitution	O
laws	O
in	O
Poland	O
,	O
which	O
I	O
published	O
--	O
which	O
was	O
published	O
by	O
the	O
Federation	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	O
Jewry	O
in	O
Germany	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
who	O
is	O
this	O
handsome	O
young	O
couple	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
made	O
in	O
Germany	O
,	O
1946	O
,	O
showing	O
myself	O
and	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
Frieda	O
.	O

We	O
looked	O
a	O
little	O
younger	O
than	O
today	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

A	O
picture	O
made	O
in	O
1947	O
,	O
showing	O
myself	O
and	O
my	O
wife	O
,	O
Frieda	O
,	O
in	O
Berchtesgaden	O
,	O
not	O
far	O
from	O
Hitler's	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
Hitler's	O
residence	O
when	O
he	O
was	O
still	O
alive	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O

He	O
never	O
expected	O
such	O
guests	O
over	O
there	O
.	O

Picture	O
showing	O
Frieda	O
in	O
the	O
old	O
school	O
in	O
Paris	O
,	O
training	O
as	O
a	O
machinist	O
.	O

The	O
Verstandig	O
family	O
on	O
board	O
the	O
Sylvania	O
,	O
January	O
1952	O
.	O

From	O
left	O
to	O
right	O
,	O
Mark	O
,	O
Frieda	O
,	O
Felicity	O
,	O
Ita	O
,	O
Solo	O
,	O
Louise	O
,	O
and	O
Willie	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
my	O
granddaughter	O
,	O
Leah	O
.	O

She	O
matriculated	O
last	O
--	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
last	O
year	O
,	O
and	O
received	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Premier's	O
award	O
for	O
literature	O
in	O
1996	O
.	O

And	O
she	O
will	O
spend	O
in	O
Israel	O
a	O
year	O
and	O
will	O
be	O
back	O
by	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
1997	O
.	O

