INT	O
:	O
Welcome	O
to	O
sunny	O
Australia	B-LOC
.	O

This	O
is	O
Melbourne	B-LOC
,	O
April	B-DATE
28	I-DATE
,	O
Monday	O
,	O
interview	O
with	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
in	O
English	O
,	O
interviewer	O
,	O
Richard	B-PER
Reisend	I-PER
.	O

Good	O
morning	O
.	O

Could	O
you	O
please	O
tell	O
us	O
your	O
name	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

Good	O
morning	O
.	O

My	O
name	O
is	O
Mark	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
how	O
do	O
you	O
spell	O
your	O
surname	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
V	O
for	O
Victor	O
,	O
E	O
for	O
Elizabeth	O
,	O
R	O
for	O
Robert	O
,	O
S	O
for	O
Sam	O
,	O
T	O
for	O
Tom	O
,	O
A	O
for	O
Andrew	O
,	O
N	O
for	O
Nellie	O
,	O
D	O
for	O
David	O
,	O
I	O
for	O
Ivan	O
,	O
G	O
for	O
George	O
.	O

You	O
are	O
lucky	O
it's	O
not	O
longer	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
very	O
much	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
name	O
of	O
your	O
mother	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
mother's	O
name	O
was	O
Gela	B-PER
,	O
again	O
,	O
Verstandig	B-PER
.	O

My	O
father's	O
name	O
was	O
Verstandig	B-PER
,	O
and	O
my	O
mother's	O
name	O
was	O
Verstandig	B-PER
.	O

They	O
were	O
cousins	O
.	O

Their	O
parents	O
--	O
their	O
fathers	O
were	O
brothers	O
.	O

The	O
brother	O
--	O
the	O
father	O
of	O
my	O
mother	O
was	O
Isaac	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
--	O
Yitzhak	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

And	O
the	O
father	O
of	O
my	O
father	O
,	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
grandfather	O
,	O
was	O
David	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

So	O
they	O
were	O
Verstandigs	B-PER
from	O
both	O
sides	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
your	O
father's	O
first	O
name	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
father's	O
first	O
name	O
was	O
Lajzer	B-PER
,	O
Lajzer	B-PER
Verstandig	I-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
do	O
you	O
remember	O
or	O
know	O
the	O
names	O
of	O
your	O
other	O
grandparents	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
.	O

It's	O
--	O
my	O
grandmother	O
on	O
the	O
maternal	O
side	O
was	O
Lana	B-PER
.	O

And	O
my	O
grandmother	O
on	O
the	O
paternal	O
--	O
on	O
the	O
paternal	O
side	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
the	O
maiden	O
name	O
of	O
your	O
paternal	O
grandmother	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

I	O
think	O
the	O
maiden	O
names	O
of	O
my	O
paternal	O
mother	O
was	O
Gross	B-PER
.	O

But	O
I	O
wouldn't	O
be	O
--	O
I	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
Gross	B-PER
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
your	O
maternal	O
grandmother	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
I	O
don't	O
remember	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

And	O
did	O
you	O
have	O
any	O
brothers	O
and	O
sisters	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
I	O
have	O
--	O
I	O
had	O
one	O
brother	O
,	O
Solomon	B-PER
.	O

And	O
I	O
had	O
five	O
sisters	O
.	O

The	O
oldest	O
is	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

She	O
was	O
called	O
the	O
name	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
after	O
my	O
grandmother	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
--	O
she	O
was	O
the	O
oldest	O
child	O
.	O

Then	O
there	O
was	O
my	O
brother	O
Solomon	B-PER
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
twin	O
--	O
he	O
had	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
twins	O
,	O
but	O
the	O
other	O
did	O
not	O
survive	O
.	O

Then	O
there	O
was	O
my	O
sister	O
Golda	B-PER
.	O

And	O
later	O
sister	O
Sucha	B-PER
or	O
Sarah	B-PER
,	O
Rachel	B-PER
,	O
or	O
Rucha	B-PER
,	O
Berta	B-PER
or	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O

And	O
we	O
were	O
,	O
all	O
together	O
,	O
seven	O
children	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
more	O
children	O
.	O

I	O
looked	O
up	O
once	O
the	O
book	O
in	O
the	O
city	O
council	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
--	O
I	O
think	O
this	O
was	O
the	O
book	O
which	O
kept	O
by	O
a	O
special	O
official	O
who	O
kept	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
old	O
--	O
he	O
kept	O
all	O
kinds	O
of	O
names	O
and	O
people	O
born	O
and	O
died	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
,	O
for	O
--	O
for	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
population	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
there	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
some	O
other	O
children	O
,	O
at	O
least	O
two	O
.	O

And	O
--	O
but	O
they	O
did	O
not	O
survive	O
.	O

They	O
died	O
in	O
childhood	O
or	O
you	O
were	O
--	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
days	O
old	O
when	O
they	O
died	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Of	O
the	O
surviving	O
children	O
in	O
childhood	O
,	O
for	O
historical	O
purposes	O
,	O
could	O
you	O
give	O
us	O
the	O
approximate	O
birth	O
dates	O
,	O
including	O
your	O
own	O
,	O
going	O
from	O
oldest	O
to	O
youngest	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
my	O
older	O
sister	O
was	O
born	O
about	O
1901	B-DATE
.	O

My	O
brother	O
was	O
born	O
in	O
1903	B-DATE
.	O

Golda	B-PER
was	O
born	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
years	O
later	O
,	O
which	O
would	O
have	O
been	O
'	B-DATE
05	I-DATE
,	O
1905	B-DATE
.	O

Sucha	B-PER
,	O
1906	B-DATE
,	O
Rucha	B-PER
,	O
1908	B-DATE
,	O
and	O
Berta	B-PER
or	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
was	O
1910	B-DATE
.	O

And	O
I	O
was	O
in	O
1912	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

Which	O
town	O
did	O
you	O
grow	O
up	O
in	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

I	O
grew	O
up	O
in	O
a	O
town	O
called	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Could	O
you	O
tell	O
us	O
where	O
it	O
was	O
,	O
which	O
part	O
of	O
the	O
country	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
in	O
Galicia	B-LOC
.	O

Officially	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
western	O
part	O
of	O
Galicia	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
it	O
was	O
really	O
the	O
central	O
part	O
of	O
Galicia	B-LOC
because	O
it	O
was	O
halfway	O
between	O
Cracow	B-LOC
and	O
Lwow	B-LOC
or	O
Lemberg	B-LOC
,	O
how	O
it	O
was	O
known	O
in	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
Austrian	B-LOC
--	O
of	O
the	O
Austrian	B-LOC
Empire	I-LOC
,	O
Austro-	B-LOC
Hungarian	I-LOC
Empire	I-LOC
.	O

so	O
Mielec	B-LOC
was	O
just	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
.	O

And	O
consequently	O
,	O
we	O
could	O
officially	O
belong	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
--	O
it	O
would	O
--	O
it	O
would	O
--	O
it	O
would	O
be	O
officially	O
belongs	O
to	O
the	O
western	O
part	O
of	O
Galicia	B-LOC
,	O
whose	O
capital	O
was	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
really	O
it	O
was	O
in	O
the	O
middle	O
.	O

Therefore	O
,	O
we	O
could	O
say	O
it	O
was	O
the	O
central	O
part	O
of	O
Galicia	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
sort	O
of	O
town	O
was	O
it	O
?	O

What	O
was	O
its	O
main	O
activity	O
or	O
industry	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
like	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
time	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
industry	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
a	O
village	O
,	O
about	O
10,000	O
people	O
,	O
about	O
5,000	O
Jews	B-MISC
and	O
about	O
5,000	O
Gentiles	B-MISC
,	O
Poles	B-MISC
--	O
the	O
Gentiles	B-MISC
--	O
Christians	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
mostly	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
industry	O
in	O
that	O
--	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
of	O
my	O
childhood	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
,	O
a	O
very	O
few	O
artisans	O
,	O
tailors	O
,	O
shoemakers	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
few	O
others	O
like	O
cabinetmakers	O
,	O
but	O
no	O
industry	O
as	O
such	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
only	O
people	O
around	O
who	O
were	O
making	O
--	O
who	O
were	O
making	O
--	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
works	O
for	O
the	O
--	O
for	O
--	O
for	O
other	O
--	O
for	O
other	O
people	O
in	O
town	O
,	O
let's	O
say	O
a	O
custom	O
tailor	O
or	O
a	O
cabinetmaker	O
,	O
who	O
was	O
not	O
making	O
for	O
any	O
export	O
or	O
for	O
any	O
--	O
or	O
for	O
any	O
shops	O
,	O
only	O
somebody	O
ordered	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
cupboard	O
or	O
somebody	O
ordered	O
a	O
bedroom	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

It's	O
a	O
local	O
industry	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
no	O
industry	O
in	O
town	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
--	O
people	O
had	O
shops	O
,	O
the	O
shopkeepers	O
.	O

And	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
were	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
villages	O
.	O

I	O
would	O
say	O
with	O
the	O
villages	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
,	O
it	O
would	O
have	O
been	O
about	O
18,000	O
people	O
around	O
or	O
--	O
or	O
even	O
more	O
.	O

And	O
once	O
a	O
week	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
come	O
to	O
town	O
,	O
where	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
buy	O
from	O
the	O
shops	O
whatever	O
they	O
needed	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
some	O
ironmongers	O
.	O

They	O
brought	O
iron	O
for	O
their	O
purposes	O
in	O
the	O
farms	O
.	O

And	O
from	O
our	O
hands	O
,	O
and	O
from	O
people	O
selling	O
cigarettes	O
,	O
they	O
--	O
or	O
tobacco	O
.	O

They	O
bought	O
tobacco	O
.	O

They	O
bought	O
everything	O
in	O
town	O
once	O
a	O
week	O
.	O

So	O
once	O
a	O
week	O
,	O
the	O
town	O
was	O
full	O
.	O

The	O
marketplace	O
,	O
which	O
was	O
the	O
central	O
square	O
,	O
was	O
full	O
of	O
carts	O
and	O
horses	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
farmers	O
,	O
the	O
small	O
farmers	O
,	O
they	O
call	O
them	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
--	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
they	O
call	O
themselves	O
peasants	O
,	O
the	O
Party	O
of	O
Peasants	O
.	O

It's	O
not	O
a	O
derogatory	O
expression	O
,	O
but	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
they	O
called	O
themselves	O
.	O

Here	O
we	O
would	O
say	O
they	O
were	O
small	O
farmers	O
.	O

So	O
they	O
bought	O
all	O
their	O
needs	O
from	O
the	O
shops	O
all	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
.	O

Most	O
of	O
the	O
shops	O
,	O
I	O
would	O
say	O
about	O
80	O
%	O
,	O
90	O
%	O
of	O
the	O
shops	O
were	O
in	O
Jewish	B-MISC
hands	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Which	O
day	O
of	O
the	O
week	O
was	O
this	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
on	O
Thursday	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
the	O
market	O
day	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
what	O
was	O
the	O
main	O
activity	O
or	O
livelihood	O
of	O
the	O
Gentile	B-MISC
population	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
Gentile	B-MISC
population	O
is	O
really	O
is	O
--	O
the	O
Gentile	B-MISC
population	O
,	O
first	O
of	O
all	O
,	O
supplied	O
public	O
servants	O
,	O
the	O
city	O
council	O
and	O
then	O
all	O
other	O
kinds	O
of	O
offices	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
the	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
Polish	B-MISC
-	O
Christian	B-MISC
population	O
were	O
occupying	O
all	O
those	O
--	O
all	O
those	O
posts	O
.	O

Besides	O
this	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
kind	O
of	O
an	O
industry	O
,	O
of	O
an	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
namely	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
people	O
or	O
Poles	B-MISC
who	O
used	O
to	O
buy	O
pigs	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
,	O
around	O
the	O
villages	O
.	O

The	O
pigs	O
were	O
slaughtered	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
exported	O
bacon	O
to	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
that	O
was	O
really	O
--	O
that	O
was	O
really	O
the	O
only	O
industry	O
there	O
.	O

We	O
called	O
them	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
buying	O
pigs	O
,	O
killing	O
them	O
,	O
processing	O
them	O
,	O
and	O
selling	O
,	O
and	O
exporting	O
to	O
--	O
and	O
exporting	O
to	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

By	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
other	O
people	O
,	O
Jews	B-MISC
,	O
who	O
were	O
exporting	O
feathers	O
from	O
from	O
geese	O
,	O
chickens	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
quite	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
people	O
employed	O
.	O

It's	O
called	O
flicking	O
the	O
feathers	O
and	O
cleaning	O
the	O
feathers	O
and	O
exporting	O
them	O
to	O
France	B-LOC
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
well	O
-	O
known	O
family	O
called	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
were	O
quite	O
well	O
off	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
exporters	O
of	O
this	O
kind	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
products	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
there	O
other	O
small	O
farms	O
,	O
except	O
for	O
pig	O
farms	O
,	O
right	O
outside	O
the	O
town	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
There	O
were	O
farms	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
not	O
only	O
pig	O
farm	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
no	O
special	O
pig	O
farms	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

In	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
farms	O
were	O
mixed	O
farms	O
,	O
small	O
--	O
small	O
holdings	O
,	O
very	O
small	O
holdings	O
.	O

No	O
,	O
you	O
mainly	O
found	O
the	O
small	O
farmers	O
,	O
very	O
small	O
holdings	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
had	O
everything	O
and	O
nothing	O
.	O

They	O
had	O
a	O
cow	O
,	O
two	O
cows	O
at	O
the	O
most	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
had	O
the	O
pigsty	O
,	O
where	O
they	O
used	O
--	O
where	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
have	O
--	O
where	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
breed	O
pigs	O
.	O

But	O
besides	O
this	O
--	O
besides	O
this	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
other	O
industry	O
,	O
no	O
other	O
industry	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
or	O
around	O
the	O
villages	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
the	O
main	O
transport	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
?	O

In	O
other	O
words	O
,	O
was	O
there	O
a	O
railway	O
station	O
close	O
by	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

If	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
railway	O
station	O
?	O

Yes	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
railway	O
station	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
railway	O
station	O
about	O
two	O
kilometers	O
away	O
from	O
--	O
about	O
two	O
kilometers	O
away	O
from	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
railway	O
station	O
was	O
built	O
just	O
before	O
the	O
First	B-MISC
World	I-MISC
War	I-MISC
.	O

And	O
the	O
story	O
goes	O
that	O
on	O
--	O
on	O
Sabbath	B-MISC
afternoon	O
,	O
Jews	B-MISC
used	O
to	O
gather	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
and	O
talk	O
politics	O
,	O
talk	O
whatever	O
they	O
like	O
to	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
go	O
the	O
two	O
kilometers	O
to	O
see	O
how	O
the	O
railway	O
is	O
proceeding	O
.	O

Now	O
there	O
was	O
one	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
who	O
was	O
an	O
invalid	O
,	O
a	O
disabled	O
man	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
could	O
not	O
walk	O
the	O
two	O
kilometers	O
.	O

So	O
--	O
and	O
one	O
day	O
,	O
one	O
Saturday	O
,	O
he	O
asked	O
them	O
,	O
tell	O
me	O
.	O

You	O
are	O
going	O
every	O
Saturday	O
to	O
this	O
railway	O
.	O

What	O
is	O
a	O
railway	O
?	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
don't	O
you	O
know	O
what's	O
a	O
railway	O
?	O

It's	O
a	O
big	O
cart	O
.	O

You	O
board	O
the	O
cart	O
in	O
the	O
evening	O
,	O
after	O
the	O
evening	O
prayers	O
.	O

And	O
in	O
the	O
morning	O
,	O
before	O
the	O
morning	O
players	O
,	O
you	O
are	O
in	O
Vienna	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
but	O
what's	O
the	O
hurry	O
?	O

That	O
was	O
the	O
atmosphere	O
in	O
this	O
small	O
town	O
.	O

What	O
is	O
the	O
hurry	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
Vienna	B-LOC
in	O
eight	O
hours	O
or	O
in	O
10	O
hours	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
where	O
does	O
this	O
railway	O
station	O
communicate	O
to	O
?	O

Was	O
it	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O

This	O
railway	O
station	O
took	O
to	O
--	O
went	O
from	O
here	O
.	O

And	O
one	O
side	O
was	O
to	O
the	O
east	O
.	O

It	O
went	O
right	O
to	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
and	O
to	O
Lwow	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
to	O
the	O
west	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
--	O
it	O
--	O
it	O
--	O
it	O
--	O
it	O
took	O
us	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
a	O
town	O
called	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
catch	O
another	O
train	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
because	O
there	O
were	O
other	O
trains	O
going	O
direct	O
Cracow	B-LOC
--	O
Cracow	B-LOC
and	O
Lwow	B-LOC
without	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Were	O
there	O
any	O
such	O
things	O
as	O
buses	O
before	O
the	O
war	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
buses	O
too	O
.	O

But	O
not	O
--	O
not	O
--	O
not	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
child	O
,	O
but	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
adolescent	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
buses	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
buses	O
were	O
taking	O
people	O
mostly	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
to	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
.	O

Tarnow	B-LOC
was	O
a	O
larger	O
town	O
.	O

And	O
people	O
used	O
to	O
travel	O
once	O
a	O
day	O
.	O

The	O
bus	O
took	O
people	O
to	O
Tarnow	B-LOC
and	O
--	O
and	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

It's	O
about	O
40	O
,	O
45	O
kilometers	O
,	O
40	O
,	O
45	O
kilometers	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
bus	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
around	O
the	O
town	O
itself	O
,	O
in	O
its	O
--	O
on	O
area	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Around	O
that	O
town	O
there	O
were	O
no	O
taxis	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
horse	O
carts	O
.	O

And	O
mainly	O
they	O
took	O
people	O
to	O
the	O
railway	O
station	O
.	O

Just	O
before	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
years	O
before	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
the	O
first	O
taxi	O
was	O
introduced	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
son	O
of	O
one	O
of	O
these	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
this	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
owners	O
of	O
such	O
horse	O
carts	O
--	O
his	O
name	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
he	O
bought	O
a	O
taxi	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
first	O
taxi	O
driver	O
.	O

And	O
a	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
also	O
a	O
mechanic	O
--	O
a	O
taxi	O
driver	O
and	O
a	O
mechanic	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
cars	O
,	O
a	O
few	O
motor	O
cars	O
in	O
town	O
.	O

One	O
belonged	O
to	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
who	O
had	O
a	O
flour	O
mill	O
.	O

But	O
the	O
few	O
others	O
were	O
--	O
belonged	O
--	O
belonged	O
to	O
Christians	B-MISC
.	O

There	O
was	O
one	O
,	O
a	O
count	O
,	O
Count	O
Bolski	B-PER
,	O
who	O
had	O
a	O
--	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
had	O
a	O
taxi	O
--	O
who	O
had	O
a	O
car	O
,	O
a	O
motor	O
car	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
fellow	O
who	O
was	O
deaf	O
and	O
dumb	O
and	O
spoke	O
French	B-MISC
and	O
German	B-MISC
fluently	O
through	O
the	O
--	O
through	O
the	O
throat	O
.	O

He	O
didn't	O
need	O
--	O
he	O
did	O
not	O
need	O
a	O
--	O
he	O
did	O
not	O
need	O
a	O
translator	O
when	O
he	O
--	O
when	O
--	O
when	O
he	O
was	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
my	O
client	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Going	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
your	O
early	O
childhood	O
,	O
let's	O
say	O
the	O
early	O
'	B-DATE
20s	I-DATE
,	O
when	O
you	O
just	O
began	O
your	O
schooling	O
,	O
can	O
we	O
just	O
have	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
bit	O
of	O
a	O
picture	O
of	O
the	O
standard	O
of	O
life	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
?	O

So	O
,	O
were	O
there	O
any	O
telephones	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
few	O
telephones	O
.	O

My	O
father	O
had	O
a	O
telephone	O
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
and	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
But	O
were	O
they	O
common	O
for	O
the	O
people	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
big	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
big	O
fixtures	O
on	O
the	O
wall	O
.	O

And	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
--	O
you	O
had	O
--	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
contact	O
the	O
local	O
post	O
office	O
and	O
ask	O
the	O
local	O
post	O
office	O
to	O
connect	O
you	O
with	O
another	O
number	O
in	O
town	O
or	O
with	O
another	O
number	O
in	O
another	O
town	O
.	O

It	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
another	O
,	O
even	O
in	O
town	O
.	O

In	O
town	O
it	O
didn't	O
take	O
long	O
,	O
and	O
you	O
could	O
get	O
a	O
--	O
you	O
could	O
get	O
a	O
connection	O
.	O

But	O
to	O
get	O
--	O
to	O
get	O
a	O
connection	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
it	O
took	O
quite	O
a	O
bit	O
of	O
time	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
about	O
electricity	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

In	O
my	O
time	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
child	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
electricity	O
.	O

But	O
later	O
on	O
,	O
it	O
could	O
--	O
there	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
about	O
,	O
maybe	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
10	O
years	O
old	O
.	O

I	O
think	O
so	O
.	O

An	O
ex--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
Pole	B-MISC
,	O
a	O
Christian	B-MISC
Pole	B-MISC
came	O
back	O
from	O
the	O
United	B-LOC
States	I-LOC
.	O

His	O
name	O
was	O
Romanovsky	B-PER
.	O

And	O
he	O
brought	O
from	O
the	O
United	B-LOC
States	I-LOC
a	O
generator	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
got	O
the	O
license	O
to	O
supply	O
electricity	O
through	O
town	O
.	O

A	O
lot	O
of	O
people	O
he	O
employed	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
went	O
out	O
and	O
,	O
like	O
,	O
put	O
these	O
wires	O
and	O
--	O
not	O
like	O
here	O
though	O
.	O

The	O
wire	O
--	O
like	O
here	O
,	O
but	O
around	O
the	O
houses	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
was	O
waiting	O
for	O
this	O
moment	O
.	O

I	O
remember	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
waiting	O
for	O
this	O
moment	O
when	O
the	O
electricity	O
will	O
--	O
will	O
start	O
--	O
will	O
start	O
working	O
because	O
they	O
had	O
these	O
big	O
lamps	O
in	O
the	O
marketplace	O
.	O

And	O
our	O
house	O
was	O
in	O
the	O
market	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
thought	O
maybe	O
electricity	O
that	O
the	O
--	O
that	O
the	O
light	O
from	O
lamp	O
will	O
be	O
so	O
big	O
,	O
so	O
--	O
it	O
will	O
--	O
so	O
bright	O
.	O

Let's	O
say	O
that	O
we	O
will	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
read	O
a	O
book	O
inside	O
from	O
the	O
light	O
which	O
is	O
going	O
to	O
come	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
the	O
light	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
square	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
my	O
imagination	O
about	O
--	O
about	O
the	O
strengths	O
,	O
about	O
the	O
brightness	O
of	O
the	O
electricity	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
electricity	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
when	O
electricity	O
was	O
introduced	O
in	O
town	O
.	O

Some	O
years	O
later	O
,	O
some	O
years	O
later	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
like	O
a	O
state	O
electricity	O
commission	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
bought	O
out	O
his	O
license	O
.	O

And	O
--	O
but	O
in	O
the	O
villages	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
electricity	O
,	O
only	O
in	O
town	O
,	O
only	O
in	O
the	O
town	O
Mielec	B-LOC
was	O
electricity	O
.	O

But	O
in	O
the	O
villages	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
electricity	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
about	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O
Well	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
kerosene	O
lamps	O
for	O
the	O
night	O
--	O
candles	O
and	O
kerosene	O
lamps	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
gas	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
your	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Was	O
there	O
any	O
gas	O
at	O
all	O
?	O

Was	O
there	O
any	O
gas	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
no	O
,	O
no	O
,	O
no	O
,	O
no	O
gas	O
at	O
all	O
.	O

No	O
gas	O
at	O
all	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
--	O
MV	O
:	O
The	O
gas	O
was	O
in	O
big	O
towns	O
,	O
but	O
not	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
no	O
.	O

No	O
,	O
not	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
not	O
in	O
the	O
villages	O
.	O

I'm	O
not	O
sure	O
if	O
they	O
sells	O
gas	O
even	O
now	O
in	O
the	O
villages	O
.	O

I'm	O
not	O
sure	O
about	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
what	O
about	O
radios	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Radios	O
?	O

Yes	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
radios	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
radios	O
.	O

We	O
had	O
a	O
radio	O
.	O

But	O
not	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
child	O
.	O

That	O
was	O
later	O
.	O

They're	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
going	O
back	O
to	O
that	O
time	O
when	O
you	O
were	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
young	O
boy	O
starting	O
school	O
,	O
what	O
was	O
your	O
impression	O
about	O
the	O
relationships	O
between	O
the	O
Gentiles	B-MISC
and	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
people	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
I	O
had	O
otherwise	O
impression	O
that	O
the	O
relationship	O
was	O
good	O
.	O

Although	O
,	O
my	O
first	O
memories	O
after	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
six	O
-	O
year	O
-	O
old	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
Poland	B-LOC
was	O
established	O
in	O
November	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
pogrom	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
small	O
--	O
the	O
farmers	O
,	O
the	O
peasants	O
came	O
to	O
town	O
and	O
looted	O
.	O

Nobody	O
--	O
we	O
could	O
have	O
--	O
you	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
beaten	O
up	O
.	O

But	O
there	O
was	O
no	O
killing	O
,	O
nothing	O
.	O

I	O
--	O
my	O
impression	O
was	O
that	O
that	O
was	O
the	O
work	O
of	O
agitators	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
people	O
were	O
good	O
people	O
.	O

A	O
Jew	B-MISC
could	O
walk	O
from	O
one	O
--	O
from	O
one	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
of	O
the	O
region	O
to	O
the	O
other	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
were	O
such	O
ones	O
,	O
peddlers	O
.	O

They	O
would	O
bring	O
a	O
few	O
chuks	O
to	O
sell	O
them	O
in	O
town	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
were	O
dressed	O
like	O
you	O
see	O
here	O
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
--	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

No	O
one	O
would	O
do	O
any	O
--	O
would	O
do	O
any	O
harm	O
to	O
them	O
.	O

That	O
relationship	O
was	O
good	O
.	O

Whenever	O
there	O
was	O
something	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
done	O
by	O
agitators	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
people	O
were	O
not	O
intelligent	O
people	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
easy	O
--	O
easy	O
stuff	O
to	O
be	O
incited	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
was	O
that	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
--	O
the	O
relation	O
was	O
very	O
good	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
was	O
your	O
father's	O
profession	O
?	O

Or	O
how	O
did	O
he	O
make	O
his	O
income	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
father	O
,	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
his	O
two	O
brothers	O
,	O
they	O
were	O
entrepreneurs	O
before	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
century	O
.	O

They	O
used	O
to	O
work	O
in	O
Germany	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
they	O
used	O
to	O
contract	O
from	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
Junkers	B-ORG
.	O

You	O
say	O
the	O
Junkers	B-ORG
in	O
--	O
they	O
were	O
this	O
--	O
the	O
feudal	O
lords	O
in	O
Germany	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
were	O
called	O
Junkers	B-ORG
,	O
the	O
rich	O
landowners	O
.	O

They	O
used	O
to	O
contract	O
from	O
them	O
harvesting	O
their	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
their	O
land	O
,	O
their	O
crops	O
.	O

And	O
for	O
that	O
purpose	O
,	O
they	O
organized	O
labor	O
in	O
Galicia	B-LOC
and	O
took	O
them	O
to	O
Germany	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
paid	O
the	O
laborers	O
.	O

And	O
after	O
the	O
harvest	O
,	O
they	O
brought	O
them	O
back	O
.	O

So	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
migrating	O
labor	O
force	O
,	O
which	O
they	O
used	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
--	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
harvest	O
the	O
land	O
owned	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
land	O
--	O
the	O
estates	O
in	O
Germany	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
that	O
is	O
--	O
that	O
was	O
done	O
by	O
my	O
--	O
by	O
my	O
father	O
and	O
his	O
two	O
brothers	O
.	O

Later	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
century	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
20th	O
century	O
,	O
they	O
went	O
to	O
Sweden	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
they	O
went	O
to	O
Sweden	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
over	O
there	O
in	O
a	O
town	O
called	O
Bromolla	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
contacted	O
the	O
production	O
of	O
porcelain	O
,	O
of	O
cutlery	O
,	O
no	O
,	O
crockery	O
,	O
of	O
crockery	O
.	O

Again	O
,	O
they	O
brought	O
,	O
this	O
time	O
they	O
brought	O
the	O
workers	O
from	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

They	O
had	O
to	O
build	O
for	O
them	O
barracks	O
and	O
houses	O
in	O
Bromolla	B-LOC
because	O
they	O
were	O
really	O
people	O
not	O
for	O
a	O
harvesting	O
,	O
but	O
there	O
were	O
permanent	O
workers	O
.	O

They	O
had	O
to	O
build	O
for	O
them	O
houses	O
.	O

They	O
had	O
to	O
bring	O
their	O
families	O
with	O
them	O
because	O
they	O
were	O
staying	O
there	O
.	O

But	O
they	O
were	O
contracted	O
and	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
they	O
were	O
contacting	O
the	O
production	O
.	O

As	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
Bromolla	B-LOC
,	O
the	O
city	B-ORG
council	I-ORG
of	I-ORG
Bromolla	I-ORG
issued	O
--	O
published	O
a	O
--	O
published	O
a	O
book	O
about	O
in	O
the	O
same	O
Bromolla	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
there	O
you	O
could	O
see	O
a	O
picture	O
of	O
the	O
two	O
brothers	O
.	O

I've	O
got	O
--	O
I've	O
got	O
this	O
picture	O
here	O
.	O

If	O
you'll	O
remind	O
me	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
show	O
it	O
to	O
you	O
.	O

I'll	O
find	O
it	O
.	O

So	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
the	O
two	O
brothers	O
since	O
they	O
called	O
them	O
the	O
two	O
--	O
the	O
three	O
brethren	O
,	O
the	O
three	O
brethren	O
Verstandig	B-PER
,	O
who	O
--	O
who	O
built	O
up	O
is	O
industry	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
town	O
of	O
Bromolla	B-LOC
.	O

Now	O
,	O
later	O
,	O
But	O
my	O
father	O
wasn't	O
--	O
my	O
father	O
was	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
only	O
occasionally	O
.	O

The	O
two	O
brothers	O
stayed	O
in	O
Sweden	B-LOC
longer	O
,	O
for	O
almost	O
all	O
the	O
time	O
.	O

And	O
my	O
father	O
built	O
a	O
house	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
came	O
from	O
Sokolov	B-LOC
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
there	O
he	O
built	O
the	O
house	O
,	O
a	O
beautiful	O
house	O
in	O
the	O
main	O
square	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
the	O
only	O
house	O
in	O
town	O
with	O
running	O
water	O
.	O

We	O
had	O
in	O
the	O
courtyard	O
--	O
in	O
the	O
courtyard	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
well	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
three	O
-	O
story	O
.	O

So	O
on	O
top	O
,	O
behind	O
the	O
roof	O
--	O
behind	O
the	O
roof	O
--	O
underneath	O
the	O
roof	O
,	O
was	O
a	O
large	O
water	O
tank	O
.	O

As	O
water	O
was	O
pumped	O
from	O
this	O
well	O
to	O
this	O
tank	O
--	O
and	O
from	O
the	O
tank	O
it	O
was	O
distributed	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
first	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
first	O
floor	O
and	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
and	O
to	O
the	O
ground	O
floor	O
.	O

So	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
two	O
--	O
the	O
only	O
house	O
in	O
Mielic	B-LOC
with	O
running	O
water	O
and	O
with	O
WC	O
,	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
toilets	O
,	O
with	O
modern	O
toilets	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
was	O
that	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
your	O
pardon	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
year	O
did	O
your	O
father	O
build	O
that	O
house	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
father	O
built	O
the	O
house	O
in	O
1903	B-DATE
,	O
because	O
I	O
--	O
I	O
know	O
exactly	O
because	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
little	O
flag	O
on	O
top	O
of	O
the	O
roof	O
,	O
which	O
said	O
1	O
-	O
3	O
--	O
1903	B-DATE
.	O

So	O
that	O
was	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
.	O

We'll	O
continue	O
next	O
tape	O
.	O

