INT	O
:	O
--	O
Verstandig	B-PER
.	O

Yes	O
,	O
we	O
were	O
talking	O
about	O
your	O
departure	O
from	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
in	O
April	O
around	O
about	O
that	O
Pesach	B-MISC
time	O
,	O
1940	B-DATE
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
.	O

I	O
--	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
was	O
a	O
border	O
town	O
between	O
the	O
Soviet	B-LOC
Russia	I-LOC
and	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
.	O

I	O
observed	O
that	O
not	O
far	O
from	O
the	O
station	O
--	O
outside	O
there	O
was	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
an	O
officer	O
working	O
,	O
an	O
officer	O
working	O
outside	O
,	O
was	O
outside	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
Russian	B-MISC
officers	O
and	O
three	O
German	B-MISC
officers	O
.	O

And	O
people	O
were	O
registering	O
there	O
to	O
--	O
people	O
from	O
the	O
army	O
,	O
from	O
the	O
--	O
these	O
invalids	O
and	O
people	O
who	O
were	O
before	O
members	O
of	O
the	O
Polish	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
who	O
had	O
demobilized	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
their	O
units	O
would	O
disappear	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
,	O
that	O
is	O
like	O
they	O
were	O
registering	O
themselves	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
to	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

Some	O
were	O
wearing	O
uniforms	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
remnants	O
of	O
uniforms	O
.	O

Others	O
were	O
in	O
civil	O
clothes	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

So	O
Poles	B-MISC
--	O
going	O
back	O
.	O

I	O
found	O
among	O
the	O
papers	O
,	O
which	O
we	O
took	O
with	O
them	O
a	O
whole	O
--	O
a	O
whole	O
suitcase	O
of	O
different	O
papers	O
,	O
which	O
we	O
--	O
and	O
then	O
we	O
emptied	O
a	O
desk	O
before	O
leaving	O
[	O
NON	O
-ENGLISH	O
]	O
there	O
were	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
papers	O
which	O
belonged	O
to	O
the	O
people	O
employed	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

Among	O
them	O
,	O
I	O
found	O
,	O
I	O
found	O
an	O
identity	O
card	O
without	O
a	O
picture	O
.	O

Most	O
of	O
identity	O
cards	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
were	O
without	O
pictures	O
--	O
only	O
a	O
description	O
--	O
how	O
high	O
you	O
are	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
found	O
,	O
I	O
had	O
it	O
--	O
I	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
some	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
a	O
name	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

The	O
description	O
was	O
similar	O
.	O

The	O
age	O
was	O
similar	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
took	O
this	O
,	O
I	O
decided	O
that	O
I'm	O
going	O
home	O
that	O
way	O
.	O

At	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
,	O
the	O
Russians	B-ORG
advise	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
and	O
Jews	B-MISC
--	O
whoever	O
were	O
--	O
people	O
who	O
came	O
as	O
refugees	O
--	O
that	O
they	O
should	O
either	O
register	O
themselves	O
to	O
accept	O
Soviet	B-MISC
citizenship	O
,	O
or	O
they	O
could	O
register	O
themselves	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
Jews	B-MISC
did	O
not	O
want	O
to	O
accept	O
Soviet	B-MISC
citizenship	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
were	O
afraid	O
they	O
will	O
never	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
war	O
may	O
be	O
finished	O
in	O
a	O
few	O
weeks'	O
time	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
live	O
in	O
France	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
England	B-LOC
.	O

The	O
English	B-ORG
,	O
will	O
start	O
the	O
offensive	O
.	O

The	O
people	O
didn't	O
want	O
to	O
accept	O
their	O
citizenship	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
thought	O
,	O
why	O
should	O
I	O
wait	O
so	O
long	O
here	O
,	O
along	O
here	O
.	O

The	O
best	O
way	O
to	O
go	O
will	O
be	O
I	O
will	O
go	O
as	O
a	O
Polish	B-MISC
soldier	O
or	O
officer	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
I	O
took	O
my	O
,	O
I	O
took	O
,	O
I	O
knew	O
that	O
I	O
will	O
have	O
two	O
suitcases	O
,	O
so	O
I	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
I	O
registered	O
myself	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
that	O
time	O
from	O
a	O
Polish	B-MISC
unit	O
,	O
so	O
and	O
so	O
.	O

I	O
felt	O
if	O
I	O
used	O
the	O
name	O
of	O
--	O
I	O
made	O
sure	O
the	O
types	O
of	O
units	O
was	O
there	O
from	O
a	O
division	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

They	O
didn't	O
make	O
any	O
,	O
they	O
didn't	O
make	O
any	O
fuss	O
.	O

They	O
just	O
put	O
the	O
name	O
on	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
asked	O
me	O
how	O
many	O
pieces	O
of	O
luggage	O
we	O
have	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
four	O
.	O

They	O
gave	O
me	O
four	O
tickets	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
plan	O
how	O
to	O
do	O
it	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
afternoon	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
allowed	O
on	O
the	O
train	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
on	O
the	O
train	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
suddenly	O
I	O
realize	O
that	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
--	O
instead	O
of	O
going	O
west	O
,	O
we	O
are	O
going	O
northwest	O
,	O
north	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
in	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

Wherever	O
it	O
was	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
place	O
like	O
that	O
--	O
I	O
think	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
that	O
they	O
started	O
--	O
Poles	B-MISC
,	O
on	O
the	O
station	O
,	O
when	O
the	O
station	O
stops	O
,	O
they	O
started	O
to	O
shout	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
People	O
who	O
are	O
healthy	O
will	O
go	O
to	O
Germany	B-LOC
for	O
work	O
,	O
will	O
go	O
to	O
Germany	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
then	O
I	O
realized	O
that	O
the	O
doors	O
are	O
locked	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
realize	O
that	O
in	O
the	O
last	O
,	O
in	O
the	O
last	O
carriage	O
were	O
German	B-MISC
soldiers	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
moment	O
the	O
train	O
stopped	O
,	O
they	O
all	O
were	O
down	O
on	O
both	O
sides	O
,	O
watching	O
the	O
train	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
decided	O
that	O
I	O
will	O
have	O
to	O
jump	O
the	O
train	O
.	O

I	O
took	O
three	O
,	O
four	O
tickets	O
--	O
because	O
I	O
decided	O
not	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
with	O
,	O
with	O
two	O
,	O
with	O
two	O
.	O

I	O
said	O
,	O
I	O
decided	O
that	O
before	O
I	O
go	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
will	O
have	O
to	O
give	O
away	O
my	O
two	O
suitcases	O
in	O
somebody	O
else's	O
trust	O
and	O
change	O
the	O
tickets	O
and	O
go	O
down	O
a	O
station	O
before	O
Mielec	B-LOC
or	O
after	O
Mielec	B-LOC
and	O
then	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

Because	O
if	O
I	O
come	O
back	O
with	O
two	O
suitcases	O
,	O
everybody	O
--	O
I	O
mean	O
,	O
it	O
will	O
draw	O
attention	O
that	O
somebody	O
came	O
from	O
that	O
side	O
without	O
,	O
somebody	O
came	O
from	O
that	O
side	O
on	O
a	O
false	O
name	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
befriended	O
a	O
man	O
next	O
to	O
me	O
--	O
he	O
was	O
an	O
invalid	O
,	O
a	O
sergeant	O
,	O
an	O
invalid	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
have	O
to	O
jump	O
train	O
.	O

Here	O
are	O
your	O
two	O
blank	O
tickets	O
.	O

Write	O
out	O
your	O
name	O
,	O
take	O
--	O
take	O
off	O
mine	O
.	O

I	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
from	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
gave	O
me	O
his	O
address	O
.	O

I	O
will	O
come	O
to	O
pick	O
them	O
up	O
.	O

And	O
I've	O
got	O
a	O
dinner	O
jacket	O
,	O
a	O
smoking	O
--	O
a	O
dinner	O
jacket	O
in	O
here	O
.	O

The	O
dinner	O
jacket	O
will	O
be	O
yours	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
pleased	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

But	O
now	O
the	O
question	O
of	O
how	O
--	O
how	O
to	O
do	O
it	O
,	O
because	O
people	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
doors	O
were	O
locked	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
spotted	O
that	O
the	O
south	O
--	O
when	O
I	O
was	O
--	O
but	O
I	O
could	O
move	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
window	O
down	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
spotted	O
that	O
when	O
the	O
train	O
makes	O
--	O
slows	O
down	O
and	O
goes	O
around	O
,	O
it	O
goes	O
not	O
straight	O
,	O
but	O
it	O
has	O
to	O
go	O
,	O
it	O
has	O
to	O
make	O
the	O
curve	O
,	O
pieces	O
of	O
coal	O
were	O
being	O
thrown	O
out	O
from	O
the	O
engine	O
to	O
be	O
collected	O
by	O
somebody	O
.	O

So	O
when	O
the	O
train	O
goes	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
they	O
threw	O
out	O
,	O
the	O
trains	O
from	O
the	O
outside	O
.	O

So	O
that	O
people	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
soldiers	O
from	O
the	O
last	O
,	O
from	O
the	O
last	O
carriage	O
couldn't	O
see	O
it	O
.	O

When	O
it	O
came	O
the	O
other	O
way	O
,	O
they	O
threw	O
out	O
the	O
coals	O
from	O
the	O
other	O
way	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
I	O
decided	O
that	O
when	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
train	O
will	O
slow	O
down	O
,	O
it	O
will	O
be	O
evening	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
jump	O
out	O
then	O
.	O

This	O
is	O
how	O
I	O
did	O
.	O

I	O
jumped	O
out	O
,	O
I	O
walked	O
in	O
the	O
forest	O
.	O

Oh	O
,	O
there	O
was	O
a	O
forest	O
not	O
far	O
from	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
,	O
not	O
far	O
from	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
walked	O
out	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
didn't	O
know	O
whether	O
it	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
or	O
not	O
.	O

I	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

I	O
walked	O
out	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
walked	O
and	O
walked	O
for	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
hours	O
in	O
the	O
dark	O
.	O

I	O
knew	O
that	O
the	O
lights	O
were	O
there	O
.	O

The	O
Germans	B-MISC
--	O
although	O
it	O
was	O
war	O
,	O
but	O
it	O
was	O
far	O
away	O
.	O

You	O
see	O
,	O
the	O
city	O
lights	O
were	O
on	O
.	O

So	O
I	O
walked	O
in	O
the	O
opposite	O
direction	O
.	O

I	O
walked	O
for	O
about	O
an	O
hour	O
,	O
an	O
hour	O
and	O
a	O
half	O
or	O
two	O
hours	O
until	O
I	O
found	O
,	O
I	O
found	O
a	O
little	O
cottage	O
.	O

I	O
knocked	O
the	O
door	O
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
--	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O

It	O
was	O
the	O
common	O
greeting	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
.	O

I	O
told	O
him	O
the	O
truth	O
--	O
that	O
I'm	O
an	O
officer	O
,	O
that	O
I	O
jumped	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
are	O
taking	O
the	O
people	O
to	O
Germany	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
I	O
want	O
to	O
--	O
I	O
want	O
to	O
,	O
I	O
want	O
to	O
sleep	O
here	O
for	O
the	O
night	O
,	O
and	O
I'll	O
go	O
away	O
tomorrow	O
morning	O
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
what	O
I	O
did	O
.	O

He	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
he	O
--	O
he	O
accepted	O
me	O
.	O

He	O
accepted	O
me	O
.	O

We	O
were	O
eating	O
breakfast	O
in	O
the	O
morning	O
--	O
I	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
--	O
he	O
--	O

I	O
could	O
see	O
that	O
he	O
has	O
got	O
a	O
daughter	O
.	O

She	O
was	O
17	O
years	O
old	O
.	O

And	O
she	O
looked	O
--	O
my	O
God	O
,	O
she	O
looked	O
like	O
a	O
typical	O
Pole	B-MISC
--	O
blond	O
and	O
blue	O
eyes	O
,	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
with	O
this	O
face	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
said	O
to	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
I'll	O
tell	O
you	O
something	O
--	O
why	O
don't	O
we	O
take	O
,	O
you	O
have	O
a	O
horse	O
,	O
the	O
cart	O
.	O

Why	O
don't	O
we	O
take	O
this	O
cart	O
and	O
you	O
give	O
me	O
a	O
lift	O
to	O
town	O
.	O

And	O
for	O
money	O
--	O
I	O
had	O
money	O
prepared	O
--	O
and	O
for	O
money	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
have	O
a	O
nice	O
meal	O
and	O
a	O
good	O
time	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
good	O
time	O
,	O
and	O
later	O
,	O
I	O
will	O
go	O
.	O

You'll	O
go	O
back	O
.	O

He	O
says	O
,	O
it's	O
a	O
very	O
good	O
idea	O
.	O

That	O
daughter	O
dressed	O
herself	O
,	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
like	O
for	O
a	O
Sunday	O
outing	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
thought	O
that	O
--	O
how	O
she	O
looks	O
like	O
,	O
it	O
will	O
be	O
the	O
best	O
possible	O
cover	O
for	O
me	O
,	O
that	O
I	O
am	O
in	O
their	O
company	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
How	O
were	O
you	O
dressed	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O

How	O
were	O
you	O
dressed	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Just	O
a	O
--	O
a	O
bit	O
ragged	O
,	O
because	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
I	O
jumped	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
was	O
a	O
little	O
bit	O
--	O
I	O
was	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
But	O
what	O
did	O
you	O
look	O
like	O
?	O

Did	O
you	O
look	O
like	O
an	O
officer	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Oh	O
,	O
yes	O
,	O
oh	O
,	O
yes	O
.	O

I	O
looked	O
like	O
an	O
officer	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
--	O
but	O
I	O
was	O
dressed	O
very	O
--	O
very	O
well	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
tore	O
my	O
jacket	O
.	O

You	O
know	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
fell	O
down	O
--	O
when	O
I	O
fell	O
down	O
at	O
the	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
nice	O
.	O

I	O
--	O
I	O
looked	O
like	O
a	O
peasant	O
.	O

I	O
looked	O
like	O
a	O
peasant	O
boy	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
not	O
an	O
old	O
man	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
.	O

And	O
that	O
--	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
I	O
thought	O
--	O
and	O
I	O
will	O
avoid	O
asking	O
people	O
the	O
way	O
to	O
the	O
station	O
.	O

They	O
took	O
me	O
to	O
the	O
station	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
bought	O
a	O
ticket	O
.	O

I	O
went	O
--	O
I	O
went	O
--	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
get	O
,	O
to	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
--	O
a	O
line	O
from	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
the	O
station	O
before	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
change	O
the	O
trains	O
in	O
Przeclaw	B-LOC
.	O

I	O
went	O
down	O
in	O
Przeclaw	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
I	O
bought	O
a	O
ticket	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
for	O
another	O
train	O
which	O
moved	O
through	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
this	O
train	O
arrived	O
--	O
my	O
train	O
arrived	O
with	O
--	O
but	O
instead	O
of	O
,	O
let	O
us	O
say	O
,	O
20	O
or	O
30	O
carriages	O
,	O
there	O
were	O
maybe	O
four	O
or	O
five	O
carriages	O
,	O
there	O
.	O

I	O
could	O
see	O
this	O
.	O

My	O
--	O
my	O
sergeant	O
--	O
my	O
sergeant	O
,	O
who	O
took	O
my	O
--	O
I	O
could	O
see	O
him	O
in	O
the	O
window	O
--	O
I	O
turned	O
my	O
head	O
that	O
he	O
shouldn't	O
see	O
me	O
,	O
that	O
he	O
shouldn't	O
see	O
me	O
.	O

So	O
that	O
was	O
how	O
I	O
came	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

Then	O
I	O
came	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
came	O
a	O
station	O
before	O
--	O
about	O
--	O
about	O
seven	O
kilometers	O
before	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
came	O
down	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
walked	O
.	O

I	O
knew	O
that	O
I	O
didn't	O
want	O
to	O
take	O
a	O
cart	O
or	O
something	O
like	O
that	O
.	O

I	O
walked	O
around	O
seven	O
kilometers	O
,	O
was	O
how	O
I	O
came	O
to	O
town	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
we	O
decided	O
that	O
the	O
best	O
way	O
will	O
be	O
that	O
I	O
go	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

There	O
are	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
Jews	B-MISC
already	O
coming	O
from	O
smaller	O
towns	O
,	O
concentrating	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
there	O
I	O
will	O
take	O
a	O
ticket	O
.	O

I'll	O
take	O
--	O
I	O
will	O
take	O
over	O
there	O
a	O
document	O
that's	O
registered	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
to	O
go	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
it	O
happened	O
.	O

I	O
went	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
later	O
,	O
went	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

From	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
went	O
by	O
train	O
to	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

From	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
I	O
started	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Why	O
was	O
the	O
registration	O
important	O
in	O
Crakow	B-LOC
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Why	O
was	O
your	O
registration	O
important	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
?	O

MV	O
:	O

Because	O
people	O
--	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
be	O
registered	O
.	O

And	O
people	O
should	O
not	O
know	O
--	O
the	O
people	O
--	O
the	O
--	O
the	O
German	B-MISC
people	O
should	O
not	O
know	O
that	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
from	O
Soviet	B-LOC
Russia	I-LOC
.	O

So	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
bring	O
a	O
document	O
that	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
from	O
Cracow	B-LOC
,	O
because	O
you	O
needed	O
a	O
so	O
-	O
called	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

In	O
order	O
to	O
be	O
accepted	O
,	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
get	O
a	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
,	O
a	O
document	O
from	O
Mielec	B-LOC
that	O
they	O
accept	O
you	O
after	O
you	O
came	O
from	O
Cracow	B-LOC
.	O

So	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
have	O
such	O
a	O
document	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
received	O
such	O
a	O
document	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
--	O
that	O
I	O
lived	O
in	O
Cracow	B-LOC
and	O
I'm	O
going	O
back	O
,	O
and	O
I'm	O
going	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
I	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
--	O
how	O
I	O
start	O
.	O

I	O
mean	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
a	O
small	O
town	O
,	O
and	O
people	O
lived	O
there	O
quite	O
,	O
quite	O
nicely	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
,	O
very	O
good	O
conditions	O
.	O

People	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
closed	O
ghetto	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
open	O
,	O
and	O
people	O
were	O
engaged	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
trade	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
had	O
their	O
shops	O
,	O
like	O
,	O
you	O
see	O
,	O
nothing	O
has	O
changed	O
.	O

The	O
only	O
thing	O
which	O
--	O
which	O
--	O
which	O
was	O
changed	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
you	O
had	O
to	O
wear	O
this	O
white	O
band	O
with	O
a	O
yellow	O
--	O
with	O
--	O
with	O
this	O
Star	B-MISC
of	I-MISC
David	I-MISC
,	O
showing	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Did	O
you	O
wear	O
that	O
band	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
.	O

I	O
wore	O
one	O
.	O

I	O
had	O
to	O
.	O

I	O
wore	O
one	O
.	O

It	O
,	O
it	O
didn't	O
bother	O
me	O
.	O

In	O
the	O
beginning	O
,	O
it	O
didn't	O
bother	O
me	O
.	O

It	O
didn't	O
bother	O
me	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
started	O
working	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
where	O
was	O
the	O
rest	O
of	O
your	O
family	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
Where	O
was	O
the	O
rest	O
of	O
your	O
family	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
rest	O
of	O
my	O
family	O
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
was	O
in	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
,	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
your	O
father	O
was	O
in	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O

My	O
father	O
was	O
in	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
.	O

My	O
mother	O
was	O
--	O
my	O
mother	O
,	O
with	O
the	O
two	O
sisters	O
,	O
were	O
in	O
--	O
my	O
mother	O
and	O
two	O
sisters	O
were	O
in	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
later	O
,	O
and	O
at	O
a	O
later	O
stage	O
,	O
my	O
father	O
went	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
.	O

The	O
reason	O
was	O
my	O
father	O
changed	O
place	O
with	O
my	O
mother	O
.	O

My	O
mother	O
went	O
from	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
--	O
my	O
mother	O
went	O
from	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
to	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
my	O
father	O
went	O
from	O
Przemysl	B-LOC
to	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
there	O
he	O
was	O
with	O
my	O
--	O
with	O
my	O
sister	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
Regina	B-PER
.	O

And	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
my	O
sister	O
in	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
and	O
my	O
brother	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
were	O
considered	O
as	O
Zionists	B-MISC
and	O
as	O
capitalists	O
.	O

Of	O
course	O
,	O
they	O
,	O
they	O
had	O
a	O
factory	O
making	O
roof	O
tiles	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
moment	O
you	O
had	O
a	O
factory	O
,	O
you	O
were	O
a	O
capitalist	O
,	O
so	O
they	O
took	O
away	O
your	O
,	O
your	O
--	O
they	O
took	O
away	O
your	O
factory	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
took	O
away	O
your	O
house	O
and	O
place	O
you	O
in	O
a	O
slum	O
,	O
because	O
you	O
are	O
a	O
capitalist	O
.	O

And	O
so	O
they	O
lived	O
there	O
in	O
a	O
slum	O
.	O

And	O
there	O
later	O
,	O
and	O
my	O
brother	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
started	O
to	O
work	O
as	O
,	O
as	O
a	O
roof	O
tiler	O
.	O

He	O
had	O
to	O
replace	O
roof	O
tiles	O
on	O
--	O
on	O
the	O
roofs	O
.	O

And	O
later	O
,	O
they	O
decided	O
that	O
they	O
would	O
--	O
the	O
moment	O
they	O
got	O
their	O
passports	O
,	O
as	O
workers	O
,	O
they	O
decided	O
to	O
leave	O
the	O
town	O
where	O
they	O
knew	O
,	O
they	O
knew	O
them	O
as	O
capitalists	O
and	O
as	O
Zionists	B-MISC
.	O

So	O
they	O
went	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
,	O
to	O
live	O
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
they	O
took	O
my	O
father	O
with	O
them	O
and	O
--	O
and	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
sister	O
.	O

They	O
took	O
them	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
with	O
them	O
.	O

And	O
it's	O
interesting	O
that	O
my	O
brother	O
,	O
who	O
lives	O
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
didn't	O
know	O
about	O
it	O
--	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
there	O
for	O
a	O
time	O
.	O

But	O
later	O
they	O
--	O
he	O
didn't	O
know	O
that	O
they	O
are	O
there	O
.	O

But	O
later	O
on	O
,	O
it	O
so	O
happened	O
when	O
they	O
were	O
--	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
brother	O
lives	O
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
he	O
didn't	O
know	O
that	O
my	O
father	O
moved	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
,	O
because	O
the	O
father	O
used	O
to	O
be	O
in	O
Wyszatyce	B-LOC
.	O

In	O
the	O
meantime	O
,	O
my	O
brother	O
was	O
arrested	O
with	O
his	O
family	O
and	O
with	O
his	O
father	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
--	O
his	O
whole	O
family	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
registered	O
themselves	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
to	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
so	O
they	O
sent	O
them	O
over	O
to	O
Siberia	B-LOC
.	O

The	O
train	O
was	O
sending	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
learned	O
later	O
that	O
my	O
--	O
my	O
sister	O
came	O
to	O
the	O
train	O
,	O
because	O
it	O
was	O
not	O
like	O
they	O
say	O
,	O
that	O
the	O
Poles	B-MISC
say	O
,	O
that	O
they	O
were	O
transported	O
like	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
to	O
the	O
gas	O
--	O
to	O
the	O
gas	O
houses	O
.	O

It's	O
not	O
true	O
.	O

They	O
were	O
quite	O
comfortable	O
in	O
this	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
--	O
in	O
these	O
carriages	O
.	O

They	O
--	O
each	O
carriage	O
had	O
a	O
stove	O
and	O
had	O
water	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
no	O
--	O
was	O
no	O
problem	O
.	O

They	O
,	O
they	O
traveled	O
the	O
same	O
way	O
as	O
the	O
Russian	B-ORG
army	I-ORG
traveled	O
.	O

But	O
my	O
sister	O
came	O
along	O
and	O
told	O
them	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
you	O
are	O
going	O
to	O
Siberia	B-LOC
.	O

Everybody	O
knows	O
about	O
that	O
.	O

Why	O
don't	O
you	O
leave	O
your	O
children	O
with	O
me	O
?	O

There	O
where	O
Louise	B-PER
,	O
and	O
the	O
boy	O
,	O
Wilhelm	B-PER
.	O

They	O
said	O
,	O
leave	O
the	O
children	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

She	O
--	O
and	O
the	O
girl	O
was	O
4	O
years	O
old	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
boy	O
was	O
8	O
,	O
9	O
years	O
old	O
.	O

She	O
said	O
leave	O
them	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

I'll	O
watch	O
them	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
will	O
--	O
I'll	O
take	O
care	O
of	O
them	O
like	O
my	O
own	O
children	O
.	O

But	O
my	O
sister	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
and	O
my	O
brother	O
said	O
that	O
where	O
we	O
go	O
,	O
our	O
children	O
go	O
with	O
me	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
didn't	O
want	O
to	O
leave	O
the	O
children	O
.	O

That's	O
a	O
dangerous	O
--	O
they	O
go	O
to	O
Siberia	B-LOC
.	O

It	O
gets	O
cold	O
.	O

They	O
said	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
they	O
are	O
going	O
with	O
us	O
.	O

And	O
the	O
fact	O
was	O
that	O
my	O
sister	O
perished	O
with	O
her	O
children	O
,	O
and	O
my	O
brother	O
survived	O
in	O
Soviet	B-LOC
Russia	I-LOC
with	O
,	O
with	O
his	O
children	O
,	O
with	O
his	O
whole	O
family	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
your	O
father	O
was	O
still	O
dressed	O
in	O
the	O
traditional	O
Jewish	B-MISC
way	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Yes	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
no	O
reason	O
in	O
Russia	B-LOC
not	O
to	O
.	O

There	O
were	O
Russians	B-MISC
going	O
with	O
beards	O
.	O

It's	O
how	O
they	O
looked	O
,	O
and	O
so	O
on	O
,	O
the	O
traditional	O
way	O
.	O

And	O
they	O
--	O
they	O
stayed	O
when	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
came	O
.	O

And	O
later	O
,	O
we	O
decided	O
--	O
they	O
wrote	O
us	O
that	O
they	O
would	O
like	O
to	O
come	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

Now	O
,	O
we	O
--	O
through	O
a	O
middleman	O
,	O
we	O
found	O
a	O
German	B-MISC
officer	O
--	O
a	O
German	B-MISC
,	O
not	O
officer	O
,	O
employee	O
--	O
a	O
German	B-MISC
with	O
his	O
own	O
car	O
.	O

And	O
we	O
paid	O
him	O
.	O

He	O
didn't	O
want	O
the	O
money	O
in	O
advance	O
,	O
even	O
.	O

He	O
said	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
bring	O
your	O
father	O
and	O
your	O
sister	O
,	O
you	O
will	O
pay	O
me	O
.	O

He	O
was	O
a	O
very	O
nice	O
man	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
had	O
to	O
go	O
by	O
car	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
to	O
bring	O
two	O
Jews	B-MISC
.	O

And	O
then	O
my	O
father	O
shaved	O
his	O
beard	O
,	O
But	O
he	O
still	O
had	O
a	O
little	O
beard	O
.	O

Shaved	O
him	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
brought	O
him	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
got	O
him	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
he	O
behaved	O
in	O
a	O
--	O
in	O
a	O
--	O
in	O
a	O
--	O
in	O
a	O
way	O
which	O
showed	O
that	O
he	O
had	O
nothing	O
to	O
do	O
with	O
the	O
Hitler	B-PER
regime	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Do	O
you	O
remember	O
his	O
name	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
?	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
his	O
name	O
.	O

I	O
don't	O
remember	O
his	O
name	O
.	O

He	O
behaves	O
in	O
a	O
very	O
--	O
in	O
what	O
--	O
what	O
--	O
was	O
--	O
what	O
--	O
what	O
hit	O
me	O
to	O
start	O
with	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
you	O
don't	O
need	O
to	O
pay	O
me	O
in	O
advance	O
.	O

When	O
I	O
bring	O
your	O
father	O
,	O
you'll	O
pay	O
me	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
What	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
year	O
was	O
this	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
I	O
don't	O
remember	O
.	O

Couldn't	O
--	O
INT	O
:	O
It's	O
1940	B-DATE
.	O

MV	O
:	O
That	O
was	O
definitely	O
in	O
1940	B-DATE
.	O

At	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
19	O
--	O
it	O
could	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
1940	B-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
So	O
this	O
was	O
already	O
a	O
year	O
after	O
the	O
war	O
started	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
no	O
no	O
,	O
no	O
.	O

Just	O
a	O
second	O
.	O

It	O
was	O
not	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
'40	B-DATE
.	O

It	O
was	O
in	O
'41	B-DATE
.	O

It	O
was	O
in	O
'41	B-DATE
,	O
because	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
Germans	B-ORG
were	O
already	O
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
.	O

And	O
this	O
is	O
how	O
he	O
could	O
have	O
traveled	O
to	O
Kowel	B-LOC
,	O
because	O
there	O
were	O
no	O
more	O
Russians	B-ORG
in	O
Kowel	B-LOC
.	O

Was	O
--	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
by	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
1941	B-DATE
.	O

Not	O
by	O
the	O
end	O
,	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
maybe	O
September	B-DATE
,	I-DATE
1941	I-DATE
.	O

INT	O
:	O
So	O
at	O
this	O
stage	O
really	O
,	O
the	O
war	O
had	O
been	O
running	O
for	O
two	O
years	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
Beg	O
pardon	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
The	O
war	O
was	O
going	O
on	O
for	O
two	O
years	O
at	O
this	O
stage	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Yeah	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Did	O
your	O
father	O
still	O
have	O
the	O
same	O
optimistic	O
views	O
about	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
war	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
,	O
I	O
never	O
discussed	O
with	O
him	O
the	O
optimistic	O
views	O
.	O

I	O
never	O
discussed	O
,	O
I	O
never	O
discussed	O
with	O
him	O
the	O
optimistic	O
views	O
.	O

But	O
I	O
don't	O
know	O
what	O
happened	O
to	O
him	O
.	O

But	O
when	O
I	O
ran	O
away	O
,	O
before	O
when	O
even	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
--	O
when	O
there	O
was	O
this	O
talk	O
about	O
something's	O
going	O
to	O
happen	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
and	O
I	O
run	O
away	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
a	O
day	O
before	O
--	O
was	O
on	O
Saturday	O
.	O

And	O
on	O
Sunday	O
--	O
on	O
Sunday	O
morning	O
,	O
the	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
let	O
it	O
be	O
known	O
through	O
the	O
remnants	O
of	O
the	O
--	O
of	O
--	O
through	O
the	O
acting	O
president	O
of	O
the	O
Judenrat	B-ORG
,	O
because	O
the	O
president	O
of	O
Judenrat	B-ORG
went	O
with	O
me	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
ran	O
away	O
with	O
me	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
.	O

He	O
let	O
it	O
be	O
known	O
that	O
they	O
were	O
right	O
--	O
there	O
were	O
something	O
to	O
be	O
happened	O
.	O

But	O
if	O
he	O
--	O
if	O
--	O
if	O
we	O
collect	O
so	O
much	O
and	O
so	O
much	O
money	O
,	O
everything	O
will	O
be	O
OK	O
,	O
like	O
it	O
was	O
before	O
.	O

Well	O
,	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
collected	O
some	O
money	O
.	O

And	O
everybody	O
was	O
--	O
was	O
--	O
was	O
full	O
of	O
joy	O
that	O
everything	O
will	O
be	O
fine	O
.	O

And	O
then	O
it	O
happened	O
that	O
my	O
father	O
came	O
to	O
my	O
wife	O
and	O
told	O
him	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
send	O
somebody	O
quick	O
to	O
Polaniec	B-LOC
that	O
Mark	B-PER
should	O
be	O
back	O
as	O
soon	O
as	O
possible	O
,	O
immediately	O
.	O

Because	O
if	O
not	O
--	O
if	O
it	O
--	O
if	O
it	O
will	O
--	O
if	O
it	O
will	O
be	O
known	O
that	O
he	O
ran	O
away	O
,	O
he	O
may	O
not	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
carry	O
on	O
as	O
a	O
solicitor	O
.	O

I	O
can't	O
understand	O
it	O
.	O

He's	O
tried	O
to	O
convince	O
her	O
that	O
I	O
should	O
come	O
back	O
,	O
because	O
I	O
will	O
--	O
I	O
broke	O
the	O
law	O
running	O
away	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
aware	O
that	O
something	O
happened	O
to	O
his	O
way	O
of	O
thinking	O
--	O
that	O
I	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
,	O
to	O
carry	O
on	O
as	O
a	O
solicitor	O
--	O
but	O
because	O
I	O
broke	O
the	O
law	O
running	O
away	O
,	O
I	O
should	O
come	O
immediately	O
back	O
.	O

No	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
--	O
I'd	O
never	O
had	O
a	O
discussion	O
with	O
him	O
about	O
his	O
optimism	O
,	O
even	O
when	O
he	O
could	O
see	O
what's	O
going	O
on	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
And	O
going	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
was	O
the	O
outbreak	O
of	O
war	O
a	O
surprise	O
for	O
you	O
and	O
your	O
family	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
The	O
outbreak	O
of	O
the	O
war	O
was	O
not	O
a	O
surprise	O
.	O

People	O
knew	O
that	O
something	O
will	O
happen	O
.	O

But	O
people	O
knew	O
at	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
that	O
something	O
could	O
be	O
,	O
that	O
something	O
may	O
happen	O
which	O
will	O
avert	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
said	O
,	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
--	O
we	O
will	O
not	O
give	O
an	O
inch	O
,	O
we	O
will	O
not	O
give	O
a	O
button	O
from	O
a	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
--	O
from	O
a	O
coat	O
.	O

We	O
will	O
not	O
give	O
anything	O
.	O

But	O
maybe	O
there	O
is	O
something	O
there	O
will	O
come	O
.	O

Something	O
will	O
happen	O
to	O
avoid	O
the	O
war	O
,	O
because	O
we	O
didn't	O
believe	O
that	O
Hitler	B-PER
is	O
--	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
is	O
ready	O
for	O
--	O
is	O
ready	O
for	O
a	O
war	O
.	O

So	O
we	O
--	O
we	O
were	O
optimistic	O
that	O
something	O
may	O
--	O
may	O
still	O
happen	O
to	O
avert	O
the	O
war	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
In	O
that	O
period	O
when	O
you	O
came	O
back	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
summer	O
,	O
1940	B-DATE
,	O
what	O
did	O
you	O
do	O
?	O

MV	O
:	O
I	O
was	O
working	O
as	O
a	O
solicitor	O
.	O

And	O
by	O
the	O
way	O
,	O
I	O
must	O
have	O
been	O
the	O
only	O
solicitor	O
in	O
Poland	B-MISC
working	O
openly	O
as	O
a	O
solicitor	O
,	O
because	O
the	O
Justice	B-ORG
Department	I-ORG
,	O
which	O
means	O
the	O
Department	B-ORG
of	I-ORG
Justice	I-ORG
--	O
the	O
Justice	B-ORG
Department	I-ORG
of	O
the	O
Generale	B-LOC
Governement	I-LOC
issued	O
an	O
order	O
that	O
Jews	B-MISC
should	O
not	O
be	O
allowed	O
to	O
practice	O
.	O

And	O
a	O
Polish	B-MISC
solicitor	O
is	O
not	O
allowed	O
to	O
employ	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
,	O
not	O
even	O
as	O
a	O
cleaner	O
.	O

Under	O
no	O
circumstances	O
,	O
should	O
be	O
employed	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
were	O
afraid	O
that	O
under	O
the	O
guise	O
of	O
a	O
cleaner	O
--	O
of	O
a	O
cleaner	O
,	O
of	O
a	O
servant	O
--	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
solicitor	O
,	O
the	O
Jewish	B-MISC
lawyer	O
will	O
be	O
working	O
together	O
with	O
Poles	B-MISC
.	O

So	O
that	O
is	O
when	O
that	O
was	O
known	O
.	O

Therefore	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
came	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
not	O
a	O
single	O
Jewish	B-MISC
solicitor	O
was	O
working	O
--	O
was	O
working	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
--	O
I	O
contacted	O
Antoni	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
,	O
who	O
was	O
a	O
partner	O
of	O
Leon	B-PER
Jacob	I-PER
Selpeter	I-PER
,	O
my	O
brother	O
-	O
in	O
-	O
law	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
was	O
working	O
in	O
his	O
premises	O
.	O

I	O
contacted	O
him	O
if	O
he	O
could	O
give	O
some	O
work	O
to	O
do	O
outside	O
,	O
to	O
--	O
to	O
do	O
illegally	O
,	O
but	O
privately	O
,	O
from	O
my	O
room	O
.	O

And	O
he	O
answered	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
look	O
,	O
Freda	B-PER
Edda	I-PER
,	O
that	O
was	O
,	O
she	O
was	O
a	O
secretary	O
.	O

There	O
was	O
a	O
typist	O
and	O
secretary	O
,	O
she	O
is	O
working	O
in	O
the	O
office	O
,	O
although	O
she	O
is	O
not	O
allowed	O
to	O
,	O
working	O
quite	O
openly	O
.	O

And	O
you	O
come	O
and	O
work	O
quite	O
openly	O
,	O
and	O
not	O
a	O
cock	O
will	O
[	O
NON	O
-	O
ENGLISH	O
]	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
No	O
rooster	O
will	O
crow	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
Huh	O
?	O

INT	O
:	O
No	O
rooster	O
will	O
crow	O
.	O

MV	O
:	O
No	O
rooster	O
will	O
crow	O
.	O

People	O
will	O
think	O
that	O
you	O
are	O
allowed	O
to	O
,	O
that	O
you	O
have	O
got	O
a	O
permit	O
.	O

People	O
don't	O
know	O
.	O

Only	O
solicitors	O
.	O

Only	O
solicitors	O
know	O
that	O
a	O
Jew	B-MISC
is	O
not	O
--	O
is	O
not	O
allowed	O
to	O
work	O
in	O
a	O
solicitor's	O
office	O
.	O

So	O
you	O
come	O
along	O
.	O

When	O
I	O
came	O
along	O
next	O
day	O
--	O
the	O
same	O
day	O
,	O
when	O
I	O
came	O
along	O
,	O
Droba	B-PER
took	O
me	O
to	O
the	O
court	O
.	O

We	O
went	O
to	O
the	O
--	O
we	O
--	O
when	O
--	O
when	O
we	O
entered	O
the	O
court	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
take	O
off	O
this	O
white	O
band	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
took	O
off	O
the	O
white	O
band	O
,	O
and	O
we	O
went	O
in	O
the	O
court	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
was	O
greeted	O
by	O
--	O
this	O
shows	O
you	O
there's	O
antisemitism	O
.	O

I	O
was	O
greeted	O
by	O
the	O
people	O
all	O
around	O
--	O
by	O
the	O
solicitors	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
clerks	O
,	O
by	O
the	O
cleaners	O
,	O
by	O
everybody	O
like	O
a	O
friend	O
.	O

And	O
as	O
a	O
matter	O
of	O
fact	O
,	O
I	O
was	O
introduced	O
to	O
one	O
fellow	O
,	O
a	O
tall	O
,	O
young	O
fellow	O
--	O
Dr.	O
Frank	B-PER
.	O

But	O
he's	O
not	O
,	O
not	O
Frank	B-PER
,	O
the	O
--	O
it	O
was	O
another	O
Frank	B-PER
.	O

He's	O
not	O
,	O
he	O
had	O
nothing	O
to	O
do	O
with	O
the	O
Governor	O
Generale	O
,	O
the	O
,	O
the	O
Generale	B-LOC
Governement	I-LOC
.	O

A	O
doctor	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
a	O
Reich	O
worker	O
working	O
as	O
a	O
solicitor	O
and	O
barrister	O
in	O
Poland	B-LOC
,	O
at	O
that	O
time	O
,	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
.	O

But	O
it	O
so	O
happened	O
that	O
he	O
was	O
the	O
son	O
of	O
Dr.	O
[	O
INAUDIBLE	O
]	O
Frank	B-PER
,	O
a	O
surgeon	O
,	O
residing	O
in	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
who	O
came	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
before	O
the	O
First	B-MISC
World	I-MISC
War	I-MISC
.	O

He	O
was	O
respected	O
by	O
all	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
town	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
was	O
in	O
the	O
best	O
--	O
the	O
best	O
relationship	O
with	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
--	O
the	O
Jews	B-MISC
in	O
town	O
.	O

His	O
son	O
went	O
to	O
school	O
with	O
Antoni	B-PER
Droba	I-PER
.	O

They	O
were	O
school	O
friends	O
.	O

But	O
later	O
he	O
went	O
back	O
to	O
Vienna	B-LOC
to	O
his	O
relatives	O
,	O
where	O
he	O
practiced	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
he	O
married	O
over	O
there	O
and	O
became	O
a	O
Reich	O
worker	O
.	O

Now	O
,	O
he	O
came	O
to	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
because	O
you	O
know	O
,	O
it's	O
much	O
easier	O
for	O
food	O
and	O
for	O
all	O
of	O
those	O
things	O
to	O
be	O
together	O
,	O
to	O
be	O
in	O
a	O
small	O
town	O
like	O
Mielec	B-LOC
,	O
where	O
his	O
father	O
was	O
the	O
mayor	O
.	O

His	O
father	O
was	O
the	O
mayor	O
of	O
the	O
town	O
.	O

So	O
he	O
introduced	O
me	O
to	O
him	O
.	O

Ah	O
,	O
yes	O
,	O
I	O
remember	O
--	O
I	O
went	O
over	O
there	O
,	O
and	O
I	O
had	O
my	O
armband	O
still	O
on	O
.	O

And	O
it	O
was	O
this	O
Dr.	O
Frank	B-PER
that	O
said	O
,	O
take	O
it	O
off	O
.	O

Here	O
,	O
in	O
this	O
court	O
,	O
between	O
us	O
,	O
you	O
are	O
our	O
colleague	O
and	O
our	O
friend	O
.	O

And	O
I	O
don't	O
want	O
to	O
see	O
you	O
with	O
that	O
here	O
.	O

INT	O
:	O
Thank	O
you	O
very	O
much	O
.	O

We'll	O
continue	O
next	O
tape	O
.	O

